<RULE>
      <PREAMB>
        <AGENCY TYPE="N">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
        <SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
        <CFR>27 CFR Part 555</CFR>
        <DEPDOC>[Docket No. ATF 2013R-9F; AG Order No. 3566-2015]</DEPDOC>
        <SUBJECT>Technical Amendments to Regulations; Correction</SUBJECT>
        <AGY>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
          <P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
        </AGY>
        <ACT>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
          <P>Final rule; Correcting amendments.</P>
        </ACT>
        <SUM>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
          <P>The Department of Justice published in the<E T="04">Federal Register</E>of August 11, 2014, a final rule making technical changes to correcting a technical amendment to a definition in the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives regulations related to commerce in explosives. That document inadvertently included an incorrect definition for &#x201C;Customs officer&#x201D; in 27 CFR part 555. This final rule corrects the 2014 amendments by revising the definition.</P>
        </SUM>
        <DATES>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
          <P>This rule is effective October 2, 2015.</P>
        </DATES>
        <FURINF>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
          <P>Shermaine Kenner, Office of Regulatory Affairs, Enforcement Programs and Services, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, U.S. Department of Justice, 99 New York Avenue NE., Washington, DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-7070 (this is not a toll-free number).</P>
        </FURINF>
      </PREAMB>
      <SUPLINF>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
        <P/>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Background</HD>

        <P>The Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) administers regulations published in title 27, chapter II, Code of Federal Regulations (CFR). On August 11, 2014, the Department of Justice (DOJ) published in the<E T="04">Federal Register</E>a final rule that made technical amendments and corrected typographical errors in ATF regulations in the CFR (79 FR 46690). Many of the technical changes were made to reflect changes in nomenclature resulting from the transfer of ATF to DOJ from the Department of the Treasury, pursuant to the Homeland Security Act of 2002. The changes were designed to provide clarity and enhance uniformity throughout these regulations.</P>

        <P>The 2014 technical amendments inadvertently contained an incorrect definition for &#x201C;Customs officer&#x201D; in 27 CFR part 555. This final rule corrects the changes in the Code of Federal Regulations made by the 2014 technical amendments by revising the definition. Section 555.11, defining &#x201C;Customs officer,&#x201D; is being amended so that it no longer contains a reference to &#x201C;Customs Service.&#x201D; The new definition reads as follows: &#x201C;Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.&#x201D;<PRTPAGE P="59581"/>
        </P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">How This Document Complies With the Federal Administrative Requirements for Rulemaking</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Executive Order 12866 and Executive Order 13563</HD>
        <P>This final rule has been drafted and reviewed in accordance with Executive Order 12866, &#x201C;Regulatory Planning and Review,&#x201D; section 1(b), The Principles of Regulation, and Executive Order 13563, &#x201C;Improving Regulation and Regulatory Review,&#x201D; section 1, General Principles of Regulation. This rule is limited to agency organization, management, or personnel matters as described by Executive Order 12866, section 3(d)(3) and, therefore, is not a &#x201C;regulation&#x201D; or &#x201C;rule&#x201D; as defined by that Executive Order.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Executive Order 13132</HD>
        <P>This final rule will not have substantial direct effects on the States, on the relationship between the Federal Government and the States, or on the distribution of power and responsibilities among the various levels of government. Therefore, in accordance with section 6 of Executive Order 13132, &#x201C;Federalism,&#x201D; the Attorney General has determined that this regulation does not have sufficient federalism implications to warrant the preparation of a federalism summary impact statement.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Executive Order 12988</HD>
        <P>This regulation meets the applicable standards set forth in sections 3(a) and 3(b)(2) of Executive Order 12988, &#x201C;Civil Justice Reform.&#x201D;</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Administrative Procedure Act</HD>

        <P>This final rule is purely a matter of agency management. Accordingly, this rule is exempt from the usual requirements of prior notice and comment and a 30-day delay in the effective date.<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 553(a)(2). In addition, prior notice and comment are not required because the final rule is a rule of agency organization, procedure, or practice.<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 553(b). Moreover, the Department finds good cause for exempting the rule from those requirements. Because this final rule makes a technical correction for accuracy and to improve the clarity of the regulations, the Department finds it unnecessary to publish this rule for public notice and comment.<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 553(b). Similarly, because delaying the effective date of this rule would serve no purpose, the Department also finds good cause to make this rule effective upon publication.<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 553(d)(3).</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">E. Regulatory Flexibility Act</HD>

        <P>The Attorney General, in accordance with the Regulatory Flexibility Act, 5 U.S.C. 605(b), has reviewed this rule and, by approving it, certifies that it will not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities because it pertains to personnel and administrative matters affecting the Department. Further, a Regulatory Flexibility Analysis is not required for this final rule because the Department was not required to publish a general notice of proposed rulemaking for this matter.<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 604.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">F. Small Business Regulatory Enforcement Fairness Act of 1996</HD>
        <P>This rule is not a major rule as defined by section 251 of the Small Business Regulatory Enforcement Fairness Act of 1996, 5 U.S.C. 804. This rule will not result in an annual effect on the economy of $100 million or more; a major increase in costs or prices; or significant adverse effects on competition, employment, investment, productivity, innovation, or on the ability of United States-based enterprises to compete with foreign-based enterprises in domestic and export markets.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">G. Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This rule was not preceded by a published notice of proposed rulemaking; will not result in the expenditure by State, local, and tribal governments, in the aggregate, or by the private sector, of $100 million or more in any one year; will not significantly or uniquely affect small governments; and does not contain significant intergovernmental mandates. Therefore, no actions were deemed necessary under the provisions of the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995, 2 U.S.C. 1531-1535.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">H. Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This final rule does not impose any new reporting or recordkeeping requirements under the Paperwork Reduction Act, 44 U.S.C. 3501-3521.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Congressional Review Act</HD>

        <P>This action pertains to agency organization, procedure, or practice, and does not substantially affect the rights or obligations of non-agency parties and, accordingly, is not a &#x201C;rule&#x201D; as that term is used by the Congressional Review Act (Subtitle E of the Small Business Regulatory Enforcement Fairness Act of 1996).<E T="03">See</E>5 U.S.C. 804(3). Therefore, the reporting requirement of 5 U.S.C. 801 does not apply.</P>
        <LSTSUB>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects in 27 CFR Part 555</HD>
          <P>Administrative practice and procedure, Customs duties and inspection, Explosives, Hazardous substances, Imports, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Safety, Security measures, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation, and Warehouses.</P>
        </LSTSUB>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Authority and Issuance</HD>
        <P>Accordingly, for the reasons discussed in the preamble, 27 CFR part 555 is amended as follows:</P>
        <REGTEXT PART="555" TITLE="27">
          <PART>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 555&#x2014;COMMERCE IN EXPLOSIVES</HD>
          </PART>
          <AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 555 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
          <AUTH>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
            <P>18 U.S.C. 847.</P>
          </AUTH>
          
        </REGTEXT>
        <REGTEXT PART="555" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>2. Revise [label:555-11-keyterm(Customs officer)]</AMDPAR>
          <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>&#xA7; 555.11</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
            <STARS/>
            <P>
              <E T="03">Customs officer.</E>Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.</P>
            <STARS/>
          </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SIG>
          <DATED>Dated: September 28, 2015.</DATED>
          <NAME>Loretta E. Lynch,</NAME>
          <TITLE>Attorney General.</TITLE>
        </SIG>
      </SUPLINF>
      <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2015-25190 Filed 10-1-15; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
      <BILCOD>BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
    </RULE>
