<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cfr.xsl"?>
<CFRGRANULE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="CFRMergedXML.xsd">
  <FDSYS>
    <CFRTITLE>40</CFRTITLE>
    <CFRTITLETEXT>Protection of Environment</CFRTITLETEXT>
    <VOL>26</VOL>
    <DATE>2015-07-01</DATE>
    <ORIGINALDATE>2015-07-01</ORIGINALDATE>
    <COVERONLY>false</COVERONLY>
    <TITLE>STANDARDS APPLICABLE TO GENERATORS OF HAZARDOUS WASTE</TITLE>
    <GRANULENUM>262</GRANULENUM>
    <HEADING>PART 262</HEADING>
    <ANCESTORS>
      <PARENT HEADING="Title 40" SEQ="2">Protection of Environment</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="CHAPTER I" SEQ="1">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (CONTINUED)</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="SUBCHAPTER I" SEQ="0">SOLID WASTES (CONTINUED)</PARENT>
    </ANCESTORS>
  </FDSYS>
  <PART>
    <EAR>Pt. 262</EAR>
    <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 262—STANDARDS APPLICABLE TO GENERATORS OF HAZARDOUS WASTE</HD>
    <CONTENTS>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—General</HD>
        <SECHD>Sec.</SECHD>
        <SECTNO>262.10</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Purpose, scope, and applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.11</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Hazardous waste determination.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.12</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>EPA identification numbers.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—The Manifest</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.20</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.21</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Manifest tracking numbers, manifest printing, and obtaining manifests.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.22</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Number of copies.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.23</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of the manifest.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.24</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of the electronic manifest.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.25</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Electronic manifest signatures.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.27</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Waste minimization certification.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Pre-Transport Requirements</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.30</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Packaging.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.31</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Labeling.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.32</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Marking.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.33</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Placarding.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.34</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Accumulation time.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart D—Recordkeeping and Reporting</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.40</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.41</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Biennial report.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.42</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exception reporting.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.43</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional reporting.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.44</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Special requirements for generators of between 100 and 1000 kg/mo.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart E—Exports of Hazardous Waste</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.50</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.51</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.52</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.53</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notification of intent to export.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.54</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Special manifest requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.55</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exception reports.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.56</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Annual reports.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.57</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.58</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>International agreements.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart F—Imports of Hazardous Waste</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.60</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Imports of hazardous waste.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart G—Farmers</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.70</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Farmers.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart H—Transboundary Movements of Hazardous Waste for Recovery Within the OECD</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.80</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.81</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.82</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General conditions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.83</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notification and consent.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.84</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Movement document.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.85</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Contracts.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.86</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Provisions relating to recognized traders.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.87</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Reporting and recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.88</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Pre-approval for U.S. recovery facilities [Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.89</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>OECD waste lists.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart I—New York State Public Utilities</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.90</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Project XL for Public Utilities in New York State.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart J—University Laboratories XL Project—Laboratory Environmental Management Standard</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.100</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what organizations does this subpart apply?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.101</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What is in this subpart?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.102</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What special definitions are included in this subpart?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What is the scope of the laboratory environmental management standard?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.104</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What are the minimum performance criteria?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.105</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What must be included in the laboratory environmental management plan?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.106</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>When must a hazardous waste determination be made?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.107</SECTNO>

        <SUBJECT>Under what circumstances will a university's participation in this environmental management standard pilot be terminated?<PRTPAGE P="352"/>
        </SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>When will this subpart expire?</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart K—Alternative Requirements for Hazardous Waste Determination and Accumulation of Unwanted Material for Laboratories Owned by Eligible Academic Entities</HD>
        <SECTNO>262.200</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions for this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.201</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.202</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>This subpart is optional.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.203</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>How an eligible academic entity indicates it will be subject to the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.204</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>How an eligible academic entity indicates it will withdraw from the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.205</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Summary of the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.206</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Labeling and management standards for containers of unwanted material in the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.207</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Training.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.208</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Removing containers of unwanted material from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.209</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Where and when to make the hazardous waste determination and where to send containers of unwanted material upon removal from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.210</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination in the laboratory before the unwanted material is removed from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.211</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination at an on-site central accumulation area.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.212</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination at an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.213</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Laboratory clean-outs.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.214</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Laboratory management plan.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.215</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Unwanted material that is not solid or hazardous waste.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>262.216</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Non-laboratory hazardous waste generated at an eligible academic entity.</SUBJECT>
        <APP>Appendix to Part 262—Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest and Instructions (EPA Forms 8700-22 and 8700-22A and Their Instructions)</APP>
      </SUBPART>
    </CONTENTS>
    <AUTH>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
      <P>42 U.S.C 6906, 6912, 6922-6925, 6937, and 6938.</P>
    </AUTH>
    <SOURCE>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
      <P>45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, unless otherwise noted.</P>
    </SOURCE>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—General</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.10</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Purpose, scope, and applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) These regulations establish standards for generators of hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>(b) 40 CFR 261.5(c) and (d) must be used to determine the applicability of provisions of this part that are dependent on calculations of the quantity of hazardous waste generated per month.</P>
        <P>(c) A generator who treats, stores, or disposes of hazardous waste on-site must only comply with the following sections of this part with respect to that waste: Section 262.11 for determining whether or not he has a hazardous waste, § 262.12 for obtaining an EPA identification number, § 262.34 for accumulation of hazardous waste, § 262.40 (c) and (d) for recordkeeping, § 262.43 for additional reporting, and if applicable, § 262.70 for farmers.</P>
        <P>(d) Any person who exports or imports wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures to or from the countries listed in § 262.58(a)(1) for recovery must comply with subpart H of this part. A waste is considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures if the waste meets the Federal definition of hazardous waste in 40 CFR 261.3 and is subject to either the Federal RCRA manifesting requirements at 40 CFR part 262, subpart B, the universal waste management standards of 40 CFR part 273, State requirements analogous to 40 CFR part 273, the export requirements in the spent lead-acid battery management standards of 40 CFR part 266, subpart G, or State requirements analogous to the export requirements in 40 CFR part 266, subpart G.</P>
        <P>(e) Any person who imports hazardous waste into the United States must comply with the standards applicable to generators established in this part.</P>
        <P>(f) A farmer who generates waste pesticides which are hazardous waste and who complies with all of the requirements of § 262.70 is not required to comply with other standards in this part or 40 CFR parts 270, 264, 265, 267, or 268 with respect to such pesticides.</P>
        <P>(g) A person who generates a hazardous waste as defined by 40 CFR part 261 is subject to the compliance requirements and penalties prescribed in section 3008 of the Act if he does not comply with the requirements of this part.</P>

        <P>(h) An owner or operator who initiates a shipment of hazardous waste from a treatment, storage, or disposal facility must comply with the generator standards established in this part.<PRTPAGE P="353"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Persons responding to an explosives or munitions emergency in accordance with 40 CFR 264.1(g)(8)(i)(D) or (iv) or 265.1(c)(11)(i)(D) or (iv), and 270.1(c)(3)(i)(D) or (iii) are not required to comply with the standards of this part.</P>
        <P>(j)(1) Universities that are participating in the Laboratory XL project are the University of Massachusetts Boston in Boston, Massachusetts, Boston College in Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts, and the University of Vermont in Burlington, Vermont (“Universities”). The Universities generate laboratory wastes (as defined in § 262.102), some of which will be hazardous wastes. As long as the Universities comply with all the requirements of subpart J of this part the Universities' laboratories that are participating in the University Laboratories XL Project as identified in Table 1 of this section, are not subject to the provisions of §§ 262.11, 262.34(c), 40 CFR parts 264 and 265, 267, and the permit requirements of 40 CFR part 270 with respect to said laboratory wastes.</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s75,8,r100,r100" COLS="4" OPTS="L2">
          <TTITLE>Table 1—Laboratory XL Project Participant Information</TTITLE>
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">Institution</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Approx. number of labs</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Departments participating</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Location of current hazardous waste accumulation areas</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Boston College, Chestnut Hill, MA</ENT>
            <ENT>120</ENT>
            <ENT>Chemistry, Biology, Geology, Physics, Psychology</ENT>
            <ENT>Merkert Chemistry Building, 2609 Beacon St., Boston, MA, Higgins Building, 140 Commonwealth Ave., Chestnut Hill, MA.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">University of Massachusetts Boston, Boston, MA</ENT>
            <ENT>150</ENT>
            <ENT>Chemistry, Biology, Psychology, Anthropology, Geology and Earth Sciences, and Environmental, Coastal and Ocean Sciences</ENT>
            <ENT>Science Building (Bldg. #080); McCormack Building (Bldg. #020); and Wheatley Building (Bldg. #010), 100 Morrissey Blvd., Boston, MA.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">University of Vermont, Burlington, VT</ENT>
            <ENT>400</ENT>
            <ENT>Colleges of: Agriculture and Life Sciences, Arts and Sciences, Medicine, and Engineering and Mathematics; and Schools of: Nursing, Allied Heath Sciences, and Natural Resources</ENT>
            <ENT>Given Bunker, 89 Beaumont Ave., Burlington, VT.</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>

        <P>(2) Each University shall have the right to change its respective departments or the on-site location of its hazardous waste accumulation areas listed in Table 1 of this section upon written notice to the Regional Administrator for EPA-Region I and the appropriate state agency. Such written notice will be provided at least ten days prior to the effective date of any such changes.
        </P>
        <P>(k) Generators in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts may comply with the State regulations regarding Class A recyclable materials in 310 C.M.R. 30.200, when authorized by the EPA under 40 CFR part 271, with respect to those recyclable materials and matters covered by the authorization, instead of complying with the hazardous waste accumulation requirements of § 262.34, the reporting requirements of § 262.41, the storage facility operator requirements of 40 CFR parts 264, 265 and 267, and the permitting requirements of 40 CFR part 270. Such generators must also comply with any other applicable requirements, including any applicable authorized State regulations governing hazardous wastes not being recycled and any applicable Federal requirements which are being directly implemented by the EPA within Massachusetts pursuant to the Hazardous and Solid Waste Amendments of 1984.</P>
        <P>(l) The laboratories owned by an eligible academic entity that chooses to be subject to the requirements of Subpart K of this part are not subject to (for purposes of this paragraph, the terms “laboratory” and “eligible academic entity” shall have the meaning as defined in § 262.200 of Subpart K of this part).:</P>
        <P>(1) The requirements of § 262.11 or § 262.34(c), for large quantity generators and small quantity generators, except as provided in Subpart K, and</P>

        <P>(2) The conditions of § 261.5(b), for conditionally exempt small quantity generators, except as provided in Subpart K.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <PRTPAGE P="354"/>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note 1:</HD>
          <P>The provisions of § 262.34 are applicable to the on-site accumulation of hazardous waste by generators. Therefore, the provisions of § 262.34 only apply to owners or operators who are shipping hazardous waste which they generated at that facility.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note 2:</HD>
          <P>A generator who treats, stores, or disposes of hazardous waste on-site must comply with the applicable standards and permit requirements set forth in 40 CFR parts 264, 265, 266, 268, and 270.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 45 FR 86970, Dec. 31, 1980; 47 FR 1251, Jan. 11, 1982; 48 FR 14294, Apr. 1, 1983; 53 FR 27164, July 19, 1988; 56 FR 3877, Jan. 31, 1991; 60 FR 25541, May 11, 1995; 61 FR 16309, Apr. 12, 1996; 62 FR 6651, Feb. 12, 1997; 64 FR 52392, Sept. 28, 1999; 69 FR 11813, Mar. 12, 2004; 73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008; 75 FR 13003, Mar. 18, 2010; 75 FR 1253, Jan. 8, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.11</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Hazardous waste determination.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A person who generates a solid waste, as defined in 40 CFR 261.2, must determine if that waste is a hazardous waste using the following method:</P>
        <P>(a) He should first determine if the waste is excluded from regulation under 40 CFR 261.4.</P>

        <P>(b) He must then determine if the waste is listed as a hazardous waste in subpart D of 40 CFR part 261.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>Even if the waste is listed, the generator still has an opportunity under 40 CFR 260.22 to demonstrate to the Administrator that the waste from his particular facility or operation is not a hazardous waste.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(c) For purposes of compliance with 40 CFR part 268, or if the waste is not listed in subpart D of 40 CFR part 261, the generator must then determine whether the waste is identified in subpart C of 40 CFR part 261 by either:</P>
        <P>(1) Testing the waste according to the methods set forth in subpart C of 40 CFR part 261, or according to an equivalent method approved by the Administrator under 40 CFR 260.21; or</P>
        <P>(2) Applying knowledge of the hazard characteristic of the waste in light of the materials or the processes used.</P>
        <P>(d) If the waste is determined to be hazardous, the generator must refer to parts 261, 264, 265, 266, 267, 268, and 273 of this chapter for possible exclusions or restrictions pertaining to management of the specific waste.</P>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 45 FR 76624, Nov. 19, 1980; 51 FR 40637, Nov. 7, 1986; 55 FR 22684, June 1, 1990; 56 FR 3877, Jan. 31, 1991; 60 FR 25541, May 11, 1995; 75 FR 13004, Mar. 18, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.12</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>EPA identification numbers.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) A generator must not treat, store, dispose of, transport, or offer for transportation, hazardous waste without having received an EPA identification number from the Administrator.</P>
        <P>(b) A generator who has not received an EPA identification number may obtain one by applying to the Administrator using EPA form 8700-12. Upon receiving the request the Administrator will assign an EPA identification number to the generator.</P>
        <P>(c) A generator must not offer his hazardous waste to transporters or to treatment, storage, or disposal facilities that have not received an EPA identification number.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—The Manifest</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.20</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) A generator who transports, or offers for transport a hazardous waste for offsite treatment, storage, or disposal, or a treatment, storage, and disposal facility who offers for transport a rejected hazardous waste load, must prepare a Manifest (OMB Control number 2050-0039) on EPA Form 8700-22, and, if necessary, EPA Form 8700-22A, according to the instructions included in the appendix to this part.</P>
        <P>(2) The revised manifest form and procedures in 40 CFR 260.10, 261.7, 262.20, 262.21, 262.27, 262.32, 262.34, 262.54, 262.60, and the appendix to part 262, shall not apply until September 5, 2006. The manifest form and procedures in 40 CFR 260.10, 261.7, 262.20, 262.21, 262.32, 262.34, 262.54, 262.60, and the appendix to part 262, contained in the 40 CFR, parts 260 to 265, edition revised as of July 1, 2004, shall be applicable until September 5, 2006.</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Electronic manifest.</E> In lieu of using the manifest form specified in paragraph (a)(1) of this section, a person required to prepare a manifest under paragraph (a)(1) of this section may <PRTPAGE P="355"/>prepare and use an electronic manifest, provided that the person:</P>
        <P>(i) Complies with the requirements in § 262.24 for use of electronic manifests, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Complies with the requirements of 40 CFR 3.10 for the reporting of electronic documents to EPA.</P>
        <P>(b) A generator must designate on the manifest one facility which is permitted to handle the waste described on the manifest.</P>
        <P>(c) A generator may also designate on the manifest one alternate facility which is permitted to handle his waste in the event an emergency prevents delivery of the waste to the primary designated facility.</P>
        <P>(d) If the transporter is unable to deliver the hazardous waste to the designated facility or the alternate facility, the generator must either designate another facility or instruct the transporter to return the waste.</P>
        <P>(e) The requirements of this subpart do not apply to hazardous waste produced by generators of greater than 100 kg but less than 1000 kg in a calendar month where:</P>
        <P>(1) The waste is reclaimed under a contractual agreement pursuant to which:</P>
        <P>(i) The type of waste and frequency of shipments are specified in the agreement;</P>
        <P>(ii) The vehicle used to transport the waste to the recycling facility and to deliver regenerated material back to the generator is owned and operated by the reclaimer of the waste; and</P>
        <P>(2) The generator maintains a copy of the reclamation agreement in his files for a period of at least three years after termination or expiration of the agreement.</P>
        <P>(f) The requirements of this subpart and § 262.32(b) do not apply to the transport of hazardous wastes on a public or private right-of-way within or along the border of contiguous property under the control of the same person, even if such contiguous property is divided by a public or private right-of-way. Notwithstanding 40 CFR 263.10(a), the generator or transporter must comply with the requirements for transporters set forth in 40 CFR 263.30 and 263.31 in the event of a discharge of hazardous waste on a public or private right-of-way.</P>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 49 FR 10500, Mar. 20, 1984; 51 FR 10175, Mar. 24, 1986; 53 FR 45090, Nov. 8, 1988; 62 FR 6651, Feb. 12, 1997; 70 FR 10815, Mar. 4, 2005; 70 FR 35037, June 16, 2005; 79 FR 7558, Feb. 7, 2014]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.21</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Manifest tracking numbers, manifest printing, and obtaining manifests.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) A registrant may not print, or have printed, the manifest for use of distribution unless it has received approval from the EPA Director of the Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery to do so under paragraphs (c) and (e) of this section.</P>
        <P>(2) The approved registrant is responsible for ensuring that the organizations identified in its application are in compliance with the procedures of its approved application and the requirements of this section. The registrant is responsible for assigning manifest tracking numbers to its manifests.</P>
        <P>(b) A registrant must submit an initial application to the EPA Director of the Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery that contains the following information:</P>
        <P>(1) Name and mailing address of registrant;</P>
        <P>(2) Name, telephone number and email address of contact person;</P>
        <P>(3) Brief description of registrant's government or business activity;</P>
        <P>(4) EPA identification number of the registrant, if applicable;</P>
        <P>(5) Description of the scope of the operations that the registrant plans to undertake in printing, distributing, and using its manifests, including:</P>

        <P>(i) A description of the printing operation. The description should include an explanation of whether the registrant intends to print its manifests in-house (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, using its own printing establishments) or through a separate (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, unaffiliated) printing company. If the registrant intends to use a separate printing company to print the manifest on its behalf, the application must identify this printing company and discuss how the registrant will oversee the company. If this includes the use of intermediaries (e.g., prime and subcontractor relationships), the role of each must be discussed. The application <PRTPAGE P="356"/>must provide the name and mailing address of each company. It also must provide the name and telephone number of the contact person at each company.</P>
        <P>(ii) A description of how the registrant will ensure that its organization and unaffiliated companies, if any, comply with the requirements of this section. The application must discuss how the registrant will ensure that a unique manifest tracking number will be pre-printed on each manifest. The application must describe the internal control procedures to be followed by the registrant and unaffiliated companies to ensure that numbers are tightly controlled and remain unique. In particular, the application must describe how the registrant will assign manifest tracking numbers to its manifests. If computer systems or other infrastructure will be used to maintain, track, or assign numbers, these should be indicated. The application must also indicate how the printer will pre-print a unique number on each form (e.g., crash or press numbering). The application also must explain the other quality procedures to be followed by each establishment and printing company to ensure that all required print specifications are consistently achieved and that printing violations are identified and corrected at the earliest practicable time.</P>
        <P>(iii) An indication of whether the registrant intends to use the manifests for its own business operations or to distribute the manifests to a separate company or to the general public (e.g., for purchase).</P>
        <P>(6) A brief description of the qualifications of the company that will print the manifest. The registrant may use readily available information to do so (e.g., corporate brochures, product samples, customer references, documentation of ISO certification), so long as such information pertains to the establishments or company being proposed to print the manifest.</P>
        <P>(7) Proposed unique three-letter manifest tracking number suffix. If the registrant is approved to print the manifest, the registrant must use this suffix to pre-print a unique manifest tracking number on each manifest.</P>
        <P>(8) A signed certification by a duly authorized employee of the registrant that the organizations and companies in its application will comply with the procedures of its approved application and the requirements of this section and that it will notify the EPA Director of the Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery of any duplicated manifest tracking numbers on manifests that have been used or distributed to other parties as soon as this becomes known.</P>
        <P>(c) EPA will review the application submitted under paragraph (b) of this section and either approve it or request additional information or modification before approving it.</P>
        <P>(d)(1) Upon EPA approval of the application under paragraph (c) of this section, EPA will provide the registrant an electronic file of the manifest, continuation sheet, and manifest instructions and ask the registrant to submit three fully assembled manifests and continuation sheet samples, except as noted in paragraph (d)(3) of this section. The registrant's samples must meet all of the specifications in paragraph (f) of this section and be printed by the company that will print the manifest as identified in the application approved under paragraph (c) of this section.</P>
        <P>(2) The registrant must submit a description of the manifest samples as follows:</P>
        <P>(i) Paper type (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, manufacturer and grade of the manifest paper);</P>
        <P>(ii) Paper weight of each copy;</P>
        <P>(iii) Ink color of the manifest's instructions. If screening of the ink was used, the registrant must indicate the extent of the screening; and</P>
        <P>(iv) Method of binding the copies.</P>
        <P>(3) The registrant need not submit samples of the continuation sheet if it will print its continuation sheet using the same paper type, paper weight of each copy, ink color of the instructions, and binding method as its manifest form samples.</P>

        <P>(e) EPA will evaluate the forms and either approve the registrant to print them as proposed or request additional information or modification to them before approval. EPA will notify the registrant of its decision by mail. The registrant cannot use or distribute its <PRTPAGE P="357"/>forms until EPA approves them. An approved registrant must print the manifest and continuation sheet according to its application approved under paragraph (c) of this section and the manifest specifications in paragraph (f) of this section. It also must print the forms according to the paper type, paper weight, ink color of the manifest instructions and binding method of its approved forms.</P>
        <P>(f) Paper manifests and continuation sheets must be printed according to the following specifications:</P>
        <P>(1) The manifest and continuation sheet must be printed with the exact format and appearance as EPA Forms 8700-22 and 8700-22A, respectively. However, information required to complete the manifest may be pre-printed on the manifest form.</P>
        <P>(2) A unique manifest tracking number assigned in accordance with a numbering system approved by EPA must be pre-printed in Item 4 of the manifest. The tracking number must consist of a unique three-letter suffix following nine digits.</P>
        <P>(3) The manifest and continuation sheet must be printed on 8<FR>1/2</FR> × 11-inch white paper, excluding common stubs (e.g., top- or side-bound stubs). The paper must be durable enough to withstand normal use.</P>

        <P>(4) The manifest and continuation sheet must be printed in black ink that can be legibly photocopied, scanned, or faxed, except that the marginal words indicating copy distribution must be printed with a distinct ink color or with another method (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> white text against black background in text box, or, black text against grey background in text box) that clearly distinguishes the copy distribution notations from the other text and data entries on the form.</P>
        <P>(5) The manifest and continuation sheet must be printed as six-copy forms. Copy-to-copy registration must be exact within <FR>1/32</FR>nd of an inch. Handwritten and typed impressions on the form must be legible on all six copies. Copies must be bound together by one or more common stubs that reasonably ensure that they will not become detached inadvertently during normal use.</P>
        <P>(6) Each copy of the manifest and continuation sheet must indicate how the copy must be distributed, as follows:</P>
        <P>(i) Page 1 (top copy): “Designated facility to destination State (if required)”.</P>
        <P>(ii) Page 2: “Designated facility to generator State (if required)”.</P>
        <P>(iii) Page 3: “Designated facility to generator”.</P>
        <P>(iv) Page 4: “Designated facility's copy”.</P>
        <P>(v) Page 5: “Transporter's copy”.</P>
        <P>(vi) Page 6 (bottom copy): “Generator's initial copy”.</P>
        <P>(7) The instructions in the appendix to 40 CFR part 262 must appear legibly on the back of the copies of the manifest and continuation sheet as provided in this paragraph (f). The instructions must not be visible through the front of the copies when photocopied or faxed.</P>
        <P>(i) Manifest Form 8700-22.</P>
        <P>(A) The “Instructions for Generators” on Copy 6;</P>
        <P>(B) The “Instructions for International Shipment Block” and “Instructions for Transporters” on Copy 5; and</P>
        <P>(C) The “Instructions for Treatment, Storage, and Disposal Facilities” on Copy 4.</P>
        <P>(ii) Manifest Form 8700-22A.</P>
        <P>(A) The “Instructions for Generators” on Copy 6;</P>
        <P>(B) The “Instructions for Transporters” on Copy 5; and</P>
        <P>(C) The “Instructions for Treatment, Storage, and Disposal Facilities” on Copy 4.</P>
        <P>(g)(1) A generator may use manifests printed by any source so long as the source of the printed form has received approval from EPA to print the manifest under paragraphs (c) and (e) of this section. A registered source may be a:</P>
        <P>(i) State agency;</P>
        <P>(ii) Commercial printer;</P>
        <P>(iii) Hazardous waste generator, transporter or TSDF; or</P>

        <P>(iv) Hazardous waste broker or other preparer who prepares or arranges shipments of hazardous waste for transportation.<PRTPAGE P="358"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) A generator must determine whether the generator state or the consignment state for a shipment regulates any additional wastes (beyond those regulated Federally) as hazardous wastes under these states' authorized programs. Generators also must determine whether the consignment state or generator state requires the generator to submit any copies of the manifest to these states. In cases where the generator must supply copies to either the generator's state or the consignment state, the generator is responsible for supplying legible photocopies of the manifest to these states.</P>
        <P>(h)(1) If an approved registrant would like to update any of the information provided in its application approved under paragraph (c) of this section (e.g., to update a company phone number or name of contact person), the registrant must revise the application and submit it to the EPA Director of the Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery, along with an indication or explanation of the update, as soon as practicable after the change occurs. The Agency either will approve or deny the revision. If the Agency denies the revision, it will explain the reasons for the denial, and it will contact the registrant and request further modification before approval.</P>
        <P>(2) If the registrant would like a new tracking number suffix, the registrant must submit a proposed suffix to the EPA Director of the Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery, along with the reason for requesting it. The Agency will either approve the suffix or deny the suffix and provide an explanation why it is not acceptable.</P>
        <P>(3) If a registrant would like to change the paper type, paper weight, ink color of the manifest instructions, or binding method of its manifest or continuation sheet subsequent to approval under paragraph (e) of this section, then the registrant must submit three samples of the revised form for EPA review and approval. If the approved registrant would like to use a new printer, the registrant must submit three manifest samples printed by the new printer, along with a brief description of the printer's qualifications to print the manifest. EPA will evaluate the manifests and either approve the registrant to print the forms as proposed or request additional information or modification to them before approval. EPA will notify the registrant of its decision by mail. The registrant cannot use or distribute its revised forms until EPA approves them.</P>
        <P>(i) If, subsequent to its approval under paragraph (e) of this section, a registrant typesets its manifest or continuation sheet instead of using the electronic file of the forms provided by EPA, it must submit three samples of the manifest or continuation sheet to the registry for approval. EPA will evaluate the manifests or continuation sheets and either approve the registrant to print them as proposed or request additional information or modification to them before approval. EPA will notify the registrant of its decision by mail. The registrant cannot use or distribute its typeset forms until EPA approves them.</P>
        <P>(j) EPA may exempt a registrant from the requirement to submit form samples under paragraph (d) or (h)(3) of this section if the Agency is persuaded that a separate review of the registrant's forms would serve little purpose in informing an approval decision (e.g., a registrant certifies that it will print the manifest using the same paper type, paper weight, ink color of the instructions and binding method of the form samples approved for some other registrant). A registrant may request an exemption from EPA by indicating why an exemption is warranted.</P>
        <P>(k) An approved registrant must notify EPA by phone or email as soon as it becomes aware that it has duplicated tracking numbers on any manifests that have been used or distributed to other parties.</P>
        <P>(l) If, subsequent to approval of a registrant under paragraph (e) of this section, EPA becomes aware that the approved paper type, paper weight, ink color of the instructions, or binding method of the registrant's form is unsatisfactory, EPA will contact the registrant and require modifications to the form.</P>
        <P>(m)(1) EPA may suspend and, if necessary, revoke printing privileges if we find that the registrant:</P>

        <P>(i) Has used or distributed forms that deviate from its approved form samples <PRTPAGE P="359"/>in regard to paper weight, paper type, ink color of the instructions, or binding method; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Exhibits a continuing pattern of behavior in using or distributing manifests that contain duplicate manifest tracking numbers.</P>
        <P>(2) EPA will send a warning letter to the registrant that specifies the date by which it must come into compliance with the requirements. If the registrant does not come in compliance by the specified date, EPA will send a second letter notifying the registrant that EPA has suspended or revoked its printing privileges. An approved registrant must provide information on its printing activities to EPA if requested.</P>
        <CITA>[70 FR 10815, Mar. 4, 2005, as amended at 74 FR 30230, June 25, 2009; 76 FR 36366, June 22, 2011]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.22</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Number of copies.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The manifest consists of at least the number of copies which will provide the generator, each transporter, and the owner or operator of the designated facility with one copy each for their records and another copy to be returned to the generator.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.23</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of the manifest.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The generator must:</P>
        <P>(1) Sign the manifest certification by hand; and</P>
        <P>(2) Obtain the handwritten signature of the initial transporter and date of acceptance on the manifest; and</P>
        <P>(3) Retain one copy, in accordance with § 262.40(a).</P>
        <P>(b) The generator must give the transporter the remaining copies of the manifest.</P>
        <P>(c) For shipments of hazardous waste within the United States solely by water (bulk shipments only), the generator must send three copies of the manifest dated and signed in accordance with this section to the owner or operator of the designated facility or the last water (bulk shipment) transporter to handle the waste in the United States if exported by water. Copies of the manifest are not required for each transporter.</P>
        <P>(d) For rail shipments of hazardous waste within the United States which originate at the site of generation, the generator must send at least three copies of the manifest dated and signed in accordance with this section to:</P>
        <P>(1) The next non-rail transporter, if any; or</P>
        <P>(2) The designated facility if transported solely by rail; or</P>
        <P>(3) The last rail transporter to handle the waste in the United States if exported by rail.</P>

        <P>(e) For shipments of hazardous waste to a designated facility in an authorized State which has not yet obtained authorization to regulate that particular waste as hazardous, the generator must assure that the designated facility agrees to sign and return the manifest to the generator, and that any out-of-state transporter signs and forwards the manifest to the designated facility.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>See § 263.20(e) and (f) for special provisions for rail or water (bulk shipment) transporters.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <P>(f) For rejected shipments of hazardous waste or container residues contained in non-empty containers that are returned to the generator by the designated facility (following the procedures of 40 CFR 264.72(f) or 265.72(f)), the generator must:</P>
        <P>(1) Sign either:</P>
        <P>(i) Item 20 of the new manifest if a new manifest is used for the returned shipment; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Item 18c of the original manifest if the original manifest is used for the returned shipment;</P>
        <P>(2) Provide the transporter a copy of the manifest;</P>
        <P>(3) Within 30 days of delivery of the rejected shipment or container residues contained in non-empty containers, send a copy of the manifest to the designated facility that returned the shipment to the generator; and</P>
        <P>(4) Retain at the generator's site a copy of each manifest for at least three years from the date of delivery.</P>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 45 FR 86973, Dec. 31, 1980; 55 FR 2354, Jan. 23, 1990; 75 FR 13004, Mar. 18, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.24</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of the electronic manifest.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Legal equivalence to paper manifests.</E> Electronic manifests that are obtained, completed, and transmitted in accordance with § 262.20(a)(3), and used in accordance with this section in lieu of EPA Forms 8700-22 and 8700-22A are <PRTPAGE P="360"/>the legal equivalent of paper manifest forms bearing handwritten signatures, and satisfy for all purposes any requirement in these regulations to obtain, complete, sign, provide, use, or retain a manifest.</P>
        <P>(1) Any requirement in these regulations to sign a manifest or manifest certification by hand, or to obtain a handwritten signature, is satisfied by signing with or obtaining a valid and enforceable electronic signature within the meaning of 262.25.</P>
        <P>(2) Any requirement in these regulations to give, provide, send, forward, or return to another person a copy of the manifest is satisfied when an electronic manifest is transmitted to the other person by submission to the system.</P>
        <P>(3) Any requirement in these regulations for a generator to keep or retain a copy of each manifest is satisfied by retention of a signed electronic manifest in the generator's account on the national e-Manifest system, provided that such copies are readily available for viewing and production if requested by any EPA or authorized state inspector.</P>
        <P>(4) No generator may be held liable for the inability to produce an electronic manifest for inspection under this section if the generator can demonstrate that the inability to produce the electronic manifest is due exclusively to a technical difficulty with the electronic manifest system for which the generator bears no responsibility.</P>
        <P>(b) A generator may participate in the electronic manifest system either by accessing the electronic manifest system from its own electronic equipment, or by accessing the electronic manifest system from portable equipment brought to the generator's site by the transporter who accepts the hazardous waste shipment from the generator for off-site transportation.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Restriction on use of electronic manifests.</E> A generator may prepare an electronic manifest for the tracking of hazardous waste shipments involving any RCRA hazardous waste only if it is known at the time the manifest is originated that all waste handlers named on the manifest participate in the electronic manifest system.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Requirement for one printed copy.</E> To the extent the Hazardous Materials regulation on shipping papers for carriage by public highway requires shippers of hazardous materials to supply a paper document for compliance with 49 CFR 177.817, a generator originating an electronic manifest must also provide the initial transporter with one printed copy of the electronic manifest.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Special procedures when electronic manifest is unavailable.</E> If a generator has prepared an electronic manifest for a hazardous waste shipment, but the electronic manifest system becomes unavailable for any reason prior to the time that the initial transporter has signed electronically to acknowledge the receipt of the hazardous waste from the generator, then the generator must obtain and complete a paper manifest and if necessary, a continuation sheet (EPA Forms 8700-22 and 8700-22A) in accordance with the manifest instructions in the appendix to this part, and use these paper forms from this point forward in accordance with the requirements of § 262.23.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Special procedures for electronic signature methods undergoing tests.</E> If a generator has prepared an electronic manifest for a hazardous waste shipment, and signs this manifest electronically using an electronic signature method which is undergoing pilot or demonstration tests aimed at demonstrating the practicality or legal dependability of the signature method, then the generator shall also sign with an ink signature the generator/offeror certification on the printed copy of the manifest provided under paragraph (d) of this section.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Imposition of user fee.</E> A generator who is a user of the electronic manifest may be assessed a user fee by EPA for the origination of each electronic manifest. EPA shall maintain and update from time-to-time the current schedule of electronic manifest user fees, which shall be determined based on current and projected system costs and level of use of the electronic manifest system. The current schedule of electronic manifest user fees shall be published as an appendix to this part.</P>
        <CITA>[79 FR 7558, Feb. 7, 2014]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="361"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.25</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Electronic manifest signatures.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Electronic signature methods for the e-Manifest system shall:</P>
        <P>(a) Be a legally valid and enforceable signature under applicable EPA and other Federal requirements pertaining to electronic signatures; and</P>
        <P>(b) Be a method that is designed and implemented in a manner that EPA considers to be as cost-effective and practical as possible for the users of the manifest.</P>
        <CITA>[79 FR 7558, Feb. 7, 2014]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.27</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Waste minimization certification.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A generator who initiates a shipment of hazardous waste must certify to one of the following statements in Item 15 of the uniform hazardous waste manifest:</P>
        <P>(a) “I am a large quantity generator. I have a program in place to reduce the volume and toxicity of waste generated to the degree I have determined to be economically practicable and I have selected the practicable method of treatment, storage, or disposal currently available to me which minimizes the present and future threat to human health and the environment;” or</P>
        <P>(b) “I am a small quantity generator. I have made a good faith effort to minimize my waste generation and select the best waste management method that is available to me and that I can afford.”</P>
        <CITA>[70 FR 10817, Mar. 4, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Pre-Transport Requirements</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.30</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Packaging.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Before transporting hazardous waste or offering hazardous waste for transportation off-site, a generator must package the waste in accordance with the applicable Department of Transportation regulations on packaging under 49 CFR parts 173, 178, and 179.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.31</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Labeling.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Before transporting or offering hazardous waste for transportation off-site, a generator must label each package in accordance with the applicable Department of Transportation regulations on hazardous materials under 49 CFR part 172.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.32</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Marking.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Before transporting or offering hazardous waste for transportation off-site, a generator must mark each package of hazardous waste in accordance with the applicable Department of Transportation regulations on hazardous materials under 49 CFR part 172;</P>

        <P>(b) Before transporting hazardous waste or offering hazardous waste for transportation off-site, a generator must mark each container of 119 gallons or less used in such transportation with the following words and information in accordance with the requirements of 49 CFR 172.304:
        </P>
        <EXTRACT>

          <P>HAZARDOUS WASTE—Federal Law Prohibits Improper Disposal. If found, contact the nearest police or public safety authority or the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.
          </P>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Generator's Name and Address _____.</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Generator's EPA Identification Number</FP>
          <FP>_____.</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Manifest Tracking Number _____.</FP>
        </EXTRACT>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 70 FR 10817, Mar. 4, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.33</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Placarding.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Before transporting hazardous waste or offering hazardous waste for transportation off-site, a generator must placard or offer the initial transporter the appropriate placards according to Department of Transportation regulations for hazardous materials under 49 CFR part 172, subpart F.</P>
        <CITA>[70 FR 35037, June 16, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.34</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Accumulation time.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Except as provided in paragraphs (d), (e), and (f) of this section, a generator may accumulate hazardous waste on-site for 90 days or less without a permit or without having interim status, provided that:</P>
        <P>(1) The waste is placed:</P>
        <P>(i) In containers and the generator complies with the applicable requirements of subparts I, AA, BB, and CC of 40 CFR part 265; and/or</P>

        <P>(ii) In tanks and the generator complies with the applicable requirements of subparts J, AA, BB, and CC of 40 <PRTPAGE P="362"/>CFR part 265 except §§ 265.197(c) and 265.200; and/or</P>
        <P>(iii) On drip pads and the generator complies with subpart W of 40 CFR part 265 and maintains the following records at the facility:</P>
        <P>(A) A description of procedures that will be followed to ensure that all wastes are removed from the drip pad and associated collection system at least once every 90 days; and</P>
        <P>(B) Documentation of each waste removal, including the quantity of waste removed from the drip pad and the sump or collection system and the date and time of removal; and/or</P>
        <P>(iv) In containment buildings and the generator complies with subpart DD of 40 CFR part 265, has placed its professional engineer certification that the building complies with the design standards specified in 40 CFR 265.1101 in the facility's operating record no later than 60 days after the date of initial operation of the unit. After February 18, 1993, PE certification will be required prior to operation of the unit. The owner or operator shall maintain the following records at the facility:</P>
        <P>(A) A written description of procedures to ensure that each waste volume remains in the unit for no more than 90 days, a written description of the waste generation and management practices for the facility showing that they are consistent with respecting the 90 day limit, and documentation that the procedures are complied with; or</P>
        <P>(B) Documentation that the unit is emptied at least once every 90 days.</P>
        <FP>In addition, such a generator is exempt from all the requirements in subparts G and H of 40 CFR part 265, except for §§ 265.111 and 265.114.</FP>
        <P>(2) The date upon which each period of accumulation begins is clearly marked and visible for inspection on each container;</P>
        <P>(3) While being accumulated on-site, each container and tank is labeled or marked clearly with the words, “Hazardous Waste”; and</P>
        <P>(4) The generator complies with the requirements for owners or operators in subparts C and D in 40 CFR part 265, with § 265.16, and with all applicable requirements under 40 CFR part 268.</P>
        <P>(b) A generator of 1,000 kilograms or greater of hazardous waste in a calendar month, or greater than 1 kg of acute hazardous waste listed in §§ 261.31 or 261.33(e) in a calendar month, who accumulates hazardous waste or acute hazardous waste for more than 90 days is an operator of a storage facility and is subject to the requirements of 40 CFR parts 264, 265, and 267 and the permit requirements of 40 CFR part 270 unless he has been granted an extension to the 90-day period. Such extension may be granted by EPA if hazardous wastes must remain on-site for longer than 90 days due to unforeseen, temporary, and uncontrollable circumstances. An extension of up to 30 days may be granted at the discretion of the Regional Administrator on a case-by-case basis.</P>
        <P>(c)(1) A generator may accumulate as much as 55 gallons of hazardous waste or one quart of acutely hazardous waste listed in § 261.31 or § 261.33(e) in containers at or near any point of generation where wastes initially accumulate which is under the control of the operator of the process generating the waste, without a permit or interim status and without complying with paragraph (a) or (d) of this section provided he:</P>
        <P>(i) Complies with §§ 265.171, 265.172, and 265.173(a) of this chapter; and</P>
        <P>(ii) Marks his containers either with the words “Hazardous Waste” or with other words that identify the contents of the containers.</P>
        <P>(2) A generator who accumulates either hazardous waste or acutely hazardous waste listed in § 261.31 or § 261.33(e) in excess of the amounts listed in paragraph (c)(1) of this section at or near any point of generation must, with respect to that amount of excess waste, comply within three days with paragraph (a) of this section or other applicable provisions of this chapter. During the three day period the generator must continue to comply with paragraphs (c)(1)(i) and (ii) of this section. The generator must mark the container holding the excess accumulation of hazardous waste with the date the excess amount began accumulating.</P>

        <P>(d) A generator who generates greater than 100 kilograms but less than 1000 <PRTPAGE P="363"/>kilograms of hazardous waste in a calendar month may accumulate hazardous waste on-site for 180 days or less without a permit or without having interim status provided that:</P>
        <P>(1) The quantity of waste accumulated on-site never exceeds 6000 kilograms;</P>
        <P>(2) The generator complies with the requirements of subpart I of part 265 of this chapter, except for §§ 265.176 and 265.178;</P>
        <P>(3) The generator complies with the requirements of § 265.201 in subpart J of part 265;</P>
        <P>(4) The generator complies with the requirements of paragraphs (a)(2) and (a)(3) of this section, the requirements of subpart C of part 265, with all applicable requirements under 40 CFR part 268; and</P>
        <P>(5) The generator complies with the following requirements:</P>

        <P>(i) At all times there must be at least one employee either on the premises or on call (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> available to respond to an emergency by reaching the facility within a short period of time) with the responsibility for coordinating all emergency response measures specified in paragraph (d)(5)(iv) of this section. This employee is the emergency coordinator.</P>
        <P>(ii) The generator must post the following information next to the telephone:</P>
        <P>(A) The name and telephone number of the emergency coordinator;</P>
        <P>(B) Location of fire extinguishers and spill control material, and, if present, fire alarm; and</P>
        <P>(C) The telephone number of the fire department, unless the facility has a direct alarm.</P>
        <P>(iii) The generator must ensure that all employees are thoroughly familiar with proper waste handling and emergency procedures, relevant to their responsibilities during normal facility operations and emergencies;</P>
        <P>(iv) The emergency coordinator or his designee must respond to any emergencies that arise. The applicable responses are as follows:</P>
        <P>(A) In the event of a fire, call the fire department or attempt to extinguish it using a fire extinguisher;</P>
        <P>(B) In the event of a spill, contain the flow of hazardous waste to the extent possible, and as soon as is practicable, clean up the hazardous waste and any contaminated materials or soil;</P>
        <P>(C) In the event of a fire, explosion, or other release which could threaten human health outside the facility or when the generator has knowledge that a spill has reached surface water, the generator must immediately notify the National Response Center (using their 24-hour toll free number 800/424-8802). The report must include the following information:</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) The name, address, and U.S. EPA Identification Number of the generator;</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) Date, time, and type of incident (e.g., spill or fire);</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">3</E>) Quantity and type of hazardous waste involved in the incident;</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">4</E>) Extent of injuries, if any; and</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">5</E>) Estimated quantity and disposition of recovered materials, if any.</P>
        <P>(e) A generator who generates greater than 100 kilograms but less than 1000 kilograms of hazardous waste in a calendar month and who must transport his waste, or offer his waste for transportation, over a distance of 200 miles or more for off-site treatment, storage or disposal may accumulate hazardous waste on-site for 270 days or less without a permit or without having interim status provided that he complies with the requirements of paragraph (d) of this section.</P>

        <P>(f) A generator who generates greater than 100 kilograms but less than 1000 kilograms of hazardous waste in a calendar month and who accumulates hazardous waste in quantities exceeding 6000 kg or accumulates hazardous waste for more than 180 days (or for more than 270 days if he must transport his waste, or offer his waste for transportation, over a distance of 200 miles or more) is an operator of a storage facility and is subject to the requirements of 40 CFR parts 264, 265 and 267, and the permit requirements of 40 CFR part 270 unless he has been granted an extension to the 180-day (or 270-day if applicable) period. Such extension may be granted by EPA if hazardous wastes must remain on-site for longer than 180 days (or 270 days if applicable) due to unforeseen, temporary, and uncontrollable circumstances. An extension of up to 30 days may be <PRTPAGE P="364"/>granted at the discretion of the Regional Administrator on a case-by-case basis.</P>
        <P>(g) A generator who generates 1,000 kilograms or greater of hazardous waste per calendar month who also generates wastewater treatment sludges from electroplating operations that meet the listing description for the RCRA hazardous waste code F006, may accumulate F006 waste on-site for more than 90 days, but not more than 180 days without a permit or without having interim status provided that:</P>
        <P>(1) The generator has implemented pollution prevention practices that reduce the amount of any hazardous substances, pollutants or contaminants entering F006 or otherwise released to the environment prior to its recycling;</P>
        <P>(2) The F006 waste is legitimately recycled through metals recovery;</P>
        <P>(3) No more than 20,000 kilograms of F006 waste is accumulated on-site at any one time; and</P>
        <P>(4) The F006 waste is managed in accordance with the following:</P>
        <P>(i) The F006 waste is placed:</P>
        <P>(A) In containers and the generator complies with the applicable requirements of subparts I, AA, BB, and CC of 40 CFR part 265; and/or</P>
        <P>(B) In tanks and the generator complies with the applicable requirements of subparts J, AA, BB, and CC of 40 CFR part 265, except §§ 265.197(c) and 265.200; and/or</P>
        <P>(C) In containment buildings and the generator complies with subpart DD of 40 CFR part 265, and has placed its professional engineer certification that the building complies with the design standards specified in 40 CFR 265.1101 in the facility's operating record prior to operation of the unit. The owner or operator must maintain the following records at the facility:</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) A written description of procedures to ensure that the F006 waste remains in the unit for no more than 180 days, a written description of the waste generation and management practices for the facility showing that they are consistent with the 180-day limit, and documentation that the generator is complying with the procedures; or</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) Documentation that the unit is emptied at least once every 180 days.</P>
        <P>(ii) In addition, such a generator is exempt from all the requirements in subparts G and H of 40 CFR part 265, except for §§ 265.111 and 265.114.</P>
        <P>(iii) The date upon which each period of accumulation begins is clearly marked and visible for inspection on each container;</P>
        <P>(iv) While being accumulated on-site, each container and tank is labeled or marked clearly with the words, “Hazardous Waste;” and</P>
        <P>(v) The generator complies with the requirements for owners or operators in subparts C and D in 40 CFR part 265, with 40 CFR 265.16, and with 40 CFR 268.7(a)(5).</P>
        <P>(h) A generator who generates 1,000 kilograms or greater of hazardous waste per calendar month who also generates wastewater treatment sludges from electroplating operations that meet the listing description for the RCRA hazardous waste code F006, and who must transport this waste, or offer this waste for transportation, over a distance of 200 miles or more for off-site metals recovery, may accumulate F006 waste on-site for more than 90 days, but not more than 270 days without a permit or without having interim status if the generator complies with the requirements of paragraphs (g)(1) through (g)(4) of this section.</P>

        <P>(i) A generator accumulating F006 in accordance with paragraphs (g) and (h) of this section who accumulates F006 waste on-site for more than 180 days (or for more than 270 days if the generator must transport this waste, or offer this waste for transportation, over a distance of 200 miles or more), or who accumulates more than 20,000 kilograms of F006 waste on-site is an operator of a storage facility and is subject to the requirements of 40 CFR parts 264, 265 and 267, and the permit requirements of 40 CFR part 270 unless the generator has been granted an extension to the 180-day (or 270-day if applicable) period or an exception to the 20,000 kilogram accumulation limit. Such extensions and exceptions may be granted by EPA if F006 waste must remain on-site for longer than 180 days (or 270 days if applicable) or if more than 20,000 kilograms of F006 waste must remain on-site due to unforeseen, <PRTPAGE P="365"/>temporary, and uncontrollable circumstances. An extension of up to 30 days or an exception to the accumulation limit may be granted at the discretion of the Regional Administrator on a case-by-case basis.</P>
        <P>(j) A member of the Performance Track Program who generates 1000 kg or greater of hazardous waste per month (or one kilogram or more of acute hazardous waste) may accumulate hazardous waste on-site without a permit or interim status for an extended period of time, provided that:</P>
        <P>(1) The generator accumulates the hazardous waste for no more than 180 days, or for no more than 270 days if the generator must transport the waste (or offer the waste for transport) more than 200 miles from the generating facility; and</P>
        <P>(2) The generator first notifies the Regional Administrator and the Director of the authorized State in writing of its intent to begin accumulation of hazardous waste for extended time periods under the provisions of this section. Such advance notice must include:</P>
        <P>(i) Name and EPA ID number of the facility, and specification of when the facility will begin accumulation of hazardous wastes for extended periods of time in accordance with this section; and</P>
        <P>(ii) A description of the types of hazardous wastes that will be accumulated for extended periods of time, and the units that will be used for such extended accumulation; and</P>
        <P>(iii) A Statement that the facility has made all changes to its operations, procedures, including emergency preparedness procedures, and equipment, including equipment needed for emergency preparedness, that will be necessary to accommodate extended time periods for accumulating hazardous wastes; and</P>
        <P>(iv) If the generator intends to accumulate hazardous wastes on-site for up to 270 days, a certification that a facility that is permitted (or operating under interim status) under part 270 of this chapter to receive these wastes is not available within 200 miles of the generating facility; and</P>
        <P>(3) The waste is managed in:</P>
        <P>(i) Containers, in accordance with the applicable requirements of subparts I, AA, BB, and CC of 40 CFR part 265 and 40 CFR 264.175; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Tanks, in accordance with the applicable requirements of subparts J, AA, BB, and CC of 40 CFR part 265, except for §§ 265.197(c) and 265.200; or</P>
        <P>(iii) Drip pads, in accordance with subpart W of 40 CFR part 265; or</P>
        <P>(iv) Containment buildings, in accordance with subpart DD of 40 CFR part 265; and</P>
        <P>(4) The quantity of hazardous waste that is accumulated for extended time periods at the facility does not exceed 30,000 kg; and</P>
        <P>(5) The generator maintains the following records at the facility for each unit used for extended accumulation times:</P>
        <P>(i) A written description of procedures to ensure that each waste volume remains in the unit for no more than 180 days (or 270 days, as applicable), a description of the waste generation and management practices at the facility showing that they are consistent with the extended accumulation time limit, and documentation that the procedures are complied with; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Documentation that the unit is emptied at least once every 180 days (or 270 days, if applicable); and</P>
        <P>(6) Each container or tank that is used for extended accumulation time periods is labeled or marked clearly with the words “Hazardous Waste,” and for each container the date upon which each period of accumulation begins is clearly marked and visible for inspection; and</P>
        <P>(7) The generator complies with the requirements for owners and operators in 40 CFR part 265, with § 265.16, and with § 268.7(a)(5). In addition, such a generator is exempt from all the requirements in subparts G and H of part 265, except for §§ 265.111 and 265.114; and</P>
        <P>(8) The generator has implemented pollution prevention practices that reduce the amount of any hazardous substances, pollutants, or contaminants released to the environment prior to its recycling, treatment, or disposal; and</P>

        <P>(9) The generator includes the following with its Performance Track Annual Performance Report, which must <PRTPAGE P="366"/>be submitted to the Regional Administrator and the Director of the authorized State:</P>
        <P>(i) Information on the total quantity of each hazardous waste generated at the facility that has been managed in the previous year according to extended accumulation time periods; and</P>
        <P>(ii) Information for the previous year on the number of off-site shipments of hazardous wastes generated at the facility, the types and locations of destination facilities, how the wastes were managed at the destination facilities (e.g., recycling, treatment, storage, or disposal), and what changes in on-site or off-site waste management practices have occurred as a result of extended accumulation times or other pollution prevention provisions of this section; and</P>
        <P>(iii) Information for the previous year on any hazardous waste spills or accidents occurring at extended accumulation units at the facility, or during off-site transport of accumulated wastes; and</P>
        <P>(iv) If the generator intends to accumulate hazardous wastes on-site for up to 270 days, a certification that a facility that is permitted (or operating under interim status) under part 270 of this chapter to receive these wastes is not available within 200 miles of the generating facility; and</P>
        <P>(k) If hazardous wastes must remain on-site at a Performance Track member facility for longer than 180 days (or 270 days, if applicable) due to unforseen, temporary, and uncontrollable circumstances, an extension to the extended accumulation time period of up to 30 days may be granted at the discretion of the Regional Administrator on a case-by-case basis.</P>
        <P>(l) If a generator who is a member of the Performance Track Program withdraws from the Performance Track Program, or if the Regional Administrator terminates a generator's membership, the generator must return to compliance with all otherwise applicable hazardous waste regulations as soon as possible, but no later than six months after the date of withdrawal or termination.</P>
        <P>(m) A generator who sends a shipment of hazardous waste to a designated facility with the understanding that the designated facility can accept and manage the waste and later receives that shipment back as a rejected load or residue in accordance with the manifest discrepancy provisions of § 264.72 or § 265.72 of this chapter may accumulate the returned waste on-site in accordance with paragraphs (a) and (b) or (d), (e) and (f) of this section, depending on the amount of hazardous waste on-site in that calendar month. Upon receipt of the returned shipment, the generator must:</P>
        <P>(1) Sign Item 18c of the manifest, if the transporter returned the shipment using the original manifest; or</P>
        <P>(2) Sign Item 20 of the manifest, if the transporter returned the shipment using a new manifest.</P>
        <CITA>[47 FR 1251, Jan. 11, 1982]</CITA>
        <EDNOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
          <P>For <E T="04">Federal Register</E> citations affecting § 262.34, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at <E T="03">www.fdsys.gov.</E>
          </P>
        </EDNOTE>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart D—Recordkeeping and Reporting</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.40</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) A generator must keep a copy of each manifest signed in accordance with § 262.23(a) for three years or until he receives a signed copy from the designated facility which received the waste. This signed copy must be retained as a record for at least three years from the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter.</P>
        <P>(b) A generator must keep a copy of each Biennial Report and Exception Report for a period of at least three years from the due date of the report.</P>
        <P>(c) A generator must keep records of any test results, waste analyses, or other determinations made in accordance with § 262.11 for at least three years from the date that the waste was last sent to on-site or off-site treatment, storage, or disposal.</P>
        <P>(d) The periods or retention referred to in this section are extended automatically during the course of any unresolved enforcement action regarding the regulated activity or as requested by the Administrator.</P>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 48 FR 3981, Jan. 28, 1983]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="367"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.41</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Biennial report.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) A generator who ships any hazardous waste off-site to a treatment, storage or disposal facility within the United States must prepare and submit a single copy of a Biennial Report to the Regional Administrator by March 1 of each even numbered year. The Biennial Report must be submitted on EPA Form 8700-13A, must cover generator activities during the previous year, and must include the following information:</P>
        <P>(1) The EPA identification number, name, and address of the generator;</P>
        <P>(2) The calendar year covered by the report;</P>
        <P>(3) The EPA identification number, name, and address for each off-site treatment, storage, or disposal facility in the United States to which waste was shipped during the year;</P>
        <P>(4) The name and EPA identification number of each transporter used during the reporting year for shipments to a treatment, storage or disposal facility within the United States;</P>
        <P>(5) A description, EPA hazardous waste number (from 40 CFR part 261, subpart C or D), DOT hazard class, and quantity of each hazardous waste shipped off-site for shipments to a treatment, storage or disposal facility within the United States. This information must be listed by EPA identification number of each such off-site facility to which waste was shipped.</P>
        <P>(6) A description of the efforts undertaken during the year to reduce the volume and toxicity of waste generated.</P>
        <P>(7) A description of the changes in volume and toxicity of waste actually achieved during the year in comparison to previous years to the extent such information is available for years prior to 1984.</P>
        <P>(8) The certification signed by the generator or authorized representative.</P>
        <P>(b) Any generator who treats, stores, or disposes of hazardous waste on-site must submit a biennial report covering those wastes in accordance with the provisions of 40 CFR parts 270, 264, 265, 266, and 267. Reporting for exports of hazardous waste is not required on the Biennial Report form. A separate annual report requirement is set forth at 40 CFR 262.56.</P>
        <CITA>[48 FR 3981, Jan. 28, 1983, as amended at 48 FR 14294, Apr. 1, 1983; 50 FR 28746, July 15, 1985; 51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986; 75 FR 13005, Mar. 18, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.42</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exception reporting.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) A generator of 1,000 kilograms or greater of hazardous waste in a calendar month, or greater than 1 kg of acute hazardous waste listed in § 261.31 or § 261.33(e) in a calendar month, who does not receive a copy of the manifest with the handwritten signature of the owner or operator of the designated facility within 35 days of the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter must contact the transporter and/or the owner or operator of the designated facility to determine the status of the hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>(2) A generator of 1,000 kilograms or greater of hazardous waste in a calendar month, or greater than 1 kg of acute hazardous waste listed in § 261.31or § 261.33(e) in a calendar month, must submit an Exception Report to the EPA Regional Administrator for the Region in which the generator is located if he has not received a copy of the manifest with the handwritten signature of the owner or operator of the designated facility within 45 days of the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter. The Exception Report must include:</P>
        <P>(i) A legible copy of the manifest for which the generator does not have confirmation of delivery;</P>
        <P>(ii) A cover letter signed by the generator or his authorized representative explaining the efforts taken to locate the hazardous waste and the results of those efforts.</P>

        <P>(b) A generator of greater than 100 kilograms but less than 1000 kilograms of hazardous waste in a calendar month who does not receive a copy of the manifest with the handwritten signature of the owner or operator of the designated facility within 60 days of the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter must submit a legible copy of the manifest, with some indication that the generator has not received confirmation of delivery, to the EPA Regional Administrator for <PRTPAGE P="368"/>the Region in which the generator is located.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>The submission to EPA need only be a handwritten or typed note on the manifest itself, or on an attached sheet of paper, stating that the return copy was not received.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(c) For rejected shipments of hazardous waste or container residues contained in non-empty containers that are forwarded to an alternate facility by a designated facility using a new manifest (following the procedures of 40 CFR 264.72(e)(1) through (6) or 40 CFR 265.72(e)(1) through (6)), the generator must comply with the requirements of paragraph (a) or (b) of this section, as applicable, for the shipment forwarding the material from the designated facility to the alternate facility instead of for the shipment from the generator to the designated facility. For purposes of paragraph (a) or (b) of this section for a shipment forwarding such waste to an alternate facility by a designated facility:</P>
        <P>(1) The copy of the manifest received by the generator must have the handwritten signature of the owner or operator of the alternate facility in place of the signature of the owner or operator of the designated facility, and</P>
        <P>(2) The 35/45/60-day timeframes begin the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter forwarding the hazardous waste shipment from the designated facility to the alternate facility.</P>
        <CITA>[52 FR 35898, Sept. 23, 1987, as amended at 75 FR 13005, Mar. 18, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.43</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional reporting.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The Administrator, as he deems necessary under sections 2002(a) and 3002(6) of the Act, may require generators to furnish additional reports concerning the quantities and disposition of wastes identified or listed in 40 CFR part 261.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.44</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Special requirements for generators of between 100 and 1000 kg/mo.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A generator of greater than 100 kilograms but less than 1000 kilograms of hazardous waste in a calendar month is subject only to the following requirements in this subpart:</P>
        <P>(a) Section 262.40(a), (c), and (d), recordkeeping;</P>
        <P>(b) Section 262.42(b), exception reporting; and</P>
        <P>(c) Section 262.43, additional reporting.</P>
        <CITA>[52 FR 35899, Sept. 23, 1987]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart E—Exports of Hazardous Waste</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.50</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <P>This subpart establishes requirements applicable to exports of hazardous waste. Except to the extent § 262.58 provides otherwise, a primary exporter of hazardous waste must comply with the special requirements of this subpart and a transporter transporting hazardous waste for export must comply with applicable requirements of part 263. Section 262.58 sets forth the requirements of international agreements between the United States and receiving countries which establish different notice, export, and enforcement procedures for the transportation, treatment, storage and disposal of hazardous waste for shipments between the United States and those countries.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.51</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In addition to the definitions set forth at 40 CFR 260.10, the following definitions apply to this subpart:</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Consignee</E> means the ultimate treatment, storage or disposal facility in a receiving country to which the hazardous waste will be sent.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">EPA Acknowledgement of Consent</E> means the cable sent to EPA from the U.S. Embassy in a receiving country that acknowledges the written consent of the receiving country to accept the hazardous waste and describes the terms and conditions of the receiving country's consent to the shipment.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Primary Exporter</E> means any person who is required to originate the manifest for a shipment of hazardous waste in accordance with 40 CFR part 262, subpart B, or equivalent State provision, which specifies a treatment, storage, or disposal facility in a receiving <PRTPAGE P="369"/>country as the facility to which the hazardous waste will be sent and any intermediary arranging for the export.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Receiving country</E> means a foreign country to which a hazardous waste is sent for the purpose of treatment, storage or disposal (except short-term storage incidental to transportation).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Transit country</E> means any foreign country, other than a receiving country, through which a hazardous waste is transported.</P>
        <CITA>[53 FR 27164, July 19, 1988]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.52</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Exports of hazardous waste are prohibited except in compliance with the applicable requirements of this subpart and part 263. Exports of hazardous waste are prohibited unless:</P>
        <P>(a) Notification in accordance with § 262.53 has been provided;</P>
        <P>(b) The receiving country has consented to accept the hazardous waste;</P>
        <P>(c) A copy of the EPA Acknowledgment of Consent to the shipment accompanies the hazardous waste shipment and, unless exported by rail, is attached to the manifest (or shipping paper for exports by water (bulk shipment)).</P>
        <P>(d) The hazardous waste shipment conforms to the terms of the receiving country's written consent as reflected in the EPA Acknowledgment of Consent.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.53</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notification of intent to export.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) A primary exporter of hazardous waste must notify EPA of an intended export before such waste is scheduled to leave the United States. A complete notification should be submitted sixty (60) days before the initial shipment is intended to be shipped off site. This notification may cover export activities extending over a twelve (12) month or lesser period. The notification must be in writing, signed by the primary exporter, and include the following information:</P>
        <P>(1) Name, mailing address, telephone number and EPA ID number of the primary exporter;</P>
        <P>(2) By consignee, for each hazardous waste type:</P>
        <P>(i) A description of the hazardous waste and the EPA hazardous waste number (from 40 CFR part 261, subparts C and D), U.S. DOT proper shipping name, hazard class and ID number (UN/NA) for each hazardous waste as identified in 49 CFR parts 171 through 177;</P>
        <P>(ii) The estimated frequency or rate at which such waste is to be exported and the period of time over which such waste is to be exported.</P>
        <P>(iii) The estimated total quantity of the hazardous waste in units as specified in the instructions to the Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest Form (8700-22);</P>
        <P>(iv) All points of entry to and departure from each foreign country through which the hazardous waste will pass;</P>
        <P>(v) A description of the means by which each shipment of the hazardous waste will be transported (e.g., mode of transportation vehicle (air, highway, rail, water, etc.), type(s) of container (drums, boxes, tanks, etc.));</P>
        <P>(vi) A description of the manner in which the hazardous waste will be treated, stored or disposed of in the receiving country (e.g., land or ocean incineration, other land disposal, ocean dumping, recycling);</P>
        <P>(vii) The name and site address of the consignee and any alternate consignee; and</P>
        <P>(viii) The name of any transit countries through which the hazardous waste will be sent and a description of the approximate length of time the hazardous waste will remain in such country and the nature of its handling while there;</P>

        <P>(b) Notifications submitted by mail should be sent to the following mailing address: Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20460. Hand-delivered notifications should be sent to: Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division, Environmental Protection Agency, Ariel Rios Bldg., Room 6144, 12th St. and Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20004. In both cases, the following shall be prominently displayed on the front of the envelope: “Attention: Notification of Intent to Export.”.<PRTPAGE P="370"/>
        </P>
        <P>(c) Except for changes to the telephone number in paragraph (a)(1) of this section, changes to paragraph (a)(2)(v) of this section and decreases in the quantity indicated pursuant to paragraph (a)(2)(iii) of this section when the conditions specified on the original notification change (including any exceedance of the estimate of the quantity of hazardous waste specified in the original notification), the primary exporter must provide EPA with a written renotification of the change. The shipment cannot take place until consent of the receiving country to the changes (except for changes to paragraph (a)(2)(viii) of this section and in the ports of entry to and departure from transit countries pursuant to paragraph (a)(2)(iv) of this section) has been obtained and the primary exporter receives an EPA Acknowledgment of Consent reflecting the receiving country's consent to the changes.</P>
        <P>(d) Upon request by EPA, a primary exporter shall furnish to EPA any additional information which a receiving country requests in order to respond to a notification.</P>
        <P>(e) In conjunction with the Department of State, EPA will provide a complete notification to the receiving country and any transit countries. A notification is complete when EPA receives a notification which EPA determines satisfies the requirements of paragraph (a) of this section. Where a claim of confidentiality is asserted with respect to any notification information required by paragraph (a) of this section, EPA may find the notification not complete until any such claim is resolved in accordance with 40 CFR 260.2.</P>
        <P>(f) Where the receiving country consents to the receipt of the hazardous waste, EPA will forward an EPA Acknowledgment of Consent to the primary exporter for purposes of § 262.54(h). Where the receiving country objects to receipt of the hazardous waste or withdraws a prior consent, EPA will notify the primary exporter in writing. EPA will also notify the primary exporter of any responses from transit countries.</P>
        <CITA>[51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986, as amended at 56 FR 43705, Sept. 4, 1991; 61 FR 16309, Apr. 12, 1996; 71 FR 40271, July 14, 2006]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.54</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Special manifest requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A primary exporter must comply with the manifest requirements of 40 CFR 262.20 through 262.23 except that:</P>
        <P>(a) In lieu of the name, site address and EPA ID number of the designated permitted facility, the primary exporter must enter the name and site address of the consignee;</P>
        <P>(b) In lieu of the name, site address and EPA ID number of a permitted alternate facility, the primary exporter may enter the name and site address of any alternate consignee.</P>
        <P>(c) In the International Shipments block, the primary exporter must check the export box and enter the point of exit (city and State) from the United States.</P>
        <P>(d) The following statement must be added to the end of the first sentence of the certification set forth in Item 16 of the Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest Form: “and conforms to the terms of the attached EPA Acknowledgment of Consent”;</P>

        <P>(e) The primary exporter may obtain the manifest from any source that is registered with the U.S. EPA as a supplier of manifests (<E T="03">e.g.</E>, states, waste handlers, and/or commercial forms printers).</P>
        <P>(f) The primary exporter must require the consignee to confirm in writing the delivery of the hazardous waste to that facility and to describe any significant discrepancies (as defined in 40 CFR 264.72(a)) between the manifest and the shipment. A copy of the manifest signed by such facility may be used to confirm delivery of the hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>(g) In lieu of the requirements of § 262.20(d), where a shipment cannot be delivered for any reason to the designated or alternate consignee, the primary exporter must:</P>
        <P>(1) Renotify EPA of a change in the conditions of the original notification to allow shipment to a new consignee in accordance with § 262.53(c) and obtain an EPA Acknowledgment of Consent prior to delivery; or</P>

        <P>(2) Instruct the transporter to return the waste to the primary exporter in the United States or designate another facility within the United States; and<PRTPAGE P="371"/>
        </P>
        <P>(3) Instruct the transporter to revise the manifest in accordance with the primary exporter's instructions.</P>
        <P>(h) The primary exporter must attach a copy of the EPA Acknowledgment of Consent to the shipment to the manifest which must accompany the hazardous waste shipment. For exports by rail or water (bulk shipment), the primary exporter must provide the transporter with an EPA Acknowledgment of Consent which must accompany the hazardous waste but which need not be attached to the manifest except that for exports by water (bulk shipment) the primary exporter must attach the copy of the EPA Acknowledgment of Consent to the shipping paper.</P>
        <P>(i) The primary exporter shall provide the transporter with an additional copy of the manifest for delivery to the U.S. Customs official at the point the hazardous waste leaves the United States in accordance with § 263.20(g)(4).</P>
        <CITA>[51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986, as amended at 70 FR 10818, Mar. 4, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.55</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exception reports.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In lieu of the requirements of § 262.42, a primary exporter must file an exception report with the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, if any of the following occurs:</P>
        <P>(a) He has not received a copy of the manifest signed by the transporter stating the date and place of departure from the United States within forty-five (45) days from the date it was accepted by the initial transporter;</P>
        <P>(b) Within ninety (90) days from the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter, the primary exporter has not received written confirmation from the consignee that the hazardous waste was received;</P>
        <P>(c) The waste is returned to the United States.</P>
        <CITA>[51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986, as amended at 75 FR 1253, Jan. 8, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.56</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Annual reports.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Primary exporters of hazardous waste shall file with the Administrator no later than March 1 of each year, a report summarizing the types, quantities, frequency, and ultimate destination of all hazardous waste exported during the previous calendar year. Such reports shall include the following:</P>
        <P>(1) The EPA identification number, name, and mailing and site address of the exporter;</P>
        <P>(2) The calendar year covered by the report;</P>
        <P>(3) The name and site address of each consignee;</P>
        <P>(4) By consignee, for each hazardous waste exported, a description of the hazardous waste, the EPA hazardous waste number (from 40 CFR part 261, subpart C or D), DOT hazard class, the name and US EPA ID number (where applicable) for each transporter used, the total amount of waste shipped and number of shipments pursuant to each notification;</P>
        <P>(5) Except for hazardous waste produced by exporters of greater than 100 kg but less than 1000 kg in a calendar month, unless provided pursuant to § 262.41, in even numbered years:</P>
        <P>(i) A description of the efforts undertaken during the year to reduce the volume and toxicity of waste generated; and</P>
        <P>(ii) A description of the changes in volume and toxicity of waste actually achieved during the year in comparison to previous years to the extent such information is available for years prior to 1984.</P>
        <P>(6) A certification signed by the primary exporter which states:</P>
        <P>I certify under penalty of law that I have personally examined and am familiar with the information submitted in this and all attached documents, and that based on my inquiry of those individuals immediately responsible for obtaining the information, I believe that the submitted information is true, accurate, and complete. I am aware that there are significant penalties for submitting false information including the possibility of fine and imprisonment.</P>

        <P>(b) Annual reports submitted by mail should be sent to the following mailing address: Office of Enforcement and <PRTPAGE P="372"/>Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20460. Hand-delivered reports should be sent to: Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division, Environmental Protection Agency, Ariel Rios Bldg., Room 6144, 12th St. and Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20004.</P>
        <CITA>[51 FR 28682, Aug. 8, 1986, as amended at 56 FR 43705, Sept. 4, 1991; 61 FR 16309, Apr. 12, 1996; 71 FR 40271, July 14, 2006]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.57</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) For all exports a primary exporter must:</P>
        <P>(1) Keep a copy of each notification of intent to export for a period of at least three years from the date the hazardous waste was accepted by the initial transporter;</P>
        <P>(2) Keep a copy of each EPA Acknowledgment of Consent for a period of at least three years from the date the hazardous waste was accepted by the initial transporter;</P>
        <P>(3) Keep a copy of each confirmation of delivery of the hazardous waste from the consignee for at least three years from the date the hazardous waste was accepted by the initial transporter; and</P>
        <P>(4) Keep a copy of each annual report for a period of at least three years from the due date of the report.</P>
        <P>(b) The periods of retention referred to in this section are extended automatically during the course of any unresolved enforcement action regarding the regulated activity or as requested by the Administrator.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.58</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>International agreements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Any person who exports or imports wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures to or from designated Member countries of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) as defined in paragraph (a)(1) of this section for purposes of recovery is subject to subpart H of this part. The requirements of subparts E and F of this part do not apply to such exports and imports. A waste is considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures if the waste meets the Federal definition of hazardous waste in 40 CFR 261.3 and is subject to either the Federal RCRA manifesting requirements at 40 CFR part 262, subpart B, the universal waste management standards of 40 CFR part 273, State requirements analogous to 40 CFR part 273, the export requirements in the spent lead-acid battery management standards of 40 CFR part 266, subpart G, or State requirements analogous to the export requirements in 40 CFR part 266, subpart G.</P>
        <P>(1) For the purposes of subpart H, the designated OECD Member countries consist of Australia, Austria, Belgium, the Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Poland, Portugal, the Republic of Korea, the Slovak Republic, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey, the United Kingdom, and the United States.</P>
        <P>(2) For the purposes of subpart H of this part, Canada and Mexico are considered OECD Member countries only for the purpose of transit.</P>

        <P>(b) Any person who exports hazardous waste to or imports hazardous waste from: A designated OECD Member country for purposes other than recovery (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> incineration, disposal), Mexico (for any purpose), or Canada (for any purpose) remains subject to the requirements of subparts E and F of this part, and is not subject to the requirements of subpart H of this part.</P>
        <CITA>[75 FR 1253, Jan. 8, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart F—Imports of Hazardous Waste</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.60</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Imports of hazardous waste.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Any person who imports hazardous waste from a foreign country into the United States must comply with the requirements of this part and the special requirements of this subpart.</P>

        <P>(b) When importing hazardous waste, a person must meet all the requirements of § 262.20 for the manifest except that:<PRTPAGE P="373"/>
        </P>
        <P>(1) In place of the generator's name, address and EPA identification number, the name and address of the foreign generator and the importer's name, address and EPA identification number must be used.</P>
        <P>(2) In place of the generator's signature on the certification statement, the U.S. importer or his agent must sign and date the certification and obtain the signature of the initial transporter.</P>

        <P>(c) A person who imports hazardous waste may obtain the manifest form from any source that is registered with the U.S. EPA as a supplier of manifests (<E T="03">e.g.</E>, states, waste handlers, and/or commercial forms printers).</P>
        <P>(d) In the International Shipments block, the importer must check the import box and enter the point of entry (city and State) into the United States.</P>
        <P>(e) The importer must provide the transporter with an additional copy of the manifest to be submitted by the receiving facility to U.S. EPA in accordance with § 264.71(a)(3) and § 265.71(a)(3) of this chapter.</P>
        <CITA>[51 FR 28685, Aug. 8, 1986, as amended at 70 FR 10818, Mar. 4, 2005; 75 FR 13005, Mar. 18, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart G—Farmers</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.70</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Farmers.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A farmer disposing of waste pesticides from his own use which are hazardous wastes is not required to comply with the standards in this part or other standards in 40 CFR parts 264, 265, 268, or 270 for those wastes provided he triple rinses each emptied pesticide container in accordance with § 261.7(b)(3) and disposes of the pesticide residues on his own farm in a manner consistent with the disposal instructions on the pesticide label.</P>
        <CITA>[53 FR 27165, July 19, 1988, as amended at 71 FR 40271, July 14, 2006]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart H—Transboundary Movements of Hazardous Waste for Recovery Within the OECD</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>75 FR 1253, Jan. 8, 2010, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.80</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The requirements of this subpart apply to imports and exports of wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures and are destined for recovery operations in the countries listed in § 262.58(a)(1). A waste is considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures if the waste:</P>
        <P>(1) Meets the Federal definition of hazardous waste in 40 CFR 261.3; and</P>
        <P>(2) Is subject to either the Federal RCRA manifesting requirements at 40 CFR part 262, subpart B, the universal waste management standards of 40 CFR part 273, State requirements analogous to 40 CFR part 273, the export requirements in the spent lead-acid battery management standards of 40 CFR part 266, subpart G, or State requirements analogous to the export requirements in 40 CFR part 266, subpart G.</P>
        <P>(b) Any person (exporter, importer, or recovery facility operator) who mixes two or more wastes (including hazardous and non-hazardous wastes) or otherwise subjects two or more wastes (including hazardous and non-hazardous wastes) to physical or chemical transformation operations, and thereby creates a new hazardous waste, becomes a generator and assumes all subsequent generator duties under RCRA and any exporter duties, if applicable, under this subpart.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.81</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The following definitions apply to this subpart.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Competent authority</E> means the regulatory authority or authorities of concerned countries having jurisdiction over transboundary movements of wastes destined for recovery operations.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Countries concerned</E> means the OECD Member countries of export or import and any OECD Member countries of transit.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Country of export</E> means any designated OECD Member country listed in § 262.58(a)(1) from which a transboundary movement of hazardous wastes is planned to be initiated or is initiated.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Country of import</E> means any designated OECD Member country listed in § 262.58(a)(1) to which a transboundary movement of hazardous wastes is <PRTPAGE P="374"/>planned or takes place for the purpose of submitting the wastes to recovery operations therein.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Country of transit</E> means any designated OECD Member country listed in § 262.58(a)(1) and (a)(2) other than the country of export or country of import across which a transboundary movement of hazardous wastes is planned or takes place.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Exporter</E> means the person under the jurisdiction of the country of export who has, or will have at the time the planned transboundary movement commences, possession or other forms of legal control of the wastes and who proposes transboundary movement of the hazardous wastes for the ultimate purpose of submitting them to recovery operations. When the United States (U.S.) is the country of export, <E T="03">exporter</E> is interpreted to mean a person domiciled in the United States.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Importer</E> means the person to whom possession or other form of legal control of the waste is assigned at the time the waste is received in the country of import.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">OECD area</E> means all land or marine areas under the national jurisdiction of any OECD Member country listed in § 262.58. When the regulations refer to shipments to or from an OECD Member country, this means OECD area.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">OECD</E> means the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Recognized trader</E> means a person who, with appropriate authorization of countries concerned, acts in the role of principal to purchase and subsequently sell wastes; this person has legal control of such wastes from time of purchase to time of sale; such a person may act to arrange and facilitate transboundary movements of wastes destined for recovery operations.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Recovery facility</E> means a facility which, under applicable domestic law, is operating or is authorized to operate in the country of import to receive wastes and to perform recovery operations on them.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Recovery operations</E> means activities leading to resource recovery, recycling, reclamation, direct re-use or alternative uses, which include:
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R1Use as a fuel (other than in direct incineration) or other means to generate energy.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R2Solvent reclamation/regeneration.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R3Recycling/reclamation of organic substances which are not used as solvents.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R4Recycling/reclamation of metals and metal compounds.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R5Recycling/reclamation of other inorganic materials.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R6Regeneration of acids or bases.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R7Recovery of components used for pollution abatement.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R8Recovery of components used from catalysts.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R9Used oil re-refining or other reuses of previously used oil.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R10Land treatment resulting in benefit to agriculture or ecological improvement.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R11Uses of residual materials obtained from any of the operations numbered R1-R10.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R12Exchange of wastes for submission to any of the operations numbered R1-R11.</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-2">R13Accumulation of material intended for any operation numbered R1-R12.</FP>
        
        <P>
          <E T="03">Transboundary movement</E> means any movement of wastes from an area under the national jurisdiction of one OECD Member country to an area under the national jurisdiction of another OECD Member country.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.82</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General conditions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Scope.</E> The level of control for exports and imports of waste is indicated by assignment of the waste to either a list of wastes subject to the Green control procedures or a list of wastes subject to the Amber control procedures and by the national procedures of the United States, as defined in § 262.80(a). The OECD Green and Amber lists are incorporated by reference in § 262.89(d).</P>
        <P>(1) <E T="03">Listed wastes subject to the Green control procedures.</E> (i) Green wastes that are not considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a) are subject to existing controls normally applied to commercial transactions.<PRTPAGE P="375"/>
        </P>
        <P>(ii) Green wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a) are subject to the Amber control procedures set forth in this subpart.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Listed wastes subject to the Amber control procedures.</E> (i) Amber wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a) are subject to the Amber control procedures set forth in this subpart.</P>
        <P>(ii) Amber wastes that are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a), are subject to the Amber control procedures in the United States, even if they are imported to or exported from a designated OECD Member country listed in § 262.58(a)(1) that does not consider the waste to be hazardous. In such an event, the responsibilities of the Amber control procedures shift as provided:</P>
        <P>(A) For U.S. exports, the United States shall issue an acknowledgement of receipt and assume other responsibilities of the competent authority of the country of import.</P>
        <P>(B) For U.S. imports, the U.S. recovery facility/importer and the United States shall assume the obligations associated with the Amber control procedures that normally apply to the exporter and country of export, respectively.</P>

        <P>(iii) Amber wastes that are not considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a), but are considered hazardous by an OECD Member country are subject to the Amber control procedures in the OECD Member country that considers the waste hazardous. All responsibilities of the U.S. importer/exporter shift to the importer/exporter of the OECD Member country that considers the waste hazardous unless the parties make other arrangements through contracts.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">a</E>)(2):</HD>

          <P>Some wastes subject to the Amber control procedures are not listed or otherwise identified as hazardous under RCRA, and therefore are not subject to the Amber control procedures of this subpart. Regardless of the status of the waste under RCRA, however, other Federal environmental statutes (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> the Toxic Substances Control Act) restrict certain waste imports or exports. Such restrictions continue to apply with regard to this subpart.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Procedures for mixtures of wastes.</E> (i) A Green waste that is mixed with one or more other Green wastes such that the resulting mixture is not considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a) shall be subject to the Green control procedures, provided the composition of this mixture does not impair its environmentally sound recovery.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">a</E>)(3)(<E T="01">i</E>):</HD>
          <P>The regulated community should note that some OECD Member countries may require, by domestic law, that mixtures of different Green wastes be subject to the Amber control procedures.</P>
        </NOTE>
        

        <P>(ii) A Green waste that is mixed with one or more Amber wastes, in any amount, <E T="03">de minimis</E> or otherwise, or a mixture of two or more Amber wastes, such that the resulting waste mixture is considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a) are subject to the Amber control procedures, provided the composition of this mixture does not impair its environmentally sound recovery.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">a</E>)(3)(<E T="01">ii</E>):</HD>

          <P>The regulated community should note that some OECD Member countries may require, by domestic law, that a mixture of a Green waste and more than a <E T="03">de minimis</E> amount of an Amber waste or a mixture of two or more Amber wastes be subject to the Amber control procedures.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(4) Wastes not yet assigned to an OECD waste list are eligible for transboundary movements, as follows:</P>
        <P>(i) If such wastes are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a), such wastes are subject to the Amber control procedures.</P>
        <P>(ii) If such wastes are not considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a), such wastes are subject to the Green control procedures.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">General conditions applicable to transboundary movements of hazardous waste:</E> (1) The waste must be destined for recovery operations at a facility that, under applicable domestic law, is operating or is authorized to operate in the importing country;</P>

        <P>(2) The transboundary movement must be in compliance with applicable international transport agreements; and
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <PRTPAGE P="376"/>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">b</E>)(2):</HD>
          <P>These international agreements include, but are not limited to, the Chicago Convention (1944), ADR (1957), ADNR (1970), MARPOL Convention (1973/1978), SOLAS Convention (1974), IMDG Code (1985), COTIF (1985), and RID (1985).</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(3) Any transit of waste through a non-OECD Member country must be conducted in compliance with all applicable international and national laws and regulations.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Provisions relating to re-export for recovery to a third country:</E> (1) Re-export of wastes subject to the Amber control procedures from the United States, as the country of import, to a third country listed in § 262.58(a)(1) may occur only after an exporter in the United States provides notification to and obtains consent from the competent authorities in the third country, the original country of export, and any transit countries. The notification must comply with the notice and consent procedures in § 262.83 for all countries concerned and the original country of export. The competent authorities of the original country of export, as well as the competent authorities of all other countries concerned have thirty (30) days to object to the proposed movement.</P>
        <P>(i) The thirty (30) day period begins once the competent authorities of both the initial country of export and new country of import issue Acknowledgements of Receipt of the notification.</P>
        <P>(ii) The transboundary movement may commence if no objection has been lodged after the thirty (30) day period has passed or immediately after written consent is received from all relevant OECD importing and transit countries.</P>
        <P>(2) In the case of re-export of Amber wastes to a country other than those listed in § 262.58(a)(1), notification to and consent of the competent authorities of the original OECD Member country of export and any OECD Member countries of transit is required as specified in paragraph (c)(1) of this section, in addition to compliance with all international agreements and arrangements to which the first importing OECD Member country is a party and all applicable regulatory requirements for exports from the first country of import.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Duty to return or re-export wastes subject to the Amber control procedures.</E> When a transboundary movement of wastes subject to the Amber control procedures cannot be completed in accordance with the terms of the contract or the consent(s) and alternative arrangements cannot be made to recover the waste in an environmentally sound manner in the country of import, the waste must be returned to the country of export or re-exported to a third country. The provisions of paragraph (c) of this section apply to any shipments to be re-exported to a third country. The following provisions apply to shipments to be returned to the country of export as appropriate:</P>
        <P>(1) Return from the United States to the country of export: The U.S. importer must inform EPA at the specified address in § 262.83(b)(1)(i) of the need to return the shipment. EPA will then inform the competent authorities of the countries of export and transit, citing the reason(s) for returning the waste. The U.S. importer must complete the return within ninety (90) days from the time EPA informs the country of export of the need to return the waste, unless informed in writing by EPA of another timeframe agreed to by the concerned Member countries. If the return shipment will cross any transit country, the return shipment may only occur after EPA provides notification to and obtains consent from the competent authority of the country of transit, and provides a copy of that consent to the U.S. importer.</P>
        <P>(2) Return from the country of import to the United States: The U.S. exporter must provide for the return of the hazardous waste shipment within ninety (90) days from the time the country of import informs EPA of the need to return the waste or such other period of time as the concerned Member countries agree. The U.S. exporter must submit an exception report to EPA in accordance with § 262.87(b).</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Duty to return wastes subject to the Amber control procedures from a country of transit.</E> When a transboundary movement of wastes subject to the Amber control procedures does not comply with the requirements of the notification and movement documents or otherwise constitutes illegal shipment, <PRTPAGE P="377"/>and if alternative arrangements cannot be made to recover these wastes in an environmentally sound manner, the waste must be returned to the country of export. The following provisions apply as appropriate:</P>
        <P>(1) Return from the United States (as country of transit) to the country of export: The U.S. transporter must inform EPA at the specified address in § 262.83(b)(1)(i) of the need to return the shipment. EPA will then inform the competent authority of the country of export, citing the reason(s) for returning the waste. The U.S. transporter must complete the return within ninety (90) days from the time EPA informs the country of export of the need to return the waste, unless informed in writing by EPA of another timeframe agreed to by the concerned Member countries.</P>
        <P>(2) Return from the country of transit to the United States (as country of export): The U.S. exporter must provide for the return of the hazardous waste shipment within ninety (90) days from the time the competent authority of the country of transit informs EPA of the need to return the waste or such other period of time as the concerned Member countries agree. The U.S. exporter must submit an exception report to EPA in accordance with § 262.87(b).</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Requirements for wastes destined for and received by R12 and R13 facilities.</E> The transboundary movement of wastes destined for R12 and R13 operations must comply with all Amber control procedures for notification and consent as set forth in § 262.83 and for the movement document as set forth in § 262.84. Additional responsibilities of R12/R13 facilities include:</P>
        <P>(1) Indicating in the notification document the foreseen recovery facility or facilities where the subsequent R1-R11 recovery operation takes place or may take place.</P>
        <P>(2) Within three (3) days of the receipt of the wastes by the R12/R13 recovery facility or facilities, the facility(ies) shall return a signed copy of the movement document to the exporter and to the competent authorities of the countries of export and import. The facility(ies) shall retain the original of the movement document for three (3) years.</P>
        <P>(3) As soon as possible, but no later than thirty (30) days after the completion of the R12/R13 recovery operation and no later than one (1) calendar year following the receipt of the waste, the R12 or R13 facility(ies) shall send a certificate of recovery to the foreign exporter and to the competent authority of the country of export and to the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW. Washington, DC 20460, by mail, e-mail without digital signature followed by mail, or fax followed by mail.</P>
        <P>(4) When an R12/R13 recovery facility delivers wastes for recovery to an R1-R11 recovery facility located in the country of import, it shall obtain as soon as possible, but no later than one (1) calendar year following delivery of the waste, a certification from the R1-R11 facility that recovery of the wastes at that facility has been completed. The R12/R13 facility must promptly transmit the applicable certification to the competent authorities of the countries of import and export, identifying the transboundary movements to which the certification pertain.</P>
        <P>(5) When an R12/R13 recovery facility delivers wastes for recovery to an R1-R11 recovery facility located:</P>
        <P>(i) In the initial country of export, Amber control procedures apply, including a new notification;</P>
        <P>(ii) In a third country other than the initial country of export, Amber control procedures apply, with the additional provision that the competent authority of the initial country of export shall also be notified of the transboundary movement.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Laboratory analysis exemption.</E> The transboundary movement of an Amber waste is exempt from the Amber control procedures if it is in certain quantities and destined for laboratory analysis to assess its physical or chemical characteristics, or to determine its suitability for recovery operations. The quantity of such waste shall be determined by the minimum quantity reasonably needed to perform the analysis in each particular case adequately, but <PRTPAGE P="378"/>in no case exceed twenty-five kilograms (25 kg). Waste destined for laboratory analysis must still be appropriately packaged and labeled.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.83</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notification and consent.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Applicability.</E> Consent must be obtained from the competent authorities of the relevant OECD countries of import and transit prior to exporting hazardous waste destined for recovery operations subject to this subpart. Hazardous wastes subject to the Amber control procedures are subject to the requirements of paragraph (b) of this section; and wastes not identified on any list are subject to the requirements of paragraph (c) of this section.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Amber wastes.</E> Exports of hazardous wastes from the United States as described in § 262.80(a) that are subject to the Amber control procedures are prohibited unless the notification and consent requirements of paragraph (b)(1) or paragraph (b)(2) of this section are met.</P>
        <P>(1) Transactions requiring specific consent:</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Notification.</E> At least forty-five (45) days prior to commencement of each transboundary movement, the exporter must provide written notification in English of the proposed transboundary movement to the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, with the words “Attention: OECD Export Notification” prominently displayed on the envelope. This notification must include all of the information identified in paragraph (d) of this section. In cases where wastes having similar physical and chemical characteristics, the same United Nations classification, the same RCRA waste codes, and are to be sent periodically to the same recovery facility by the same exporter, the exporter may submit one general notification of intent to export these wastes in multiple shipments during a period of up to one (1) year. Even when a general notification is used for multiple shipments, each shipment still must be accompanied by its own movement document pursuant to § 262.84.</P>
        <P>(ii) <E T="03">Tacit consent.</E> If no objection has been lodged by any countries concerned (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> exporting, importing, or transit) to a notification provided pursuant to paragraph (b)(1)(i) of this section within thirty (30) days after the date of issuance of the Acknowledgement of Receipt of notification by the competent authority of the country of import, the transboundary movement may commence. Tacit consent expires one (1) calendar year after the close of the thirty (30) day period; renotification and renewal of all consents is required for exports after that date.</P>
        <P>(iii) <E T="03">Written consent.</E> If the competent authorities of all the relevant OECD importing and transit countries provide written consent in a period less than thirty (30) days, the transboundary movement may commence immediately after all necessary consents are received. Written consent expires for each relevant OECD importing and transit country one (1) calendar year after the date of that country's consent unless otherwise specified; renotification and renewal of each expired consent is required for exports after that date.</P>
        <P>(2) Transboundary movements to facilities pre-approved by the competent authorities of the importing countries to accept specific wastes for recovery:</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Notification.</E> The exporter must provide EPA a notification that contains all the information identified in paragraph (d) of this section in English, at least ten (10) days in advance of commencing shipment to a pre-approved facility. The notification must indicate that the recovery facility is pre-approved, and may apply to a single specific shipment or to multiple shipments as described in paragraph (b)(1)(i) of this section. This information must be sent to the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, with the words “OECD Export Notification—Pre-approved Facility” prominently displayed on the envelope. General notifications that cover multiple shipments as described in paragraph <PRTPAGE P="379"/>(b)(1)(i) of this section may cover a period of up to three (3) years. Even when a general notification is used for multiple shipments, each shipment still must be accompanied by its own movement document pursuant to § 262.84.</P>
        <P>(ii) Exports to pre-approved facilities may take place after the elapse of seven (7) working days from the issuance of an Acknowledgement of Receipt of the notification by the competent authority of the country of import unless the exporter has received information indicating that the competent authority of any countries concerned objects to the shipment.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Wastes not covered in the OECD Green and Amber lists.</E> Wastes destined for recovery operations, that have not been assigned to the OECD Green and Amber lists, incorporated by reference in § 262.89(d), but which are considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined in § 262.80(a), are subject to the notification and consent requirements established for the Amber control procedures in accordance with paragraph (b) of this section. Wastes destined for recovery operations, that have not been assigned to the OECD Green and Amber lists incorporated by reference in § 262.89(d), and are not considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures as defined by § 262.80(a) are subject to the Green control procedures.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Notifications submitted under this section must include the information specified in paragraphs (d)(1) through (d)(14) of this section:</E> (1) Serial number or other accepted identifier of the notification document;</P>
        <P>(2) Exporter name and EPA identification number (if applicable), address, telephone, fax numbers, and e-mail address;</P>
        <P>(3) Importing recovery facility name, address, telephone, fax numbers, e-mail address, and technologies employed;</P>
        <P>(4) Importer name (if not the owner or operator of the recovery facility), address, telephone, fax numbers, and e-mail address; whether the importer will engage in waste exchange recovery operation R12 or waste accumulation recovery operation R13 prior to delivering the waste to the final recovery facility and identification of recovery operations to be employed at the final recovery facility;</P>
        <P>(5) Intended transporter(s) and/or their agent(s); address, telephone, fax, and e-mail address;</P>
        <P>(6) Country of export and relevant competent authority, and point of departure;</P>
        <P>(7) Countries of transit and relevant competent authorities and points of entry and departure;</P>
        <P>(8) Country of import and relevant competent authority, and point of entry;</P>
        <P>(9) Statement of whether the notification is a single notification or a general notification. If general, include period of validity requested;</P>
        <P>(10) Date(s) foreseen for commencement of transboundary movement(s);</P>
        <P>(11) Means of transport envisaged;</P>
        <P>(12) Designation of waste type(s) from the appropriate OECD list incorporated by reference in § 262.89(d), description(s) of each waste type, estimated total quantity of each, RCRA waste code, and the United Nations number for each waste type;</P>
        <P>(13) Specification of the recovery operation(s) as defined in § 262.81.</P>

        <P>(14) Certification/Declaration signed by the exporter that states:
        </P>
        <EXTRACT>
          <P>I certify that the above information is complete and correct to the best of my knowledge. I also certify that legally-enforceable written contractual obligations have been entered into, and that any applicable insurance or other financial guarantees are or shall be in force covering the transboundary movement.</P>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name:</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature:</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date:</FP>
        </EXTRACT>
        
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">d</E>)(14):</HD>
          <P>The United States does not currently require financial assurance for these waste shipments. However, U.S. exporters may be asked by other governments to provide and certify to such assurance as a condition of obtaining consent to a proposed movement.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Certificate of Recovery.</E> As soon as possible, but no later than thirty (30) days after the completion of recovery and no later than one (1) calendar year following receipt of the waste, the U.S. recovery facility shall send a certificate of recovery to the exporter and to the competent authorities of the countries of export and import by mail, e-<PRTPAGE P="380"/>mail without a digital signature followed by mail, or fax followed by mail. The certificate of recovery shall include a signed, written and dated statement that affirms that the waste materials were recovered in the manner agreed to by the parties to the contract required under § 262.85.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.84</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Movement document.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) All U.S. parties subject to the contract provisions of § 262.85 must ensure that a movement document meeting the conditions of paragraph (b) of this section accompanies each transboundary movement of wastes subject to the Amber control procedures from the initiation of the shipment until it reaches the final recovery facility, including cases in which the waste is stored and/or sorted by the importer prior to shipment to the final recovery facility, except as provided in paragraphs (a)(1) and (2) of this section.</P>
        <P>(1) For shipments of hazardous waste within the United States solely by water (bulk shipments only), the generator must forward the movement document with the manifest to the last water (bulk shipment) transporter to handle the waste in the United States if exported by water, (in accordance with the manifest routing procedures at § 262.23(c)).</P>
        <P>(2) For rail shipments of hazardous waste within the United States which originate at the site of generation, the generator must forward the movement document with the manifest (in accordance with the routing procedures for the manifest in § 262.23(d)) to the next non-rail transporter, if any, or the last rail transporter to handle the waste in the United States if exported by rail.</P>
        <P>(b) The movement document must include all information required under § 262.83 (for notification), as well as the following paragraphs (b)(1) through (b)(7) of this section:</P>
        <P>(1) Date movement commenced;</P>
        <P>(2) Name (if not exporter), address, telephone, fax numbers, and e-mail of primary exporter;</P>
        <P>(3) Company name and EPA ID number of all transporters;</P>
        <P>(4) Identification (license, registered name or registration number) of means of transport, including types of packaging envisaged;</P>
        <P>(5) Any special precautions to be taken by transporter(s);</P>

        <P>(6) Certification/declaration signed by the exporter that no objection to the shipment has been lodged, as follows:
        </P>
        <EXTRACT>
          <P>I certify that the above information is complete and correct to the best of my knowledge. I also certify that legally-enforceable written contractual obligations have been entered into, that any applicable insurance or other financial guarantees are or shall be in force covering the transboundary movement, and that:</P>
          <P>1. All necessary consents have been received; OR</P>
          <P>2. The shipment is directed to a recovery facility within the OECD area and no objection has been received from any of the countries concerned within the thirty (30) day tacit consent period; OR</P>

          <P>3. The shipment is directed to a recovery facility pre-approved for that type of waste within the OECD area; such an authorization has not been revoked, and no objection has been received from any of the countries concerned.
          </P>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-1">(Delete sentences that are not applicable)</FP>
          
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name:</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature:</FP>
          <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date:</FP>
        </EXTRACT>
        
        <P>(7) Appropriate signatures for each custody transfer (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> transporter, importer, and owner or operator of the recovery facility).</P>
        <P>(c) Exporters also must comply with the special manifest requirements of 40 CFR 262.54(a), (b), (c), (e), and (i) and importers must comply with the import requirements of 40 CFR part 262, subpart F.</P>

        <P>(d) Each U.S. person that has physical custody of the waste from the time the movement commences until it arrives at the recovery facility must sign the movement document (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> transporter, importer, and owner or operator of the recovery facility).</P>

        <P>(e) Within three (3) working days of the receipt of imports subject to this subpart, the owner or operator of the U.S. recovery facility must send signed copies of the movement document to the exporter, to the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, and to the competent authorities of the countries of export <PRTPAGE P="381"/>and transit. If the concerned U.S. recovery facility is a R12/R13 recovery facility as defined under § 262.81, the facility shall retain the original of the movement document for three (3) years.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.85</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Contracts.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Transboundary movements of hazardous wastes subject to the Amber control procedures are prohibited unless they occur under the terms of a valid written contract, chain of contracts, or equivalent arrangements (when the movement occurs between parties controlled by the same corporate or legal entity). Such contracts or equivalent arrangements must be executed by the exporter and the owner or operator of the recovery facility, and must specify responsibilities for each. Contracts or equivalent arrangements are valid for the purposes of this section only if persons assuming obligations under the contracts or equivalent arrangements have appropriate legal status to conduct the operations specified in the contract or equivalent arrangements.</P>
        <P>(b) Contracts or equivalent arrangements must specify the name and EPA ID number, where available, of paragraph (b)(1) through (b)(4) of this section:</P>
        <P>(1) The generator of each type of waste;</P>
        <P>(2) Each person who will have physical custody of the wastes;</P>
        <P>(3) Each person who will have legal control of the wastes; and</P>
        <P>(4) The recovery facility.</P>
        <P>(c) Contracts or equivalent arrangements must specify which party to the contract will assume responsibility for alternate management of the wastes if their disposition cannot be carried out as described in the notification of intent to export. In such cases, contracts must specify that:</P>
        <P>(1) The person having actual possession or physical control over the wastes will immediately inform the exporter and the competent authorities of the countries of export and import and, if the wastes are located in a country of transit, the competent authorities of that country; and</P>
        <P>(2) The person specified in the contract will assume responsibility for the adequate management of the wastes in compliance with applicable laws and regulations including, if necessary, arranging the return of wastes and, as the case may be, shall provide the notification for re-export.</P>
        <P>(d) Contracts must specify that the importer will provide the notification required in § 262.82(c) prior to the re-export of controlled wastes to a third country.</P>

        <P>(e) Contracts or equivalent arrangements must include provisions for financial guarantees, if required by the competent authorities of any countries concerned, in accordance with applicable national or international law requirements.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">e</E>):</HD>
          <P>Financial guarantees so required are intended to provide for alternate recycling, disposal or other means of sound management of the wastes in cases where arrangements for the shipment and the recovery operations cannot be carried out as foreseen. The United States does not require such financial guarantees at this time; however, some OECD Member countries do. It is the responsibility of the exporter to ascertain and comply with such requirements; in some cases, transporters or importers may refuse to enter into the necessary contracts absent specific references or certifications to financial guarantees.</P>
        </NOTE>
        
        <P>(f) Contracts or equivalent arrangements must contain provisions requiring each contracting party to comply with all applicable requirements of this subpart.</P>

        <P>(g) Upon request by EPA, U.S. exporters, importers, or recovery facilities must submit to EPA copies of contracts, chain of contracts, or equivalent arrangements (when the movement occurs between parties controlled by the same corporate or legal entity). Information contained in the contracts or equivalent arrangements for which a claim of confidentiality is asserted in accordance with 40 CFR 2.203(b) will be treated as confidential and will be disclosed by EPA only as provided in 40 CFR 260.2.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">g</E>):</HD>

          <P>Although the United States does not require routine submission of contracts at this time, the OECD Decision allows Member countries to impose such requirements. When other OECD Member countries require submission of partial <PRTPAGE P="382"/>or complete copies of the contract as a condition to granting consent to proposed movements, EPA will request the required information; absent submission of such information, some OECD Member countries may deny consent for the proposed movement.</P>
        </NOTE>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.86</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Provisions relating to recognized traders.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) A recognized trader who takes physical custody of a waste and conducts recovery operations (including storage prior to recovery) is acting as the owner or operator of a recovery facility and must be so authorized in accordance with all applicable Federal laws.</P>
        <P>(b) A recognized trader acting as an exporter or importer for transboundary shipments of waste must comply with all the requirements of this subpart associated with being an exporter or importer.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.87</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Reporting and recordkeeping.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Annual reports.</E> For all waste movements subject to this subpart, persons (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> exporters, recognized traders) who meet the definition of primary exporter in § 262.51 or who initiate the movement documentation under § 262.84 shall file an annual report with the Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, no later than March 1 of each year summarizing the types, quantities, frequency, and ultimate destination of all such hazardous waste exported during the previous calendar year. (If the primary exporter or the person who initiates the movement document under § 262.84 is required to file an annual report for waste exports that are not covered under this subpart, he may include all export information in one report provided the following information on exports of waste destined for recovery within the designated OECD Member countries is contained in a separate section.) Such reports shall include all of the following paragraphs (a)(1) through (a)(6) of this section specified as follows:</P>
        <P>(1) The EPA identification number, name, and mailing and site address of the exporter filing the report;</P>
        <P>(2) The calendar year covered by the report;</P>
        <P>(3) The name and site address of each final recovery facility;</P>
        <P>(4) By final recovery facility, for each hazardous waste exported, a description of the hazardous waste, the EPA hazardous waste number (from 40 CFR part 261, subpart C or D), designation of waste type(s) and applicable waste code(s) from the appropriate OECD waste list incorporated by reference in § 262.89(d), DOT hazard class, the name and U.S. EPA identification number (where applicable) for each transporter used, the total amount of hazardous waste shipped pursuant to this subpart, and number of shipments pursuant to each notification;</P>
        <P>(5) In even numbered years, for each hazardous waste exported, except for hazardous waste produced by exporters of greater than 100kg but less than 1,000kg in a calendar month, and except for hazardous waste for which information was already provided pursuant to § 262.41:</P>
        <P>(i) A description of the efforts undertaken during the year to reduce the volume and toxicity of the waste generated; and</P>
        <P>(ii) A description of the changes in volume and toxicity of the waste actually achieved during the year in comparison to previous years to the extent such information is available for years prior to 1984; and</P>

        <P>(6) A certification signed by the person acting as primary exporter or initiator of the movement document under § 262.84 that states:
        </P>
        <EXTRACT>
          <P>I certify under penalty of law that I have personally examined and am familiar with the information submitted in this and all attached documents, and that based on my inquiry of those individuals immediately responsible for obtaining the information, I believe that the submitted information is true, accurate, and complete. I am aware that there are significant penalties for submitting false information including the possibility of fine and imprisonment.</P>
        </EXTRACT>
        
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Exception reports.</E> Any person who meets the definition of primary exporter in § 262.51 or who initiates the movement document under § 262.84 must file an exception report in lieu of the requirements of § 262.42 (if applicable) with the Office of Enforcement and <PRTPAGE P="383"/>Compliance Assurance, Office of Federal Activities, International Compliance Assurance Division (2254A), Environmental Protection Agency, 1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW., Washington, DC 20460, if any of the following occurs:</P>
        <P>(1) He has not received a copy of the RCRA hazardous waste manifest (if applicable) signed by the transporter identifying the point of departure of the waste from the United States, within forty-five (45) days from the date it was accepted by the initial transporter;</P>
        <P>(2) Within ninety (90) days from the date the waste was accepted by the initial transporter, the exporter has not received written confirmation from the recovery facility that the hazardous waste was received;</P>
        <P>(3) The waste is returned to the United States.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Recordkeeping.</E> (1) Persons who meet the definition of primary exporter in § 262.51 or who initiate the movement document under § 262.84 shall keep the following records in paragraphs (c)(1)(i) through (c)(1)(iv) of this section:</P>
        <P>(i) A copy of each notification of intent to export and all written consents obtained from the competent authorities of countries concerned for a period of at least three (3) years from the date the hazardous waste was accepted by the initial transporter;</P>
        <P>(ii) A copy of each annual report for a period of at least three (3) years from the due date of the report;</P>

        <P>(iii) A copy of any exception reports and a copy of each confirmation of delivery (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> movement document) sent by the recovery facility to the exporter for at least three (3) years from the date the hazardous waste was accepted by the initial transporter or received by the recovery facility, whichever is applicable; and</P>
        <P>(iv) A copy of each certificate of recovery sent by the recovery facility to the exporter for at least three (3) years from the date that the recovery facility completed processing the waste shipment.</P>
        <P>(2) The periods of retention referred to in this section are extended automatically during the course of any unresolved enforcement action regarding the regulated activity or as requested by the Administrator.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.88</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Pre-approval for U.S. recovery facilities [Reserved]</SUBJECT>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.89</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>OECD waste lists.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> For the purposes of this subpart, a waste is considered hazardous under U.S. national procedures, and hence subject to this subpart, if the waste:</P>
        <P>(1) Meets the Federal definition of hazardous waste in 40 CFR 261.3; and</P>
        <P>(2) Is subject to either the Federal RCRA manifesting requirements at 40 CFR part 262, subpart B, the universal waste management standards of 40 CFR part 273, State requirements analogous to 40 CFR part 273, the export requirements in the spent lead-acid battery management standards of 40 CFR part 266, subpart G, or State requirements analogous to the export requirements in 40 CFR part 266, subpart G.</P>
        <P>(b) If a waste is hazardous under paragraph (a) of this section, it is subject to the Amber control procedures, regardless of whether it appears in Appendix 4 of the OECD Decision, as defined in § 262.81.</P>
        <P>(c) The appropriate control procedures for hazardous wastes and hazardous waste mixtures are addressed in § 262.82.</P>

        <P>(d) The OECD waste lists, as set forth in Annex B (“Green List”) and Annex C (“Amber List”) (collectively “OECD waste lists”) of the 2009 “Guidance Manual for the Implementation of Council Decision C(2001)107/FINAL, as Amended, on the Control of Transboundary Movements of Wastes Destined for Recovery Operations,” are incorporated by reference. This incorporation by reference was approved by the Director of the Federal Register in accordance with 5 U.S.C. 552(a) and 1 CFR part 51. This material is incorporated as it exists on the date of the approval and a notice of any change in these materials will be published in the <E T="04">Federal Register.</E> The materials are available for inspection at: the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Docket Center Public Reading Room, EPA West, Room 3334, 1301 Constitution Avenue NW., Washington, DC 20004 (Docket # EPA-HQ-RCRA-2005-0018) or <PRTPAGE P="384"/>at the National Archives and Records Administration (NARA), and may be obtained from the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, Environment Directorate, 2 rue André Pascal, F-75775 Paris Cedex 16, France. For information on the availability of this material at NARA, call 202-741-6030, or go to: <E T="03">http://www.archives.gov/federal-register/cfr/ibr-locations.html.</E> To contact the EPA Docket Center Public Reading Room, call (202) 566-1744. To contact the OECD, call +33 (0) 1 45 24 81 67.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart I—New York State Public Utilities</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>64 FR 37636, July 12, 1999, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.90</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Project XL for Public Utilities in New York State.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The following definitions apply to this section:</P>
        <P>(1) A <E T="03">Utility</E> is any company that operates wholesale and/or retail oil and gas pipelines, or any company that provides electric power or telephone service and is regulated by New York State's Public Service Commission or the New York Power Authority.</P>
        <P>(2) A <E T="03">right-of-way</E> is a fixed, integrated network of aboveground or underground conveyances, including land structures, fixed equipment, and other appurtenances, controlled or owned by a Utility, and used for the purpose of conveying its products or services to customers.</P>
        <P>(3) A <E T="03">remote location</E> is a location in New York State within a Utility's right-of-way network that is not permanently staffed.</P>
        <P>(4) A <E T="03">Utility's central collection facility (UCCF)</E> is a Utility-owned facility within the Utility's right-of-way network to which hazardous waste, generated by the Utility at remote locations within the same right-of-way network, is brought.</P>
        <P>(b) A UCCF designated pursuant to paragraph (e) of this section may consolidate hazardous waste (with the exception of mixed waste) generated by that Utility at its remote locations (and at that UCCF) for up to 90 days without a permit or without having interim status, provided that:</P>
        <P>(1) The Utility complies with all applicable requirements for generators in 40 CFR part 262 (except § 262.34 (d) through (f)) for hazardous waste generated at its remote locations and at the UCCF, including the manifest and pretransport requirements for all shipments greater than 100 kilograms sent from a remote location to a UCCF.</P>
        <P>(2) The Utility transports the hazardous waste from the remote location to a UCCF immediately after collection of all hazardous waste at the remote location is complete or when the staff collecting the hazardous waste leave the remote location, whichever comes first.</P>
        <P>(3) The Utility complies with all applicable requirements for transporters in 40 CFR part 263 for each shipment of hazardous waste greater than 100 kilograms which is sent from remote location to the UCCF, and all applicable Department of Transportation requirements.</P>
        <P>(4)(i) The Utility complies with 40 CFR 262.34 (a) through (c), regardless of the total quantity of hazardous waste generated or consolidated at the UCCF per calendar month;</P>
        <P>(ii) The Utility complies with 40 CFR 264.178; and</P>
        <P>(iii) Secondary containment is provided for all liquid hazardous waste consolidated in containers if:</P>
        <P>(A) The UCCF is consolidating 8,800 gallons or more of liquid hazardous waste, or</P>
        <P>(B) The UCCF is consolidating 185 gallons or more of liquid hazardous waste and is located in an area designated by New York State that overlays a sole-source aquifer.</P>

        <P>(5) The Utility submits a biennial report in accordance with 40 CFR 262.41 including all hazardous waste shipped from remote locations to the UCCF. This UCCF biennial report may be submitted in lieu of submitting a biennial report for each remote location. However, for hazardous waste generated at a particular remote location that exceeds 1000 kg per calendar month and that is not sent to the UCCF, the Utility must submit a separate biennial report.<PRTPAGE P="385"/>
        </P>
        <P>(6) Waste generated at a remote location that is not sent to a UCCF is managed according to the requirements of parts 260 through 270 of this chapter.</P>
        <P>(7) The Utility maintains records at the UCCF in accordance with all the recordkeeping requirements set forth in subpart D of 40 CFR part 262, including 40 CFR 262.40, and maintains records on any PCB test results for hazardous wastes brought to the facility from remote locations.</P>
        <P>(8) The UCCF obtains an EPA identification number.</P>
        <P>(9) The UCCF receives hazardous waste only from its remote location.</P>
        <P>(10) The Utility reinvests at least one-third of the direct savings described in paragraph (h) of this section in one or more environmentally beneficial projects, such as remediation or pollution prevention, that are over and above existing legal requirements and that have not been initiated prior to the Utility's receipt of approval to consolidate hazardous waste pursuant to this section.</P>
        <P>(c) Utilities seeking to have UCCFs designated under paragraph (e) of this section must comply with the following requirements:</P>
        <P>(1) Any New York State Utility seeking approval to consolidate hazardous waste under this section must notify local governments and communities of the Utility's intent to designate specific UCCFs.</P>
        <P>(2) In carrying out paragraph (c)(1) of this section, the Utility must solicit public comment. In soliciting public comment, the Utility must use the notice method set forth in paragraph (c)(2)(i) of this section, as well as at least two of the methods set forth in paragraphs (c)(2)(ii) through (vii) of this section. Each Utility must also notify by mail all parties who commented on the proposed rule for this XL project.</P>
        <P>(i) A public notice in a newspaper of general circulation within the area in which each proposed UCCF is located;</P>
        <P>(ii) A radio announcement in each affected community during peak listening hours;</P>
        <P>(iii) Mailings to all citizens within a five-mile radius of proposed UCCF;</P>
        <P>(iv) Well-publicized community meetings;</P>
        <P>(v) Presentations to the local community board;</P>
        <P>(vi) Placement of copies of this section and the Final Project Agreement that explains the regulatory relief outlined in this section in the local library nearest the proposed UCCF, and inclusion of the name and address of the library in the newspaper notice; and</P>
        <P>(vii) Placement of copies of this section and the Final Project Agreement that explains the regulatory relief outlined in this section on the Utility's web site, and inclusion of the web site's address in the newspaper notice.</P>
        <P>(3) All outreach efforts made under paragraph (c)(2) of this section shall be prepared in English (and any other language spoken by a large number of persons in the community of concern) and at a minimum shall include the following information:</P>
        <P>(i) A brief description of the XL project, the intended new use of the facility, and a request for comments on the proposed UCCF.</P>
        <P>(ii) The name, if any, and address of the proposed UCCF and its current status under the RCRA Subtitle C program.</P>
        <P>(iii) The intended duration of use of the UCCF under the requirements of this section.</P>
        <P>(iv) Names, addresses, and telephone numbers of contact persons, representing the Utility, to whom questions or comments may be directed.</P>
        <P>(v) Notification of when the comment period of no less than 30 days will close.</P>
        <P>(4) Prior to the solicitation of public comment pursuant to paragraph (c)(2) of this section, the Utility must submit copies of each notice, announcement or mailing directly to local governments and to EPA.</P>

        <P>(5) At the close of the comment period, the Utility shall prepare a Responsiveness Package containing a summary of public outreach efforts, all comments and questions received as a result of its outreach efforts, and the Utility's written responses to all comments and questions. The Utility shall provide copies of its Responsiveness Package to any citizens that participated in the public notice process, local governments and EPA.<PRTPAGE P="386"/>
        </P>
        <P>(d) Upon completion of the public notice procedures described in paragraph (c) of this section, the Utility must provide written notice to EPA of its intent to participate. The Notice of Intent must contain the following information:</P>
        <P>(1) The name of the Utility, corporate address, and corporate mailing address, if different.</P>
        <P>(2) The name, mailing address, and telephone number of a corporate-level contact person to whom communications and inquiries may be directed. This contact person may be changed by written notification to EPA.</P>
        <P>(3) A list of the names, addresses, and EPA identification numbers, if applicable, of all Utility-owned facilities in New York State that are proposed UCCFs and the names and telephone numbers of a designated contact person at each facility.</P>
        <P>(4) A summary of public outreach efforts undertaken pursuant to paragraph (c) of this section.</P>
        <P>(5) A commitment that one-third of the direct cost savings outlined in paragraph (h) of this section due to project participation will be reinvested in one or more environmentally beneficial projects which are over and above existing legal requirements and which have not been initiated prior to the Utility's receipt of approval to consolidate hazardous waste pursuant to this section.</P>
        <P>(6) An acknowledgment that the signatory is personally familiar with the terms and conditions of this section and has the authority to obligate and does obligate the Utility to comply with all such terms and conditions. The Utility shall comply with the signatory requirements set forth in 40 CFR 270.11(a)(1).</P>
        <P>(e) The procedures for designating UCCFs are as follows:</P>
        <P>(1) Subject to paragraphs (e)(2) through (5) of this section, the Utility and specified UCCF shall receive approval to comply with the requirements set forth in paragraph (b) of this section upon the receipt of written acknowledgment from EPA that the Notice of Intent described in paragraph (d) of this section has been received and found to be complete and in compliance with all the requirements set forth in paragraph (d) of this section. This acknowledgment will state whether the UCCF has been designated under this section and any additional limitations which have been placed on the UCCF.</P>
        <P>(2) Based on information provided and comments received during the public notice and comment period, EPA shall prepare a response to the comments received. The response to comments shall be attached to the acknowledgment described in paragraph (e)(1). Both the acknowledgment and the response to comments shall be sent to all persons who commented on the designation of the UCCF(s) that are the subject of the acknowledgment.</P>
        <P>(3) Based on information provided and comments received during or after the public notice and comment period, designated UCCFs may be rejected for the proposed use, or, if EPA determines that acceptance for the proposed use under the conditions of paragraph (b) of this section may not fully protect human health and the environment based on the Utility's compliance history or other appropriate factors, the acknowledgment may impose conditions in addition to those in paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(4) If EPA determines that a site-specific informational public meeting is warranted prior to determining the acceptability of a designated UCCF, the acknowledgment will so state.</P>
        <P>(5) Subsequent to any public meeting, EPA may reject or prohibit UCCFs from participating in this project based on information provided or comments received during or after the public notice process or based on a determination that acceptance for the proposed use under the conditions of paragraph (b) of this section may not fully protect human health and the environment based on the Utility's compliance history or other appropriate factors.</P>
        <P>(f) At any time, a Utility may add or remove UCCF designations by complying with the following requirements:</P>

        <P>(1) A Utility may notify EPA of its intent to designate additional UCCFs. Such a notification shall be submitted to, and processed by, EPA, in the manner indicated in paragraphs (d) and (e) of this section.<PRTPAGE P="387"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) To have one or more additional UCCFs designated, the Utility must comply with paragraph (c) of this section.</P>
        <P>(3) A Utility can discontinue use of a facility as a UCCF by notifying EPA in writing.</P>
        <P>(g) Each Utility that receives approval to consolidate hazardous waste pursuant to this section shall submit an Annual Progress Report with the following information for the preceding year:</P>
        <P>(1) The number of remote locations statewide for which hazardous waste was handled in accordance with paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(2) The total tonnage of each type of hazardous waste handled by each UCCF.</P>
        <P>(3) The number of remote locations statewide from which 1,000 kilograms or more of hazardous waste were collected per calendar month.</P>
        <P>(4) The number of remote locations statewide from which between 100 and 1,000 kilograms of hazardous waste were collected per calendar month.</P>
        <P>(5) An estimate of the monetary value, on a Utility-wide basis, of the direct savings realized by participation in this project. Direct savings at a minimum include those outlined in paragraph (h) of this section.</P>
        <P>(6) Descriptions of the environmental compliance, remediation, or pollution prevention projects or activities into which the savings, described in paragraph (h) of this section, have been reinvested, with an estimate of the savings reinvested in each. Any such projects must consist of activities that are over and above existing legal requirements and that have not been initiated prior to the Utility's receipt of approval to consolidate hazardous waste pursuant to this section.</P>
        <P>(7) The addresses and EPA identification numbers for all facilities that served as UCCFs for hazardous waste from remote locations.</P>
        <P>(h) Utilities that receive approval to consolidate hazardous waste pursuant to this section must assess the direct savings realized as a result. Cost estimates shall include direct savings based on relief from any regulatory requirements, which the facility expects to be relieved from due to compliance with the provisions of this section including, but not limited to, the following:</P>
        <P>(1) Database management for each remote location as an individual generator;</P>
        <P>(2) Biennial Report preparation costs; and/or</P>
        <P>(3) Cost savings realized from consolidation of waste for economical shipment (including no longer shipping waste directly to a TSD from remote locations).</P>
        <P>(i) If any UCCF or Utility that receives approval under this section fails to comply with any of the requirements of this section, EPA may terminate or suspend the UCCF's or Utility's participation. EPA will provide a UCCF or Utility with 15 days written notice of its intent to terminate or suspend participation. During this period, the UCCF will have the opportunity to come back into compliance or provide a written explanation as to why it was not in compliance with the terms of this section and how it will come back into compliance. If EPA then issues a written notice terminating or suspending participation, the Utility must take immediate action to come into compliance with all otherwise applicable federal requirements. EPA may also take enforcement action against a Utility for non-compliance with the provisions of this section.</P>
        <P>(j) This section will expire on May 24, 2011.</P>
        <CITA>[64 FR 37636, July 12, 1999, as amended at 70 FR 29913, May 24, 2005; 71 FR 40272, July 14, 2006]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart J—University Laboratories XL Project—Laboratory Environmental Management Standard</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>64 FR 53292, Sept. 28, 1999, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.100</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what organizations does this subpart apply?</SUBJECT>
        <P>This subpart applies to an organization that meets all three of the following conditions:</P>

        <P>(a) It is one of the three following academic institutions: The University of Massachusetts Boston in Boston, <PRTPAGE P="388"/>Massachusetts, Boston College in Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts, or the University of Vermont in Burlington, Vermont (“Universities”); and</P>
        <P>(b) It is a laboratory at one of the Universities (identified pursuant to § 262.105(c)(2)(ii)) where laboratory scale activities, as defined in § 262.102, result in laboratory waste; and</P>
        <P>(c) It complies with all the requirements of this subpart.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.101</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What is in this subpart?</SUBJECT>
        <P>This subpart provides a framework for a new management system for wastes that are generated in University laboratories. This framework is called the Laboratory Environmental Management Standard. The standard includes some specific definitions that apply to the University laboratories. It contains specific requirements for how to handle laboratory waste that are called Minimum Performance Criteria. The standard identifies the requirements for developing and implementing an environmental management plan. It outlines the responsibilities of the management staff of each participating university. Finally, the standard identifies requirements for training people who will work in the laboratories or manage laboratory waste. This Subpart contains requirements for RCRA solid and hazardous waste determination, and circumstances for termination and expiration of this pilot.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.102</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What special definitions are included in this subpart?</SUBJECT>
        <P>For purposes of this subpart, the following definitions apply:</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Acutely Hazardous Laboratory Waste</E> means a laboratory waste, defined in the Environmental Management Plan as posing significant potential hazards to human health or the environment and which must include RCRA “P” wastes, and may include particularly hazardous substances as designated in a University's Chemical Hygiene Plan under OSHA, or Extremely Hazardous Substances under the Emergency Planning and Community Right to Know Act.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Emergency</E> means any occurrence such as, but not limited to, equipment failure, rupture of containers or failure of control equipment which results in the potential uncontrolled release of a hazardous chemical into the environment and which requires agency or fire department notification and/or reporting.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Environmental Management Plan</E> (EMP) means a written program developed and implemented by the university which sets forth standards and procedures, responsibilities, pollution control equipment, performance criteria, resources and work practices that both protect human health and the environment from the hazards presented by laboratory wastes within a laboratory and between a laboratory and the hazardous waste accumulation area, and satisfies the plan requirements defined elsewhere in this Subpart. Certain requirements of this plan are satisfied through the use of the Chemical Hygiene Plan (see, 29 CFR 1910.1450), or equivalent, and other relevant plans, including a waste minimization plan. The elements of the Environmental Management Plan must be easily accessible, but may be integrated into existing plans, incorporated as an attachment, or developed as a separate document.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Environmental Objective</E> means an overall environmental goal of the organization which is verifiable.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Environmental Performance</E> means results of the data collected pursuant to implementation of the Environmental Management Plan as measured against policy, objectives and targets.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Environmental Target</E> means an environmental performance requirement of the organization which is quantifiable, where practicable, verifiable and designed to be achieved within a specified time frame.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Hazardous Chemical</E> means any chemical which is a physical hazard or a health hazard. A physical hazard means a chemical for which there is scientifically valid evidence that it is a combustible liquid, a compressed gas, explosive, flammable, an organic peroxide, an oxidizer, pyrophoric, unstable (reactive) or water-reactive. A health hazard means a chemical for which there is statistically significant evidence based on at least one study conducted in accordance with established scientific principles that acute or <PRTPAGE P="389"/>chronic health effects may occur in exposed employees. The term “health hazard” includes chemicals which are carcinogens, toxic or highly toxic agents, reproductive toxins, irritants, corrosives, sensitizers, hepatotoxins, nephrotoxins, neurotoxins, agents which act on the hematopoietic system and agents which damage the lungs, skin, eyes or mucous membranes.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Hazardous Chemical of Concern</E> means a chemical that the organization has identified as having the potential to be of significant risk to human health or the environment if not managed in accordance with procedures or practices defined by the organization.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Hazardous Waste Accumulation Area</E> means the on-site area at a University where the University will make a solid and hazardous waste determination with respect to laboratory wastes.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">In-Line Waste Collection</E> means a system for the automatic collection of laboratory waste which is directly connected to or part of a laboratory scale activity and which is constructed or operated in a manner which prevents the release of any laboratory waste therein into the environment during collection.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory</E> means, for the purpose of this Subpart, an area within a facility where the laboratory use of hazardous chemicals occurs. It is a workplace where relatively small quantities of hazardous chemicals are used on a non-production basis. The physical extent of individual laboratories within an organization will be defined by the Environmental Management Plan. A laboratory may include more than a single room if the rooms are in the same building and under the common supervision of a laboratory supervisor.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory Clean-Out</E> means an evaluation of the chemical inventory of a laboratory as a result of laboratory renovation, relocation or a change in laboratory supervision that may result in the transfer of laboratory wastes to the hazardous waste accumulation area.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory Environmental Management Standard</E> means the provisions of this Subpart and includes the requirements for preparation of Environmental Management Plans and the inclusion of Minimum Performance Criteria within each Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory Scale</E> means work with substances in which containers used for reactions, transfers and other handling of substances are designed to be safely and easily manipulated by one person. “Laboratory Scale” excludes those workplaces whose function is to produce commercial quantities of chemicals.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory Waste</E> means a hazardous chemical that results from laboratory scale activities and includes the following: excess or unused hazardous chemicals that may or may not be reused outside their laboratory of origin; hazardous chemicals determined to be RCRA hazardous waste as defined in 40 CFR Part 261; and hazardous chemicals that will be determined not to be RCRA hazardous waste pursuant to § 262.106.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory Worker</E> means a person who is assigned to handle hazardous chemicals in the laboratory and may include researchers, students or technicians.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Legal and Other Requirements</E> means requirements imposed by, or as a result of, governmental permits, governmental laws and regulations, judicial and administrative enforcement orders, non-governmental legally enforceable contracts, research grants and agreements, certification specifications, formal voluntary commitments and organizational policies and standards.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Senior Management</E> means senior personnel with overall responsibility, authority and accountability for managing laboratory activities within the organization.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Universities</E> means the following academic institutions; University of Vermont, Boston College, and the University of Massachusetts Boston, which are participants in this Laboratory XL project and which are subject to the requirements set forth in this Subpart J.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What is the scope of the laboratory environmental management standard?</SUBJECT>

        <P>The Laboratory Environmental Management Standard will not affect or supersede any legal requirements other than those described in § 262.10(j). The <PRTPAGE P="390"/>requirements that continue to apply include, but are not limited to, OSHA, Fire Codes, wastewater permit limitations, emergency response notification provisions, or other legal requirements applicable to University laboratories.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.104</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What are the minimum performance criteria?</SUBJECT>
        <P>The Minimum Performance Criteria that each University must meet in managing its Laboratory Waste are:</P>
        <P>(a) Each University must label all laboratory waste with the general hazard class and either the words “laboratory waste” or with the chemical name of the contents. If the container is too small to hold a label, the label must be placed on a secondary container.</P>
        <P>(b) Each University may temporarily hold up to 55 gallons of laboratory waste or one quart of acutely hazardous laboratory waste, or weight equivalent, in each laboratory, but upon reaching these thresholds, each University must mark that laboratory waste with the date when this threshold requirement was met (by dating the container(s) or secondary container(s)).</P>
        <P>(c) Each university must remove all of the dated laboratory waste from the laboratory for delivery to a location identified in paragraph (i) of this section within 30 days of reaching the threshold amount identified in paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(d) In no event shall the excess laboratory waste that a laboratory temporarily holds before dated laboratory waste is removed exceed an additional 55 gallons of laboratory waste (or one additional quart of acutely hazardous laboratory waste). No more than 110 gallons of laboratory waste total (or no more than two quarts of acutely hazardous laboratory waste total) may be temporarily held in a laboratory at any one time. Excess laboratory waste must be dated and removed in accordance with the requirements of paragraphs (b) and (c) of this section.</P>
        <P>(e) Containers of laboratory wastes must be:</P>
        <P>(1) Closed at all times except when wastes are being added to (including during in-line waste collection) or removed from the container;</P>
        <P>(2) Maintained in good condition and stored in the laboratory in a manner to avoid leaks;</P>
        <P>(3) Compatible with their contents to avoid reactions between the waste and its container; and must be made of, or lined with, materials which are compatible with the laboratory wastes to be temporarily held in the laboratory so that the container is not impaired; and</P>
        <P>(4) Inspected regularly (at least annually) to ensure that they meet requirements for container management.</P>
        <P>(f) The management of laboratory waste must not result in the release of hazardous constituents into the land, air and water where such release is prohibited under federal law.</P>
        <P>(g) The requirements for emergency response are:</P>
        <P>(1) Each University must post notification procedures, location of emergency response equipment to be used by laboratory workers and evacuation procedures;</P>
        <P>(2) Emergency response equipment and procedures for emergency response must be appropriate to the hazards in the laboratory such that hazards to human health and the environment will be minimized in the event of an emergency;</P>
        <P>(3) In the event of a fire, explosion or other release of laboratory waste which could threaten human health or the environment, the laboratory worker must follow the notification procedures under paragraph (g)(1) of this section.</P>
        <P>(h) Each University must investigate, document, and take actions to correct and prevent future incidents of hazardous chemical spills, exposures and other incidents that trigger a reportable emergency or that require reporting under paragraph (g) of this section.</P>
        <P>(i) Each University may only transfer laboratory wastes from a laboratory:</P>

        <P>(1) Directly to an on-site designated hazardous waste accumulation area. Notwithstanding 40 CFR 263.10(a), each University must comply with requirements for transporters set forth in 40 CFR 263.30 and 263.31 in the event of a discharge of laboratory waste en route from a laboratory to an on-site hazardous waste accumulation area; or<PRTPAGE P="391"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) To a treatment, storage or disposal (TSD) facility permitted to handle the waste under 40 CFR part 270 or in interim status under 40 CFR parts 265 and 270 (or authorized to handle the waste by a state with a hazardous waste management program approved under 40 CFR part 271) if it is determined in the laboratory by the individuals identified in § 262.105(b)(3) to be responsible for waste management decisions that the waste is a hazardous waste and that it is prudent to transfer it directly to a treatment, storage, and disposal facility rather than an on-site accumulation area.</P>
        <P>(j) Each University must ensure that laboratory workers receive training and are provided with information so that they can implement and comply with these Minimum Performance Criteria.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.105</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>What must be included in the laboratory environmental management plan?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Each University must include specific measures it will take to protect human health and the environment from hazards associated with the management of laboratory wastes and from the reuse, recycling or disposal of such materials outside the laboratory.</P>
        <P>(b) Each University must write, implement and comply with an Environmental Management Plan that includes the following:</P>
        <P>(1) The specific procedures to assure compliance with each of the Minimum Performance Criteria set forth in § 262.104.</P>
        <P>(2) An environmental policy, or environmental, health and safety policy, signed by the University's senior management, which must include commitments to regulatory compliance, waste minimization, risk reduction and continual improvement of the environmental management system.</P>
        <P>(3) A description of roles and responsibilities for the implementation and maintenance of the Laboratory Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(4) A system for identifying and tracking legal and other requirements applicable to laboratory waste, including the procedures for providing updates to laboratory supervisors.</P>
        <P>(5) Criteria for the identification of physical and chemical hazards and the control measures to reduce the potential for releases of laboratory wastes to the environment, including engineering controls, the use of personal protective equipment and hygiene practices, containment strategies and other control measures.</P>
        <P>(6) A pollution prevention plan, including, but not limited to, roles and responsibilities, training, pollution prevention activities, and performance review.</P>
        <P>(7) A system for conducting and updating annual surveys of hazardous chemicals of concern and procedures for identifying acutely hazardous laboratory waste.</P>
        <P>(8) The procedures for conducting laboratory clean-outs with regard to the safe management and disposal of laboratory wastes.</P>
        <P>(9) The criteria that laboratory workers must comply with for managing, containing and labeling laboratory wastes, including: an evaluation of the need for and the use of any special containers or labeling circumstances, and the use of laboratory wastes secondary containers including packaging, bottles, or test tube racks.</P>
        <P>(10) The procedures relevant to the safe and timely removal of laboratory wastes from the laboratory.</P>
        <P>(11) The emergency preparedness and response procedures to be implemented for laboratory waste.</P>
        <P>(12) Provisions for information dissemination and training, provided for in paragraph (d) of this section.</P>
        <P>(13) The procedures for the development and approval of changes to the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(14) The procedures and work practices for safely transferring or moving laboratory wastes from a laboratory to a location identified in § 262.104(i).</P>
        <P>(15) The procedures for regularly inspecting a laboratory to assess conformance with the requirements of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>

        <P>(16) The procedures for the identification of environmental management plan noncompliance, and the assignment of responsibility, timelines and corrective actions to prevent their reoccurrence.<PRTPAGE P="392"/>
        </P>
        <P>(17) The record keeping requirements to document conformance with this Plan.</P>
        <P>(c) Organizational responsibilities for each university. Each University must:</P>
        <P>(1) Develop and oversee implementation of its Laboratory Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(2) Identify the following:</P>
        <P>(i) Annual environmental objectives and targets;</P>
        <P>(ii) Those laboratories covered by the requirements of the Laboratory Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(3) Assign roles and responsibilities for the effective implementation of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(4) Determine whether laboratory wastes are solid wastes under RCRA and, if so, whether they are hazardous.</P>
        <P>(5) Develop, implement, and maintain:</P>
        <P>(i) Policies, procedures and practices governing its compliance with the Environmental Management Plan and applicable federal and state hazardous waste regulations.</P>
        <P>(ii) Procedures to monitor and measure relevant conformance and environmental performance data for the purpose of supporting continual improvement of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(iii) Policies and procedures for managing environmental documents and records applicable to this Environmental Management Standard.</P>
        <P>(6) Ensure that:</P>
        <P>(i) Its Environmental Management Plan is available to laboratory workers, vendors, employee representatives, visitors, on-site contractors, and upon request, to governmental representatives.</P>
        <P>(ii) Personnel designated by each University to handle laboratory wastes and RCRA hazardous waste receive appropriate training.</P>
        <P>(iii) The Environmental Management Plan is reviewed at least annually by senior management to ensure its continuing suitability, adequacy and effectiveness. The reviews may include, but not be limited to, a consideration of monitoring and measuring information, Laboratory Environmental Management Standard performance data, assessment and audit results and other relevant information and data.</P>
        <P>(d) What are the Information and Training Requirements for Each University?</P>
        <P>(1) Each University must ensure that laboratory workers receive training and are provided with the information to understand and implement the elements of each University's Environmental Management Plan that are relevant to the laboratory workers' responsibilities.</P>
        <P>(2) When must each University ensure that laboratory workers receive training and information?</P>
        <P>(i) Each University must provide the information to each laboratory worker when he/she is first assigned to a work area where laboratory wastes may be generated.</P>
        <P>(ii) Each University must ensure that each laboratory worker has had training within six months of when he/she is first assigned to a work area where laboratory wastes may be generated. Each University must retrain a laboratory worker when a laboratory waste poses a new or unique hazard for which the laboratory worker has not received prior training and as frequently as needed to maintain knowledge of the procedures of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(3) Each University must provide an outline of training and specify who is to receive training in its Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(4) Each University must ensure that laboratory workers are informed of:</P>
        <P>(i) The contents of this Subpart and the Laboratory Environmental Management Plan(s) for the laboratory(ies) in which they will be performing work;</P>
        <P>(ii) The location and availability of the Environmental Management Plan;</P>
        <P>(iii) Emergency response measures applicable to laboratories;</P>
        <P>(iv) Signs and indicators of a hazardous substance release;</P>
        <P>(v) The location and availability of known reference materials relevant to implementation of the Environmental Management Plan; and</P>
        <P>(vi) Environmental training requirements applicable to laboratory workers.</P>

        <P>(5) Each University must ensure that Laboratory workers have received training in:<PRTPAGE P="393"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Methods and observations that may be used to detect the presence or release of a hazardous substance;</P>
        <P>(ii) The chemical and physical hazards associated with laboratory wastes in their work area;</P>
        <P>(iii) The relevant measures a laboratory worker can take to protect human health and the environment; and</P>
        <P>(iv) Details of the Environmental Management Plan sufficient to ensure they manage laboratory waste in accordance with the requirements of this Subpart.</P>
        <P>(6) Requirements pertaining to Laboratory visitors:</P>
        <P>(i) Laboratory visitors, such as on-site contractors or environmental vendors, that require information and training under this standard must be identified in the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(ii) Laboratory visitors identified in the Environmental Management Plan must be informed of the existence and location of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(iii) Laboratory visitors identified in the Environmental Management Plan must be informed of relevant policies, procedures or work practices to ensure compliance with the requirements of the Environmental Management Plan.</P>
        <P>(7) Each University must define methods of providing objective evidence and records of training and information dissemination in its Environmental Management Plan.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.106</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>When must a hazardous waste determination be made?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) For laboratory waste sent from a laboratory to an on-site hazardous waste accumulation area, each University must evaluate the laboratory wastes to determine whether they are solid wastes under RCRA and, if so, determine pursuant to § 262.11 (a) through (d) whether they are hazardous wastes, as soon as the laboratory wastes reach the University's Hazardous Waste Accumulation area(s). At this point each University must determine whether the laboratory waste will be reused or whether it must be managed as RCRA solid or hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>(b) For laboratory waste that will be sent from a laboratory to a TSD facility permitted to handle the waste, each University must evaluate such laboratory wastes to determine whether they are solid wastes under RCRA and, if so, determine pursuant to § 262.11 (a) through (d) whether they are hazardous wastes, prior to the 30-day deadline for removing dated laboratory waste from the laboratory.</P>
        <P>(c) Laboratory waste that is determined to be hazardous waste is no longer subject to the provisions of this subpart and must be managed in accordance with all applicable provisions of 40 CFR Parts 260 through 270.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.107</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Under what circumstances will a university's participation in this environmental management standard pilot be terminated?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) EPA retains the right to terminate a University's participation in this Laboratory XL project if the University:</P>
        <P>(1) Is in non-compliance with the Minimum Performance Criteria in § 262.104; or</P>
        <P>(2) Has actual environmental management practices in the laboratory that do not conform to its Environmental Management Plan; or</P>
        <P>(3) Is in non-compliance with the Hazardous Waste Determination requirements of § 262.106.</P>

        <P>(b) In the event of termination, EPA will provide the University with 15 days written notice of its intent to terminate. During this period, which commences upon receipt of the notice, the University will have the opportunity to come back into compliance with the Minimum Performance Criteria, its Environmental Management Plan, or the requirements for making a hazardous waste determination at § 262.106 or to provide a written explanation as to why it was not in compliance and how it intends to return to compliance. If, upon review of the University's written explanation, EPA then re-issues a written notice terminating the University from this XL Project, the provisions of paragraph (c) of this section will immediately apply and the University shall have 90 days to come into compliance with the applicable RCRA requirements deferred by § 262.10(j). During the 90-day transition period, the provisions of this subpart <PRTPAGE P="394"/>shall continue to apply to the University.</P>
        <P>(c) If a University withdraws from this XL project, or receives a notice of termination pursuant to this section, it must submit to EPA and the state a schedule for returning to full compliance with RCRA requirements at the laboratory level. The schedule must show how the University will return to full compliance with RCRA within 90 days from the date of the notice of termination or withdrawal.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>When will this subpart expire?</SUBJECT>
        <P>This subpart will expire on April 15, 2009.</P>
        <CITA>[71 FR 35550, June 21, 2006]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart K—Alternative Requirements for Hazardous Waste Determination and Accumulation of Unwanted Material for Laboratories Owned by Eligible Academic Entities</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.200</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions for this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The following definitions apply to this subpart:</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Central accumulation area</E> means an on-site hazardous waste accumulation area subject to either § 262.34(a)-(b) of this part (large quantity generators) or § 262.34(d)-(f) of this part (small quantity generators). A central accumulation area at an eligible academic entity that chooses to be subject to this subpart must also comply with § 262.211 when accumulating unwanted material and/or hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">College/University</E> means a private or public, post-secondary, degree-granting, academic institution, that is accredited by an accrediting agency listed annually by the U.S. Department of Education.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Eligible academic entity</E> means a college or university, or a non-profit research institute that is owned by or has a formal written affiliation agreement with a college or university, or a teaching hospital that is owned by or has a formal written affiliation agreement with a college or university.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Formal written affiliation agreement</E> for a non-profit research institute means a written document that establishes a relationship between institutions for the purposes of research and/or education and is signed by authorized representatives, as defined by § 260.10, from each institution. A relationship on a project-by-project or grant-by-grant basis is not considered a formal written affiliation agreement. A <E T="03">formal written affiliation agreement</E> for a teaching hospital means a master affiliation agreement and program letter of agreement, as defined by the Accreditation Council for Graduate Medical Education, with an accredited medical program or medical school.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory</E> means an area owned by an eligible academic entity where relatively small quantities of chemicals and other substances are used on a non-production basis for teaching or research (or diagnostic purposes at a teaching hospital) and are stored and used in containers that are easily manipulated by one person. Photo laboratories, art studios, and field laboratories are considered laboratories. Areas such as chemical stockrooms and preparatory laboratories that provide a support function to teaching or research laboratories (or diagnostic laboratories at teaching hospitals) are also considered laboratories.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory clean-out</E> means an evaluation of the inventory of chemicals and other materials in a laboratory that are no longer needed or that have expired and the subsequent removal of those chemicals or other unwanted materials from the laboratory. A clean-out may occur for several reasons. It may be on a routine basis (e.g., at the end of a semester or academic year) or as a result of a renovation, relocation, or change in laboratory supervisor/occupant. A regularly scheduled removal of unwanted material as required by § 262.208 does not qualify as a laboratory clean-out.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Laboratory worker</E> means a person who handles chemicals and/or unwanted material in a laboratory and may include, but is not limited to, faculty, staff, post-doctoral fellows, interns, researchers, technicians, supervisors/managers, and principal investigators. A person does not need to be <PRTPAGE P="395"/>paid or otherwise compensated for his/her work in the laboratory to be considered a laboratory worker. Undergraduate and graduate students in a supervised classroom setting are not laboratory workers.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Non-profit research institute</E> means an organization that conducts research as its primary function and files as a non-profit organization under the tax code of 26 U.S.C. 501(c)(3).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material</E> means an unwanted material that is one of the acutely hazardous commercial chemical products listed in § 261.33(e) for reactivity.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Teaching hospital</E> means a hospital that trains students to become physicians, nurses or other health or laboratory personnel.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Trained professional</E> means a person who has completed the applicable RCRA training requirements of § 265.16 for large quantity generators, or is knowledgeable about normal operations and emergencies in accordance with § 262.34(d)(5)(iii) for small quantity generators and conditionally exempt small quantity generators. A trained professional may be an employee of the eligible academic entity or may be a contractor or vendor who meets the requisite training requirements.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Unwanted material</E> means any chemical, mixtures of chemicals, products of experiments or other material from a laboratory that is no longer needed, wanted or usable in the laboratory and that is destined for hazardous waste determination by a trained professional. Unwanted materials include reactive acutely hazardous unwanted materials and materials that may eventually be determined not to be solid waste pursuant to § 261.2, or a hazardous waste pursuant to § 261.3. If an eligible academic entity elects to use another equally effective term in lieu of “unwanted material,” as allowed by § 262.206(a)(1)(i), the equally effective term has the same meaning and is subject to the same requirements as “unwanted material” under this subpart.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Working container</E> means a small container (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, two gallons or less) that is in use at a laboratory bench, hood, or other work station, to collect unwanted material from a laboratory experiment or procedure.</P>
        <CITA>[73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008, as amended at 75 FR 79308, Dec. 20, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.201</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Large quantity generators and small quantity generators. This subpart provides alternative requirements to the requirements in §§ 262.11 and 262.34(c) for the hazardous waste determination and accumulation of hazardous waste in laboratories owned by eligible academic entities that choose to be subject to this subpart, provided that they complete the notification requirements of § 262.203.</P>
        <P>(b) Conditionally exempt small quantity generators. This subpart provides alternative requirements to the conditional exemption in § 261.5(b) for the accumulation of hazardous waste in laboratories owned by eligible academic entities that choose to be subject to this subpart, provided that they complete the notification requirements of § 262.203.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.202</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>This subpart is optional.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Large quantity generators and small quantity generators: Eligible academic entities have the option of complying with this subpart with respect to its laboratories, as an alternative to complying with the requirements of §§ 262.11 and 262.34(c).</P>
        <P>(b) Conditionally exempt small quantity generators. Eligible academic entities have the option of complying with this subpart with respect to its laboratories, as an alternative to complying with the conditional exemption of § 261.5(b).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.203</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>How an eligible academic entity indicates it will be subject to the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) An eligible academic entity must notify the appropriate EPA Regional Administrator in writing, using the RCRA Subtitle C Site Identification Form (EPA Form 8700-12), that it is electing to be subject to the requirements of this subpart for all the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity under the same EPA Identification Number. An eligible academic entity that is a conditionally exempt small quantity generator and <PRTPAGE P="396"/>does not have an EPA Identification Number must notify that it is electing to be subject to the requirements of this subpart for all the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity that are on-site, as defined by § 260.10. An eligible academic entity must submit a separate notification (Site Identification Form) for each EPA Identification Number (or site, for conditionally exempt small quantity generators) that is electing to be subject to the requirements of this subpart, and must submit the Site Identification Form before it begins operating under this subpart.</P>
        <P>(b) When submitting the Site Identification Form, the eligible academic entity must, at a minimum, fill out the following fields on the form:</P>
        <P>(1) Reason for Submittal.</P>
        <P>(2) Site EPA Identification Number (except for conditionally exempt small quantity generators).</P>
        <P>(3) Site Name.</P>
        <P>(4) Site Location Information.</P>
        <P>(5) Site Land Type.</P>
        <P>(6) North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) Code(s) for the Site.</P>
        <P>(7) Site Mailing Address.</P>
        <P>(8) Site Contact Person.</P>
        <P>(9) Operator and Legal Owner of the Site.</P>
        <P>(10) Type of Regulated Waste Activity.</P>
        <P>(11) Certification.</P>
        <P>(c) An eligible academic entity must keep a copy of the notification on file at the eligible academic entity for as long as its laboratories are subject to this subpart.</P>
        <P>(d) A teaching hospital that is not owned by a college or university must keep a copy of its formal written affiliation agreement with a college or university on file at the teaching hospital for as long as its laboratories are subject to this subpart.</P>
        <P>(e) A non-profit research institute that is not owned by a college or university must keep a copy of its formal written affiliation agreement with a college or university on file at the non-profit research institute for as long as its laboratories are subject to this subpart.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.204</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>How an eligible academic entity indicates it will withdraw from the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) An eligible academic entity must notify the appropriate EPA Regional Administrator in writing, using the RCRA Subtitle C Site Identification Form (EPA Form 8700-12), that it is electing to no longer be subject to the requirements of this subpart for all the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity under the same EPA Identification Number and that it will comply with the requirements of §§ 262.11 and 262.34(c) for small quantity generators and large quantity generators. An eligible academic entity that is a conditionally exempt small quantity generator and does not have an EPA Identification Number must notify that it is withdrawing from the requirements of this subpart for all the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity that are on-site and that it will comply with the conditional exemption in § 261.5(b). An eligible academic entity must submit a separate notification (Site Identification Form) for each EPA Identification Number (or site, for conditionally exempt small quantity generators) that is withdrawing from the requirements of this subpart and must submit the Site Identification Form before it begins operating under the requirements of §§ 262.11 and 262.34(c) for small quantity generators and large quantity generators, or § 261.5(b) for conditionally exempt small quantity generators.</P>
        <P>(b) When submitting the Site Identification Form, the eligible academic entity must, at a minimum, fill out the following fields on the form:</P>
        <P>(1) Reason for Submittal.</P>
        <P>(2) Site EPA Identification Number (except for conditionally exempt small quantity generators).</P>
        <P>(3) Site Name.</P>
        <P>(4) Site Location Information.</P>
        <P>(5) Site Land Type.</P>
        <P>(6) North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) Code(s) for the Site.</P>
        <P>(7) Site Mailing Address.</P>
        <P>(8) Site Contact Person.</P>
        <P>(9) Operator and Legal Owner of the Site.</P>
        <P>(10) Type of Regulated Waste Activity.<PRTPAGE P="397"/>
        </P>
        <P>(11) Certification.</P>
        <P>(c) An eligible academic entity must keep a copy of the withdrawal notice on file at the eligible academic entity for three years from the date of the notification.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.205</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Summary of the requirements of this subpart.</SUBJECT>
        <P>An eligible academic entity that chooses to be subject to this subpart is not required to have interim status or a RCRA Part B permit for the accumulation of unwanted material and hazardous waste in its laboratories, provided the laboratories comply with the provisions of this subpart and the eligible academic entity has a Laboratory Management Plan (LMP) in accordance with § 262.214 that describes how the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity will comply with the requirements of this subpart.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.206</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Labeling and management standards for containers of unwanted material in the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <P>An eligible academic entity must manage containers of unwanted material while in the laboratory in accordance with the requirements in this section.</P>
        <P>(a) Labeling: Label unwanted material as follows:</P>
        <P>(1) The following information must be affixed or attached to the container:</P>
        <P>(i) The words “unwanted material” or another equally effective term that is to be used consistently by the eligible academic entity and that is identified in Part I of the Laboratory Management Plan, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Sufficient information to alert emergency responders to the contents of the container. Examples of information that would be sufficient to alert emergency responders to the contents of the container include, but are not limited to:</P>
        <P>(A) The name of the chemical(s),</P>
        <P>(B) The type or class of chemical, such as organic solvents or halogenated organic solvents.</P>
        <P>(2) The following information may be affixed or attached to the container, but must at a minimum be associated with the container:</P>
        <P>(i) The date that the unwanted material first began accumulating in the container, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Information sufficient to allow a trained professional to properly identify whether an unwanted material is a solid and hazardous waste and to assign the proper hazardous waste code(s), pursuant to § 262.11. Examples of information that would allow a trained professional to properly identify whether an unwanted material is a solid or hazardous waste include, but are not limited to:</P>
        <P>(A) The name and/or description of the chemical contents or composition of the unwanted material, or, if known, the product of the chemical reaction,</P>
        <P>(B) Whether the unwanted material has been used or is unused,</P>
        <P>(C) A description of the manner in which the chemical was produced or processed, if applicable.</P>
        <P>(b) Management of Containers in the Laboratory: An eligible academic entity must properly manage containers of unwanted material in the laboratory to assure safe storage of the unwanted material, to prevent leaks, spills, emissions to the air, adverse chemical reactions, and dangerous situations that may result in harm to human health or the environment. Proper container management must include the following:</P>
        <P>(1) Containers are maintained and kept in good condition and damaged containers are replaced, overpacked, or repaired, and</P>
        <P>(2) Containers are compatible with their contents to avoid reactions between the contents and the container; and are made of, or lined with, material that is compatible with the unwanted material so that the container's integrity is not impaired, and</P>
        <P>(3) Containers must be kept closed at all times, except:</P>
        <P>(i) When adding, removing or bulking unwanted material, or</P>
        <P>(ii) A working container may be open until the end of the procedure or work shift, or until it is full, whichever comes first, at which time the working container must either be closed or the contents emptied into a separate container that is then closed, or</P>
        <P>(iii) When venting of a container is necessary.<PRTPAGE P="398"/>
        </P>
        <P>(A) For the proper operation of laboratory equipment, such as with in-line collection of unwanted materials from high performance liquid chromatographs, or</P>
        <P>(B) To prevent dangerous situations, such as build-up of extreme pressure.</P>
        <CITA>[73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008, as amended at 75 FR 79308, Dec. 20, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.207</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Training.</SUBJECT>
        <P>An eligible academic entity must provide training to all individuals working in a laboratory at the eligible academic entity, as follows:</P>
        <P>(a) Training for laboratory workers and students must be commensurate with their duties so they understand the requirements in this subpart and can implement them.</P>
        <P>(b) An eligible academic entity can provide training for laboratory workers and students in a variety of ways, including, but not limited to:</P>
        <P>(1) Instruction by the professor or laboratory manager before or during an experiment; or</P>
        <P>(2) Formal classroom training; or</P>
        <P>(3) Electronic/written training; or</P>
        <P>(4) On-the-job training; or</P>
        <P>(5) Written or oral exams.</P>
        <P>(c) An eligible academic entity that is a large quantity generator must maintain documentation for the durations specified in § 265.16(e) demonstrating training for all laboratory workers that is sufficient to determine whether laboratory workers have been trained. Examples of documentation demonstrating training can include, but are not limited to, the following:</P>
        <P>(1) Sign-in/attendance sheet(s) for training session(s); or</P>
        <P>(2) Syllabus for training session; or</P>
        <P>(3) Certificate of training completion; or</P>
        <P>(4) Test results.</P>
        <P>(d) A trained professional must:</P>
        <P>(1) Accompany the transfer of unwanted material and hazardous waste when the unwanted material and hazardous waste is removed from the laboratory, and</P>
        <P>(2) Make the hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.208</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Removing containers of unwanted material from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Removing containers of unwanted material on a regular schedule. An eligible academic entity must either:</P>
        <P>(1) Remove all containers of unwanted material from each laboratory on a regular interval, not to exceed 6 months; or</P>
        <P>(2) Remove containers of unwanted material from each laboratory within 6 months of each container's accumulation start date.</P>
        <P>(b) The eligible academic entity must specify in Part I of its Laboratory Management Plan whether it will comply with paragraph (a)(1) or (a)(2) of this section for the regular removal of unwanted material from its laboratories.</P>
        <P>(c) The eligible academic entity must specify in Part II of its Laboratory Management Plan how it will comply with paragraph (a)(1) or (a)(2) of this section and develop a schedule for regular removals of unwanted material from its laboratories.</P>
        <P>(d) Removing containers of unwanted material when volumes are exceeded.</P>
        <P>(1) If a laboratory accumulates a total volume of unwanted material (including reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material) in excess of 55 gallons before the regularly scheduled removal, the eligible academic entity must ensure that all containers of unwanted material in the laboratory (including reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material):</P>
        <P>(i) Are marked on the label that is associated with the container (or on the label that is affixed or attached to the container, if that is preferred) with the date that 55 gallons is exceeded; and</P>
        <P>(ii) Are removed from the laboratory within 10 calendar days of the date that 55 gallons was exceeded, or at the next regularly scheduled removal, whichever comes first.</P>

        <P>(2) If a laboratory accumulates more than 1 quart of reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material before the regularly scheduled removal, then the eligible academic entity must ensure that all containers of reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material:<PRTPAGE P="399"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Are marked on the label that is associated with the container (or on the label that is affixed or attached to the container, if that is preferred) with the date that 1 quart is exceeded; and</P>
        <P>(ii) Are removed from the laboratory within 10 calendar days of the date that 1 quart was exceeded, or at the next regularly scheduled removal, whichever comes first.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.209</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Where and when to make the hazardous waste determination and where to send containers of unwanted material upon removal from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Large quantity generators and small quantity generators—an eligible academic entity must ensure that a trained professional makes a hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material in any of the following areas:</P>
        <P>(1) In the laboratory before the unwanted material is removed from the laboratory, in accordance with § 262.210;</P>
        <P>(2) Within 4 calendar days of arriving at an on-site central accumulation area, in accordance with § 262.211; and</P>
        <P>(3) Within 4 calendar days of arriving at an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility, in accordance with § 262.212.</P>
        <P>(b) Conditionally exempt small quantity generators—an eligible academic entity must ensure that a trained professional makes a hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material in the laboratory before the unwanted material is removed from the laboratory, in accordance with § 262.210.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.210</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination in the laboratory before the unwanted material is removed from the laboratory.</SUBJECT>
        <P>If an eligible academic entity makes the hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material in the laboratory, it must comply with the following:</P>
        <P>(a) A trained professional must make the hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, before the unwanted material is removed from the laboratory.</P>
        <P>(b) If an unwanted material is a hazardous waste, the eligible academic entity must:</P>
        <P>(1) Write the words “hazardous waste” on the container label that is affixed or attached to the container, before the hazardous waste may be removed from the laboratory; and</P>
        <P>(2) Write the appropriate hazardous waste code(s) on the label that is associated with the container (or on the label that is affixed or attached to the container, if that is preferred) before the hazardous waste is transported off-site.</P>
        <P>(3) Count the hazardous waste toward the eligible academic entity's generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d), in the calendar month that the hazardous waste determination was made.</P>
        <P>(c) A trained professional must accompany all hazardous waste that is transferred from the laboratory(ies) to an on-site central accumulation area or on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</P>
        <P>(d) When hazardous waste is removed from the laboratory:</P>
        <P>(1) Large quantity generators and small quantity generators must ensure it is taken directly from the laboratory(ies) to an on-site central accumulation area, or on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility, or transported off-site.</P>
        <P>(2) Conditionally exempt small quantity generators must ensure it is taken directly from the laboratory(ies) to any of the types of facilities listed in § 261.5(f)(3) for acute hazardous waste, or § 261.5(g)(3) for hazardous waste.</P>
        <P>(e) An unwanted material that is a hazardous waste is subject to all applicable hazardous waste regulations when it is removed from the laboratory.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.211</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination at an on-site central accumulation area.</SUBJECT>
        <P>If an eligible academic entity makes the hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material at an on-site central accumulation area, it must comply with the following:</P>

        <P>(a) A trained professional must accompany all unwanted material that is transferred from the laboratory(ies) to an on-site central accumulation area.<PRTPAGE P="400"/>
        </P>
        <P>(b) All unwanted material removed from the laboratory(ies) must be taken directly from the laboratory(ies) to the on-site central accumulation area.</P>
        <P>(c) The unwanted material becomes subject to the generator accumulation regulations of § 262.34(a) (or § 262.34(j) and (k) for Performance Track members) for large quantity generators or § 262.34(d)-(f) for small quantity generators as soon as it arrives in the central accumulation area, except for the “hazardous waste” labeling requirements of § 262.34(a)(3) (or § 262.34(j)(6) for Performance Track members).</P>
        <P>(d) A trained professional must determine, pursuant to § 262.11, if the unwanted material is a hazardous waste within 4 calendar days of the unwanted materials' arrival at the on-site central accumulation area.</P>
        <P>(e) If the unwanted material is a hazardous waste, the eligible academic entity must:</P>
        <P>(1) Write the words “hazardous waste” on the container label that is affixed or attached to the container, within 4 calendar days of arriving at the on-site central accumulation area and before the hazardous waste may be removed from the on-site central accumulation area, and</P>
        <P>(2) Write the appropriate hazardous waste code(s) on the container label that is associated with the container (or on the label that is affixed or attached to the container, if that is preferred) before the hazardous waste may be treated or disposed of on-site or transported off-site, and</P>
        <P>(3) Count the hazardous waste toward the eligible academic entity's generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d) in the calendar month that the hazardous waste determination was made, and</P>
        <P>(4) Manage the hazardous waste according to all applicable hazardous waste regulations.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.212</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Making the hazardous waste determination at an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</SUBJECT>
        <P>If an eligible academic entity makes the hazardous waste determination, pursuant to § 262.11, for unwanted material at an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility, it must comply with the following:</P>
        <P>(a) A trained professional must accompany all unwanted material that is transferred from the laboratory(ies) to an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</P>
        <P>(b) All unwanted material removed from the laboratory(ies) must be taken directly from the laboratory(ies) to the on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</P>
        <P>(c) The unwanted material becomes subject to the terms of the eligible academic entity's hazardous waste permit or interim status as soon as it arrives in the on-site treatment, storage or disposal facility.</P>
        <P>(d) A trained professional must determine, pursuant to § 262.11, if the unwanted material is a hazardous waste within 4 calendar days of the unwanted materials' arrival at an on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility.</P>
        <P>(e) If the unwanted material is a hazardous waste, the eligible academic entity must:</P>
        <P>(1) Write the words “hazardous waste” on the container label that is affixed or attached to the container within 4 calendar days of arriving at the on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility and before the hazardous waste may be removed from the on-site interim status or permitted treatment, storage or disposal facility, and</P>
        <P>(2) Write the appropriate hazardous waste code(s) on the container label that is associated with the container (or on the label that is affixed or attached to the container, if that is preferred) before the hazardous waste may be treated or disposed on-site or transported off-site, and</P>
        <P>(3) Count the hazardous waste toward the eligible academic entity's generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d) in the calendar month that the hazardous waste determination was made, and</P>
        <P>(4) Manage the hazardous waste according to all applicable hazardous waste regulations.</P>
        <CITA>[73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008, as amended at 75 FR 79308, Dec. 20, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="401"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.213</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Laboratory clean-outs.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) One time per 12 month period for each laboratory, an eligible academic entity may opt to conduct a laboratory clean-out that is subject to all the applicable requirements of this subpart, except that:</P>
        <P>(1) If the volume of unwanted material in the laboratory exceeds 55 gallons (or 1 quart of reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material), the eligible academic entity is not required to remove all unwanted materials from the laboratory within 10 calendar days of exceeding 55 gallons (or 1 quart of reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material), as required by § 262.208. Instead, the eligible academic entity must remove all unwanted materials from the laboratory within 30 calendar days from the start of the laboratory clean-out; and</P>
        <P>(2) For the purposes of on-site accumulation, an eligible academic entity is not required to count a hazardous waste that is an unused commercial chemical product (listed in 40 CFR part 261, subpart D or exhibiting one or more characteristics in 40 CFR part 261, subpart C) generated solely during the laboratory clean-out toward its hazardous waste generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d). An unwanted material that is generated prior to the beginning of the laboratory clean-out and is still in the laboratory at the time the laboratory clean-out commences must be counted toward hazardous waste generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d), if it is determined to be hazardous waste; and</P>
        <P>(3) For the purposes of off-site management, an eligible academic entity must count all its hazardous waste, regardless of whether the hazardous waste was counted toward generator status under paragraph (a)(2) of this section, and if it generates more than 1 kg/month of acute hazardous waste or more than 100 kg/month of hazardous waste (i.e., the conditionally exempt small quantity generator limits of § 261.5), the hazardous waste is subject to all applicable hazardous waste regulations when it is transported off-site; and</P>
        <P>(4) An eligible academic entity must document the activities of the laboratory clean-out. The documentation must, at a minimum, identify the laboratory being cleaned out, the date the laboratory clean-out begins and ends, and the volume of hazardous waste generated during the laboratory clean-out. The eligible academic entity must maintain the records for a period of three years from the date the clean-out ends; and</P>
        <P>(b) For all other laboratory clean-outs conducted during the same 12-month period, an eligible academic entity is subject to all the applicable requirements of this subpart, including, but not limited to:</P>
        <P>(1) The requirement to remove all unwanted materials from the laboratory within 10 calendar days of exceeding 55 gallons (or 1 quart of reactive acutely hazardous unwanted material), as required by § 262.208; and</P>
        <P>(2) The requirement to count all hazardous waste, including unused hazardous waste, generated during the laboratory clean-out toward its hazardous waste generator status, pursuant to § 261.5(c) and (d).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.214</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Laboratory management plan.</SUBJECT>

        <P>An eligible academic entity must develop and retain a written Laboratory Management Plan, or revise an existing written plan. The Laboratory Management Plan is a site-specific document that describes how the eligible academic entity will manage unwanted materials in compliance with this subpart. An eligible academic entity may write one Laboratory Management Plan for all the laboratories owned by the eligible academic entity that have opted into this subpart, even if the laboratories are located at sites with different EPA Identification Numbers. The Laboratory Management Plan must contain two parts with a total of nine elements identified in paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section. In Part I of its Laboratory Management Plan, an eligible academic entity must describe its procedures for each of the elements listed in paragraph (a) of this section. An eligible academic entity must implement and comply with the specific provisions that it develops to address the elements in Part I of the Laboratory Management Plan. In Part II of its Laboratory Management Plan, an <PRTPAGE P="402"/>eligible academic entity must describe its best management practices for each of the elements listed in paragraph (b) of this section. The specific actions taken by an eligible academic entity to implement each element in Part II of its Laboratory Management Plan may vary from the procedures described in the eligible academic entity's Laboratory Management Plan, without constituting a violation of this subpart. An eligible academic entity may include additional elements and best management practices in Part II of its Laboratory Management Plan if it chooses.</P>
        <P>(a) The eligible academic entity must implement and comply with the specific provisions of Part I of its Laboratory Management Plan. In Part I of its Laboratory Management Plan, an eligible academic entity must:</P>
        <P>(1) Describe procedures for container labeling in accordance with § 262.206(a), as follows:</P>
        <P>(i) Identifying whether the eligible academic entity will use the term “unwanted material” on the containers in the laboratory. If not, identify an equally effective term that will be used in lieu of “unwanted material” and consistently by the eligible academic entity. The equally effective term, if used, has the same meaning and is subject to the same requirements as “unwanted material.”</P>
        <P>(ii) Identifying the manner in which information that is “associated with the container” will be imparted.</P>
        <P>(2) Identify whether the eligible academic entity will comply with § 262.208(a)(1) or (a)(2) for regularly scheduled removals of unwanted material from the laboratory.</P>
        <P>(b) In Part II of its Laboratory Management Plan, an eligible academic entity must:</P>
        <P>(1) Describe its intended best practices for container labeling and management (see the required standards at § 262.206).</P>
        <P>(2) Describe its intended best practices for providing training for laboratory workers and students commensurate with their duties (see the required standards at § 262.207(a)).</P>
        <P>(3) Describe its intended best practices for providing training to ensure safe on-site transfers of unwanted material and hazardous waste by trained professionals (see the required standards at § 262.207(d)(1)).</P>
        <P>(4) Describe its intended best practices for removing unwanted material from the laboratory, including:</P>
        <P>(i) For regularly scheduled removals—Develop a regular schedule for identifying and removing unwanted materials from its laboratories (see the required standards at § 262.208(a)(1) and (a)(2)).</P>
        <P>(ii) For removals when maximum volumes are exceeded:</P>
        <P>(A) Describe its intended best practices for removing unwanted materials from the laboratory within 10 calendar days when unwanted materials have exceeded their maximum volumes (see the required standards at § 262.208(d)).</P>
        <P>(B) Describe its intended best practices for communicating that unwanted materials have exceeded their maximum volumes.</P>
        <P>(5) Describe its intended best practices for making hazardous waste determinations, including specifying the duties of the individuals involved in the process (see the required standards at § 262.11 and §§ 262.209 through 262.212).</P>
        <P>(6) Describe its intended best practices for laboratory clean-outs, if the eligible academic entity plans to use the incentives for laboratory clean-outs provided in § 262.213, including:</P>
        <P>(i) Procedures for conducting laboratory clean-outs (see the required standards at § 262.213(a)(1) through (3)); and</P>
        <P>(ii) Procedures for documenting laboratory clean-outs (see the required standards at § 262.213(a)(4)).</P>
        <P>(7) Describe its intended best practices for emergency prevention, including:</P>
        <P>(i) Procedures for emergency prevention, notification, and response, appropriate to the hazards in the laboratory; and</P>
        <P>(ii) A list of chemicals that the eligible academic entity has, or is likely to have, that become more dangerous when they exceed their expiration date and/or as they degrade; and</P>
        <P>(iii) Procedures to safely dispose of chemicals that become more dangerous when they exceed their expiration date and/or as they degrade; and</P>

        <P>(iv) Procedures for the timely characterization of unknown chemicals.<PRTPAGE P="403"/>
        </P>
        <P>(c) An eligible academic entity must make its Laboratory Management Plan available to laboratory workers, students, or any others at the eligible academic entity who request it.</P>
        <P>(d) An eligible academic entity must review and revise its Laboratory Management Plan, as needed.</P>
        <CITA>[73 FR 72954, Dec. 1, 2008, as amended at 75 FR 79308, Dec. 20, 2010]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.215</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Unwanted material that is not solid or hazardous waste.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) If an unwanted material does not meet the definition of solid waste in § 261.2, it is no longer subject to this subpart or to the RCRA hazardous waste regulations.</P>
        <P>(b) If an unwanted material does not meet the definition of hazardous waste in § 261.3, it is no longer subject to this subpart or to the RCRA hazardous waste regulations, but must be managed in compliance with any other applicable regulations and/or conditions.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 262.216</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Non-laboratory hazardous waste generated at an eligible academic entity.</SUBJECT>
        <P>An eligible academic entity that generates hazardous waste outside of a laboratory is not eligible to manage that hazardous waste under this subpart; and</P>
        <P>(a) Remains subject to the generator requirements of §§ 262.11 and 262.34(c) for large quantity generators and small quantity generators (if the hazardous waste is managed in a satellite accumulation area), and all other applicable generator requirements of 40 CFR part 262, with respect to that hazardous waste; or</P>
        <P>(b) Remains subject to the conditional exemption of § 261.5(b) for conditionally exempt small quantity generators, with respect to that hazardous waste.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <APPENDIX>
        <EAR>Pt. 262, App.</EAR>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Appendix to Part 262—Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest and Instructions (EPA Forms 8700-22 and 8700-22A and Their Instructions)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">U.S. EPA Form 8700-22</HD>
        <P>Read all instructions before completing this form.</P>
        <P>1. This form has been designed for use on a 12-pitch (elite) typewriter which is also compatible with standard computer printers; a firm point pen may also be used—press down hard.</P>
        <P>2. Federal regulations require generators and transporters of hazardous waste and owners or operators of hazardous waste treatment, storage, and disposal facilities to complete this form (FORM 8700-22) and, if necessary, the continuation sheet (FORM 8700-22A) for both inter- and intrastate transportation of hazardous waste.</P>
        <GPH DEEP="432" SPAN="2">
          <PRTPAGE P="404"/>
          <GID>ER16JN05.012</GID>
        </GPH>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Manifest 8700-22</HD>
        <P>The following statement must be included with each Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest, either on the form, in the instructions to the form, or accompanying the form:</P>

        <P>Public reporting burden for this collection of information is estimated to average: 30 minutes for generators, 10 minutes for transporters, and 25 minutes for owners or operators of treatment, storage, and disposal facilities. This includes time for reviewing instructions, gathering data, completing, reviewing and transmitting the form. Any correspondence regarding the PRA burden statement for the manifest must be sent to <PRTPAGE P="405"/>the Director of the Collection Strategies Division in EPA's Office of Information Collection at the following address: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (2822T), 1200 Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20460. Do not send the completed form to this address.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Instructions for Generators</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Manifest 8700-22</HD>
        <P>The following statement must be included with each Uniform Hazardous Waste Manifest, either on the form, in the instructions to the form, or accompanying the form:</P>
        <P>Public reporting burden for this collection of information is estimated to average: 30 minutes for generators, 10 minutes for transporters, and 25 minutes for owners or operators of treatment, storage, and disposal facilities. This includes time for reviewing instructions, gathering data, completing, reviewing and transmitting the form. Send comments regarding the burden estimate, including suggestions for reducing this burden, to: Chief, Information Policy Branch (2136), U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Ariel Rios Building; 1200 Pennsylvania Ave., NW., Washington, DC 20460; and to the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs, Office of Management and Budget, Washington, DC 20503.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Instructions for Generators</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 1. Generator's U.S. EPA Identification Number</HD>
        <P>Enter the generator's U.S. EPA twelve digit identification number, or the State generator identification number if the generator site does not have an EPA identification number.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 2. Page 1 of _</HD>

        <P>Enter the total number of pages used to complete this Manifest (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, the first page (EPA Form 8700-22) plus the number of Continuation Sheets (EPA Form 8700-22A), if any).</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 3. Emergency Response Phone Number</HD>
        <P>Enter a phone number for which emergency response information can be obtained in the event of an incident during transportation. The emergency response phone number must:</P>
        <P>1. Be the number of the generator or the number of an agency or organization who is capable of and accepts responsibility for providing detailed information about the shipment;</P>
        <P>2. Reach a phone that is monitored 24 hours a day at all times the waste is in transportation (including transportation related storage); and</P>

        <P>3. Reach someone who is either knowledgeable of the hazardous waste being shipped and has comprehensive emergency response and spill cleanup/incident mitigation information for the material being shipped or has immediate access to a person who has that knowledge and information about the shipment.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>

          <P>Emergency Response phone number information should only be entered in Item 3 when there is one phone number that applies to all the waste materials described in Item 9b. If a situation (<E T="03">e.g.</E>, consolidated shipments) arises where more than one Emergency Response phone number applies to the various wastes listed on the manifest, the phone numbers associated with each specific material should be entered after its description in Item 9b.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 4. Manifest Tracking Number</HD>
        <P>This unique tracking number must be pre-printed on the manifest by the forms printer.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 5. Generator's Mailing Address, Phone Number and Site Address</HD>
        <P>Enter the name of the generator, the mailing address to which the completed manifest signed by the designated facility should be mailed, and the generator's telephone number. Note, the telephone number (including area code) should be the normal business number for the generator, or the number where the generator or his authorized agent may be reached to provide instructions in the event the designated and/or alternate (if any) facility rejects some or all of the shipment. Also enter the physical site address from which the shipment originates only if this address is different than the mailing address.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 6. Transporter 1 Company Name, and U.S. EPA ID Number</HD>
        <P>Enter the company name and U.S. EPA ID number of the first transporter who will transport the waste. Vehicle or driver information may not be entered here.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 7. Transporter 2 Company Name and U.S. EPA ID Number</HD>
        <P>If applicable, enter the company name and U.S. EPA ID number of the second transporter who will transport the waste. Vehicle or driver information may not be entered here.</P>
        <P>If more than two transporters are needed, use a Continuation Sheet(s) (EPA Form 8700-22A).</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 8. Designated Facility Name, Site Address, and U.S. EPA ID Number</HD>

        <P>Enter the company name and site address of the facility designated to receive the waste listed on this manifest. Also enter the <PRTPAGE P="406"/>facility's phone number and the U.S. EPA twelve digit identification number of the facility.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 9. U.S. DOT Description (Including Proper Shipping Name, Hazard Class or Division, Identification Number, and Packing Group)</HD>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Item 9a.</E> If the wastes identified in Item 9b consist of both hazardous and nonhazardous materials, then identify the hazardous materials by entering an “X” in this Item next to the corresponding hazardous material identified in Item 9b.</P>
        <P>If applicable, enter the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the second transporter. That person must acknowledge acceptance of the waste described on the manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Item 9b.</E> Enter the U.S. DOT Proper Shipping Name, Hazard Class or Division, Identification Number (UN/NA) and Packing Group for each waste as identified in 49 CFR 172. Include technical name(s) and reportable quantity references, if applicable.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>If additional space is needed for waste descriptions, enter these additional descriptions in Item 27 on the Continuation Sheet (EPA Form 8700-22A). Also, if more than one Emergency Response phone number applies to the various wastes described in either Item 9b or Item 27, enter applicable Emergency Response phone numbers immediately following the shipping descriptions for those Items.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 10. Containers (Number and Type)</HD>
        <P>Enter the number of containers for each waste and the appropriate abbreviation from Table I (below) for the type of container.</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s150" COLS="1" OPTS="L0">
          <TTITLE>Table I—Types of Containers</TTITLE>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">BA = Burlap, cloth, paper, or plastic bags.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">CF = Fiber or plastic boxes, cartons, cases.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">CM = Metal boxes, cartons, cases (including roll-offs).</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">CW = Wooden boxes, cartons, cases.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">CY = Cylinders.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">DF = Fiberboard or plastic drums, barrels, kegs.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">DM = Metal drums, barrels, kegs.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">DT = Dump truck.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">DW = Wooden drums, barrels, kegs.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">HG = Hopper or gondola cars.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">TC = Tank cars.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">TP = Portable tanks.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">TT = Cargo tanks (tank trucks).</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 11. Total Quantity</HD>

        <P>Enter, in designated boxes, the total quantity of waste. Round partial units to the nearest whole unit, and <E T="03">do not</E> enter decimals or fractions. To the extent practical, report quantities using appropriate units of measure that will allow you to report quantities with precision. Waste quantities entered should be based on actual measurements or reasonably accurate estimates of actual quantities shipped. Container capacities are not acceptable as estimates.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 12. Units of Measure (Weight/Volume)</HD>
        <P>Enter, in designated boxes, the appropriate abbreviation from Table II (below) for the unit of measure.</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s150" COLS="1" OPTS="L0">
          <TTITLE>Table II—Units of Measure</TTITLE>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">G = Gallons (liquids only).</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">K = Kilograms.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">L = Liters (liquids only).</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">M = Metric Tons (1000 kilograms).</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">N = Cubic Meters.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">P = Pounds.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">T = Tons (2000 pounds).</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22">Y = Cubic Yards.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <TNOTE>
            <E T="02">Note:</E> Tons, Metric Tons, Cubic Meters, and Cubic Yards should only be reported in connection with very large bulk shipments, such as rail cars, tank trucks, or barges.</TNOTE>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 13. Waste Codes</HD>
        <P>Enter up to six federal and state waste codes to describe each waste stream identified in Item 9b. State waste codes that are not redundant with federal codes must be entered here, in addition to the federal waste codes which are most representative of the properties of the waste.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 14. Special Handling Instructions and Additional Information.</HD>
        <P>1. Generators may enter any special handling or shipment-specific information necessary for the proper management or tracking of the materials under the generator's or other handler's business processes, such as waste profile numbers, container codes, bar codes, or response guide numbers. Generators also may use this space to enter additional descriptive information about their shipped materials, such as chemical names, constituent percentages, physical state, or specific gravity of wastes identified with volume units in Item 12.</P>
        <P>2. This space may be used to record limited types of federally required information for which there is no specific space provided on the manifest, including any alternate facility designations; the manifest tracking number of the original manifest for rejected wastes and residues that are re-shipped under a second manifest; and the specification of PCB waste descriptions and PCB out-of-service dates required under 40 CFR 761.207. Generators, however, cannot be required to enter information in this space to meet state regulatory requirements.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 15. Generator's/Offeror's Certifications</HD>

        <P>1. The generator must read, sign, and date the waste minimization certification statement. In signing the waste minimization certification statement, those generators who have not been exempted by statute or regulation from the duty to make a waste minimization certification under section 3002(b) <PRTPAGE P="407"/>of RCRA are also certifying that they have complied with the waste minimization requirements. The Generator's Certification also contains the required attestation that the shipment has been properly prepared and is in proper condition for transportation (the shipper's certification). The content of the shipper's certification statement is as follows: “I hereby declare that the contents of this consignment are fully and accurately described above by the proper shipping name, and are classified, packaged, marked, and labeled/placarded, and are in all respects in proper condition for transport by highway according to applicable international and national governmental regulations. If export shipment and I am the Primary Exporter, I certify that the contents of this consignment conform to the terms of the attached EPA Acknowledgment of Consent.” When a party other than the generator prepares the shipment for transportation, this party may also sign the shipper's certification statement as the offeror of the shipment.</P>

        <P>2. Generator or Offeror personnel may preprint the words, “On behalf of” in the signature block or may hand write this statement in the signature block prior to signing the generator/offeror certification, to indicate that the individual signs as the employee or agent of the named principal.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>All of the above information except the handwritten signature required in Item 15 may be pre-printed.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Instructions for International Shipment Block</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 16. International Shipments</HD>
        <P>For export shipments, the primary exporter must check the export box, and enter the point of exit (city and state) from the United States. For import shipments, the importer must check the import box and enter the point of entry (city and state) into the United States. For exports, the transporter must sign and date the manifest to indicate the day the shipment left the United States. Transporters of hazardous waste shipments must deliver a copy of the manifest to the U.S. Customs when exporting the waste across U.S. borders.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">III. Instructions for Transporters</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 17. Transporters' Acknowledgments of Receipt</HD>
        <P>Enter the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the first transporter. That person must acknowledge acceptance of the waste described on the manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt. Only one signature per transportation company is required. Signatures are not required to track the movement of wastes in and out of transfer facilities, unless there is a change of custody between transporters.</P>

        <P>If applicable, enter the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the second transporter. That person must acknowledge acceptance of the waste described on the manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt.
        </P>
        <NOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
          <P>Transporters carrying imports, who are acting as importers, may have responsibilities to enter information in the International Shipments Block. Transporters carrying exports may also have responsibilities to enter information in the International Shipments Block. See above instructions for Item 16.</P>
        </NOTE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">IV. Instructions for Owners and Operators of Treatment, Storage, and Disposal Facilities</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 18. Discrepancy</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Item 18a. Discrepancy Indication Space</HD>
        <P>1. The authorized representative of the designated (or alternate) facility's owner or operator must note in this space any discrepancies between the waste described on the Manifest and the waste actually received at the facility. Manifest discrepancies are: significant differences (as defined by §§ 264.72(b) and 265.72(b)) between the quantity or type of hazardous waste designated on the manifest or shipping paper, and the quantity and type of hazardous waste a facility actually receives, rejected wastes, which may be a full or partial shipment of hazardous waste that the TSDF cannot accept, or container residues, which are residues that exceed the quantity limits for “empty” containers set forth in 40 CFR 261.7(b).</P>

        <P>2. For rejected loads and residues (40 CFR 264.72(d), (e), and (f), or 40 CFR 265.72(d), (e), or (f)), check the appropriate box if the shipment is a rejected load (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, rejected by the designated and/or alternate facility and is sent to an alternate facility or returned to the generator) or a regulated residue that cannot be removed from a container. Enter the reason for the rejection or the inability to remove the residue and a description of the waste. Also, reference the manifest tracking number for any additional manifests being used to track the rejected waste or residue shipment on the original manifest. Indicate the original manifest tracking number in Item 14, the Special Handling Block and Additional Information Block of the additional manifests.</P>

        <P>3. Owners or operators of facilities located in unauthorized States (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, states in which the U.S. EPA administers the hazardous waste management program) who cannot resolve significant differences in quantity or type within 15 days of receiving the waste must submit to their Regional Administrator a letter with a copy of the Manifest at <PRTPAGE P="408"/>issue describing the discrepancy and attempts to reconcile it (40 CFR 264.72(c) and 265.72(c)).</P>

        <P>4. Owners or operators of facilities located in authorized States (<E T="03">i.e.</E>, those States that have received authorization from the U.S. EPA to administer the hazardous waste management program) should contact their State agency for information on where to report discrepancies involving “significant differences” to state officials.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Item 18b. Alternate Facility (or Generator) for Receipt of Full Load Rejections</HD>
        <P>Enter the name, address, phone number, and EPA Identification Number of the Alternate Facility which the rejecting TSDF has designated, after consulting with the generator, to receive a fully rejected waste shipment. In the event that a fully rejected shipment is being returned to the generator, the rejecting TSDF may enter the generator's site information in this space. This field is not to be used to forward partially rejected loads or residue waste shipments.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Item 18c. Alternate Facility (or Generator) Signature</HD>
        <P>The authorized representative of the alternate facility (or the generator in the event of a returned shipment) must sign and date this field of the form to acknowledge receipt of the fully rejected wastes or residues identified by the initial TSDF.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 19. Hazardous Waste Report Management Method Codes</HD>
        <P>Enter the most appropriate Hazardous Waste Report Management Method code for each waste listed in Item 9. The Hazardous Waste Report Management Method code is to be entered by the first treatment, storage, or disposal facility (TSDF) that receives the waste and is the code that best describes the way in which the waste is to be managed when received by the TSDF.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 20. Designated Facility Owner or Operator Certification of Receipt (Except As Noted in Item 18a)</HD>
        <P>Enter the name of the person receiving the waste on behalf of the owner or operator of the facility. That person must acknowledge receipt or rejection of the waste described on the Manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt or rejection where indicated. Since the Facility Certification acknowledges receipt of the waste except as noted in the Discrepancy Space in Item 18a, the certification should be signed for both waste receipt and waste rejection, with the rejection being noted and described in the space provided in Item 18a. Fully rejected wastes may be forwarded or returned using Item 18b after consultation with the generator. Enter the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the owner or operator of the alternate facility or the original generator. That person must acknowledge receipt or rejection of the waste described on the Manifest by signing and entering the date they received or rejected the waste in Item 18c. Partially rejected wastes and residues must be re-shipped under a new manifest, to be initiated and signed by the rejecting TSDF as offeror of the shipment.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Manifest Continuation Sheet</HD>
        <GPH DEEP="432" SPAN="2">
          <PRTPAGE P="409"/>
          <GID>ER16JN05.013</GID>
        </GPH>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Instructions—Continuation Sheet, U.S. EPA Form 8700-22A</HD>
        <P>Read all instructions before completing this form. This form has been designed for use on a 12-pitch (elite) typewriter; a firm point pen may also be used—press down hard.</P>
        <P>This form must be used as a continuation sheet to U.S. EPA Form 8700-22 if:</P>
        <P>• More than two transporters are to be used to transport the waste; or</P>
        <P>• More space is required for the U.S. DOT descriptions and related information in Item 9 of U.S. EPA Form 8700-22.</P>

        <P>Federal regulations require generators and transporters of hazardous waste and owners or operators of hazardous waste treatment, <PRTPAGE P="410"/>storage, or disposal facilities to use the uniform hazardous waste manifest (EPA Form 8700-22) and, if necessary, this continuation sheet (EPA Form 8700-22A) for both interstate and intrastate transportation.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 21. Generator's ID Number</HD>
        <P>Enter the generator's U.S. EPA twelve digit identification number or, the State generator identification number if the generator site does not have an EPA identification number.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 22. Page _—</HD>
        <P>Enter the page number of this Continuation Sheet.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 23. Manifest Tracking Number</HD>
        <P>Enter the Manifest Tracking number from Item 4 of the Manifest form to which this continuation sheet is attached.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 24. Generator's Name—</HD>
        <P>Enter the generator's name as it appears in Item 5 on the first page of the Manifest.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 25. Transporter—Company Name</HD>
        <P>If additional transporters are used to transport the waste described on this Manifest, enter the company name of each additional transporter in the order in which they will transport the waste. Enter after the word “Transporter” the order of the transporter. For example, Transporter 3 Company Name. Also enter the U.S. EPA twelve digit identification number of the transporter described in Item 25.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 26. Transporter—Company Name</HD>
        <P>If additional transporters are used to transport the waste described on this Manifest, enter the company name of each additional transporter in the order in which they will transport the waste. Enter after the word “Transporter” the order of the transporter. For example, Transporter 4 Company Name. Each Continuation Sheet can record the names of two additional transporters. Also enter the U.S. EPA twelve digit identification number of the transporter named in Item 26.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 27. U.S. D.O.T. Description Including Proper Shipping Name, Hazardous Class, and ID Number (UN/NA)</HD>
        <P>For each row enter a sequential number under Item 27b that corresponds to the order of waste codes from one continuation sheet to the next, to reflect the total number of wastes being shipped. Refer to instructions for Item 9 of the manifest for the information to be entered.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 28. Containers (No. And Type)</HD>
        <P>Refer to the instructions for Item 10 of the manifest for information to be entered.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 29. Total Quantity</HD>
        <P>Refer to the instructions for Item 11 of the manifest form.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 30. Units of Measure (Weight/Volume)</HD>
        <P>Refer to the instructions for Item 12 of the manifest form.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 31. Waste Codes</HD>
        <P>Refer to the instructions for Item 13 of the manifest form.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 32. Special Handling Instructions and Additional Information</HD>
        <P>Refer to the instructions for Item 14 of the manifest form.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Transporters</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 33. Transporter—Acknowledgment of Receipt of Materials</HD>
        <P>Enter the same number of the Transporter as identified in Item 25. Enter also the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the Transporter (Company Name) identified in Item 25. That person must acknowledge acceptance of the waste described on the Manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 34. Transporter—Acknowledgment of Receipt of Materials</HD>
        <P>Enter the same number of the Transporter as identified in Item 26. Enter also the name of the person accepting the waste on behalf of the Transporter (Company Name) identified in Item 26. That person must acknowledge acceptance of the waste described on the Manifest by signing and entering the date of receipt.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Owner and Operators of Treatment, Storage, or Disposal Facilities</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 35. Discrepancy Indication Space</HD>
        <P>Refer to Item 18. This space may be used to more fully describe information on discrepancies identified in Item 18a of the manifest form.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Item 36. Hazardous Waste Report Management Method Codes</HD>

        <P>For each field here, enter the sequential number that corresponds to the waste materials described under Item 27, and enter the appropriate process code that describes how the materials will be processed when received. If additional continuation sheets are attached, continue numbering the waste materials and process code fields sequentially, and enter on each sheet the process codes <PRTPAGE P="411"/>corresponding to the waste materials identified on that sheet.</P>
        <CITA>[45 FR 33142, May 19, 1980, as amended at 70 FR 10818, Mar. 4, 2005]</CITA>
      </APPENDIX>
    </SUBPART>
  </PART>
</CFRGRANULE>
