<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cfr.xsl"?>
<CFRGRANULE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="CFRMergedXML.xsd">
  <FDSYS>
    <CFRTITLE>12</CFRTITLE>
    <CFRTITLETEXT>Banks and Banking</CFRTITLETEXT>
    <VOL>8</VOL>
    <DATE>2012-01-01</DATE>
    <ORIGINALDATE>2012-01-01</ORIGINALDATE>
    <COVERONLY>false</COVERONLY>
    <TITLE>MORTGAGE ACTS AND PRACTICES-ADVERTISING (REGULATION N)</TITLE>
    <GRANULENUM>1014</GRANULENUM>
    <HEADING>PART 1014</HEADING>
    <ANCESTORS>
      <PARENT HEADING="Title 12" SEQ="1">Banks and Banking</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="CHAPTER X" SEQ="0">BUREAU OF CONSUMER FINANCIAL PROTECTION</PARENT>
    </ANCESTORS>
  </FDSYS>
  <PART>
    <EAR>Pt. 1014</EAR>
    <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 1014—MORTGAGE ACTS AND PRACTICES—ADVERTISING (REGULATION N)</HD>
    <CONTENTS>
      <SECHD>Sec.</SECHD>
      <SECTNO>1014.1</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Scope of regulations in this part.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.2</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.3</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Prohibited representations.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.4</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Waiver not permitted.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.5</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping requirements.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.6</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Actions by states.</SUBJECT>
      <SECTNO>1014.7</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Severability.</SUBJECT>
    </CONTENTS>
    <AUTH>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
      <P>12 U.S.C. 5512, 5581; 15 U.S.C. 1638 note.</P>
    </AUTH>
    <SOURCE>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
      <P>76 FR 78133, Dec. 16, 2011, unless otherwise noted.</P>
    </SOURCE>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.1</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Scope of regulations in this part.</SUBJECT>
      <P>This part, known as Regulation N, is issued by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection to implement the 2009 Omnibus Appropriations Act, Public L. 111-8, section 626, 123 Stat. 524 (Mar. 11, 2009), as amended by the Credit Card Accountability Responsibility and Disclosure Act of 2009, Public Law 111-24, section 511, 123 Stat. 1734 (May 22, 2009), and as amended by the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010, Public Law 111-203, section 1097, 124 Stat. 1376 (July 21, 2010). This part applies to persons over which the Federal Trade Commission has jurisdiction under the Federal Trade Commission Act.</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.2</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
      <P>For the purposes of this part:</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Commercial communication</E> means any written or oral statement, illustration, or depiction, whether in English or any other language, that is designed to effect a sale or create interest in purchasing goods or services, whether it appears on or in a label, package, package insert, radio, television, cable television, brochure, newspaper, magazine, pamphlet, leaflet, circular, mailer, book insert, free standing insert, letter, catalogue, poster, chart, billboard, public transit card, point of purchase display, film, slide, audio program transmitted over a telephone system, telemarketing script, on-hold script, upsell script, training materials provided to telemarketing firms, program-length commercial (“infomercial”), the internet, cellular network, or any other medium. Promotional materials and items and Web pages are included in the term <E T="03">commercial communication.</E>
      </P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Consumer</E> means a natural person to whom a mortgage credit product is offered or extended.</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Credit</E> means the right to defer payment of debt or to incur debt and defer its payment.</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Dwelling</E> means a residential structure that contains one to four units, whether or not that structure is attached to real property. The term includes any of the following if used as a residence: an individual condominium unit, cooperative unit, mobile home, manufactured home, or trailer.</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Mortgage credit product</E> means any form of credit that is secured by real <PRTPAGE P="352"/>property or a dwelling and that is offered or extended to a consumer primarily for personal, family, or household purposes.</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Person</E> means any individual, group, unincorporated association, limited or general partnership, corporation, or other business entity.</P>
      <P>
        <E T="03">Term</E> means any of the fees, costs, obligations, or characteristics of or associated with the product. It also includes any of the conditions on or related to the availability of the product.</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.3</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Prohibited representations.</SUBJECT>
      <P>It is a violation of this part for any person to make any material misrepresentation, expressly or by implication, in any commercial communication, regarding any term of any mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations about:</P>
      <P>(a) The interest charged for the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning:</P>
      <P>(1) The amount of interest that the consumer owes each month that is included in the consumer's payments, loan amount, or total amount due, or</P>
      <P>(2) Whether the difference between the interest owed and the interest paid is added to the total amount due from the consumer;</P>
      <P>(b) The annual percentage rate, simple annual rate, periodic rate, or any other rate;</P>
      <P>(c) The existence, nature, or amount of fees or costs to the consumer associated with the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations that no fees are charged;</P>
      <P>(d) The existence, cost, payment terms, or other terms associated with any additional product or feature that is or may be sold in conjunction with the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to credit insurance or credit disability insurance;</P>
      <P>(e) The terms, amounts, payments, or other requirements relating to taxes or insurance associated with the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations about:</P>
      <P>(1) Whether separate payment of taxes or insurance is required; or</P>
      <P>(2) The extent to which payment for taxes or insurance is included in the loan payments, loan amount, or total amount due from the consumer;</P>
      <P>(f) Any prepayment penalty associated with the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning the existence, nature, amount, or terms of such penalty;</P>
      <P>(g) The variability of interest, payments, or other terms of the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations using the word “fixed”;</P>
      <P>(h) Any comparison between:</P>
      <P>(1) Any rate or payment that will be available for a period less than the full length of the mortgage credit product; and</P>
      <P>(2) Any actual or hypothetical rate or payment;</P>
      <P>(i) The type of mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations that the product is or involves a fully amortizing mortgage;</P>
      <P>(j) The amount of the obligation, or the existence, nature, or amount of cash or credit available to the consumer in connection with the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations that the consumer will receive a certain amount of cash or credit as part of a mortgage credit transaction;</P>
      <P>(k) The existence, number, amount, or timing of any minimum or required payments, including but not limited to misrepresentations about any payments or that no payments are required in a reverse mortgage or other mortgage credit product;</P>
      <P>(l) The potential for default under the mortgage credit product, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning the circumstances under which the consumer could default for nonpayment of taxes, insurance, or maintenance, or for failure to meet other obligations;</P>

      <P>(m) The effectiveness of the mortgage credit product in helping the consumer resolve difficulties in paying debts, including but not limited to misrepresentations that any mortgage credit product can reduce, eliminate, or restructure debt or result in a waiver or forgiveness, in whole or in part, of the consumer's existing obligation with any person;<PRTPAGE P="353"/>
      </P>
      <P>(n) The association of the mortgage credit product or any provider of such product with any other person or program, including but not limited to misrepresentations that:</P>
      <P>(1) The provider is, or is affiliated with, any governmental entity or other organization; or</P>
      <P>(2) The product is or relates to a government benefit, or is endorsed, sponsored by, or affiliated with any government or other program, including but not limited to through the use of formats, symbols, or logos that resemble those of such entity, organization, or program;</P>
      <P>(o) The source of any commercial communication, including but not limited to misrepresentations that a commercial communication is made by or on behalf of the consumer's current mortgage lender or servicer;</P>
      <P>(p) The right of the consumer to reside in the dwelling that is the subject of the mortgage credit product, or the duration of such right, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning how long or under what conditions a consumer with a reverse mortgage can stay in the dwelling;</P>
      <P>(q) The consumer's ability or likelihood to obtain any mortgage credit product or term, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning whether the consumer has been preapproved or guaranteed for any such product or term;</P>
      <P>(r) The consumer's ability or likelihood to obtain a refinancing or modification of any mortgage credit product or term, including but not limited to misrepresentations concerning whether the consumer has been preapproved or guaranteed for any such refinancing or modification; and</P>
      <P>(s) The availability, nature, or substance of counseling services or any other expert advice offered to the consumer regarding any mortgage credit product or term, including but not limited to the qualifications of those offering the services or advice.</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.4</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Waiver not permitted.</SUBJECT>
      <P>It is a violation of this part for any person to obtain, or attempt to obtain, a waiver from any consumer of any protection provided by or any right of the consumer under this part.</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.5</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Recordkeeping requirements.</SUBJECT>
      <P>(a) Any person subject to this part shall keep, for a period of twenty-four months from the last date the person made or disseminated the applicable commercial communication regarding any term of any mortgage credit product, the following evidence of compliance with this part:</P>
      <P>(1) Copies of all materially different commercial communications as well as sales scripts, training materials, and marketing materials, regarding any term of any mortgage credit product, that the person made or disseminated during the relevant time period;</P>
      <P>(2) Documents describing or evidencing all mortgage credit products available to consumers during the time period in which the person made or disseminated each commercial communication regarding any term of any mortgage credit product, including but not limited to the names and terms of each such mortgage credit product available to consumers; and</P>
      <P>(3) Documents describing or evidencing all additional products or services (such as credit insurance or credit disability insurance) that are or may be offered or provided with the mortgage credit products available to consumers during the time period in which the person made or disseminated each commercial communication regarding any term of any mortgage credit product, including but not limited to the names and terms of each such additional product or service available to consumers.</P>
      <P>(b) Any person subject to this part may keep the records required by paragraph (a) of this section in any legible form, and in the same manner, format, or place as they keep such records in the ordinary course of business. Failure to keep all records required under paragraph (a) of this section shall be a violation of this part.</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.6</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Actions by states.</SUBJECT>

      <P>Any attorney general or other officer of a state authorized by the state to bring an action under this part may do so pursuant to section 626(b) of the 2009 Omnibus Appropriations Act, Public Law 111-8, section 626, 123 Stat. 524 (Mar. 11, 2009), as amended by the Credit Card Accountability Responsibility and Disclosure Act of 2009, Public Law <PRTPAGE P="354"/>111-24, section 511, 123 Stat. 1734 (May 22, 2009), and as amended by Public Law 111-203, section 1097, 124 Stat. 2102 (July 21, 2010).</P>
    </SECTION>
    <SECTION>
      <SECTNO>§ 1014.7</SECTNO>
      <SUBJECT>Severability.</SUBJECT>
      <P>The provisions of this part are separate and severable from one another. If any provision is stayed or determined to be invalid, it is the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection's intention that the remaining provisions shall continue in effect.</P>
    </SECTION>
  </PART>
</CFRGRANULE>
