<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cfr.xsl"?>
<CFRGRANULE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="CFRMergedXML.xsd">
  <FDSYS>
    <CFRTITLE>12</CFRTITLE>
    <CFRTITLETEXT>Banks and Banking</CFRTITLETEXT>
    <VOL>8</VOL>
    <DATE>2012-01-01</DATE>
    <ORIGINALDATE>2012-01-01</ORIGINALDATE>
    <COVERONLY>false</COVERONLY>
    <TITLE>LAND REGISTRATION (REGULATION J)</TITLE>
    <GRANULENUM>1010</GRANULENUM>
    <HEADING>PART 1010</HEADING>
    <ANCESTORS>
      <PARENT HEADING="Title 12" SEQ="1">Banks and Banking</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="CHAPTER X" SEQ="0">BUREAU OF CONSUMER FINANCIAL PROTECTION</PARENT>
    </ANCESTORS>
  </FDSYS>
  <PART>
    <EAR>Pt. 1010</EAR>
    <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 1010—LAND REGISTRATION (REGULATION J)</HD>
    <CONTENTS>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—General Requirements</HD>
        <SECHD>Sec.</SECHD>
        <SECTNO>1010.1</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.2</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.3</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.4</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exemptions—general.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.5</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statutory exemptions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.6</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>One hundred lot exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.7</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Twelve lot exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.8</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Scattered site subdivisions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.9</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Twenty acre lots.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.10</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Single-family residence exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.11</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Manufactured home exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.12</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Intrastate exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.13</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.14</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemptions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.15</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemption—multiple site subdivision—determination required.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.16</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemption—determination required.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.17</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Advisory opinion.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.18</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>No Action Letter.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.19</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.20</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Requirements for registering a subdivision—Statement of Record—filing and form.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.21</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effective dates.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.22</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statement of record—initial or consolidated.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.23</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Amendment—filing and form.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.24-1010.28</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.29</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of property report—misstatements, omissions or representation of Bureau approval prohibited.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.35</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Payment of fees.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.45</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Suspensions.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—Reporting Requirements</HD>
        <SECTNO>1010.100</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statement of Record—format.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.101</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.102</SECTNO>

        <SUBJECT>General instructions for completing the Statement of Record.<PRTPAGE P="260"/>
        </SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Developer obligated improvements.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.104</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.105</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cover page.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.106</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Table of contents.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.107</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Risks of buying land.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.109</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Title to the property and land use.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.110</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Roads.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.111</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Utilities.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.112</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Financial information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.113</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Local services.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.114</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recreational facilities.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.115</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Subdivision characteristics and climate.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.116</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.117</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cost sheet, signature of Senior Executive Officer.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.118</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Receipt, agent certification, and cancellation page.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.200</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Instructions for Statement of Record, Additional Information and Documentation.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.201-1010.207</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.208</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.209</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Title and land use.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.210</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Roads.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.211</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Utilities.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.212</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Financial information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.214</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recreational facilities.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.215</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Subdivision characteristics and climate.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.216</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional information.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.219</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Affirmation.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.310</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Annual report of activity.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Certification of Substantially Equivalent State Law</HD>
        <SECTNO>1010.500</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.503</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notice of certification.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.504</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cooperation among certified states and between certified states and the Director.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.505</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Withdrawal of state certification.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.506</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>State/Federal filing requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.507</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effect of suspension or withdrawal of certification granted under § 1010.501(a): Full disclosure requirement.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.508</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effect of suspension of certification granted under § 1010.501(b): Sufficient protection requirement.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.552</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.556</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—amendments and consolidations.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.558</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—notice of revocation rights on property report cover page.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>1010.559</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—notice of revocation rights in contracts and agreements.</SUBJECT>
        <APP>Appendix A to Part 1010—Standard and Model Forms and Clauses</APP>
      </SUBPART>
    </CONTENTS>
    <AUTH>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
      <P>12 U.S.C. 5512, 5581; 15 U.S.C. 1718.</P>
    </AUTH>
    <SOURCE>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
      <P>76 FR 79489, Dec. 21, 2011, unless otherwise noted.</P>
    </SOURCE>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—General Requirements</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.1</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Statutory terms.</E> All terms are used in accordance with their statutory meaning in 15 U.S.C. 1702, unless otherwise defined in paragraph (b) of this section or elsewhere in this part.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Other terms.</E> As used in this part:</P>
        <P>(1)
          <E T="03">Act</E> means the Interstate Land Sales Full Disclosure Act, 15 U.S.C. 1701.</P>
        <P>(2)
          <E T="03">Advisory opinion</E> means the formal written opinion of the Director as to jurisdiction in a particular case or the applicability of an exemption under §§ 1010.5 through 1010.15, based on facts submitted to the Director.</P>
        <P>(3)
          <E T="03">Available for use</E> means that in addition to being constructed, the subject facility is fully operative and supplied with any materials and staff necessary for its intended purpose.</P>
        <P>(4)
          <E T="03">Beneficial property restrictions</E> means restrictions that are enforceable by the lot owners and are designed to control the use of the lot and to preserve or enhance the environment and the aesthetic and economic value of the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(5)
          <E T="03">Date of filing</E> means the date a Statement of Record, amendment, or consolidation, accompanied by the applicable fee, is received by the Director.</P>
        <P>(6)
          <E T="03">Good faith estimate</E> means an estimate based on documentary evidence. In the case of cost estimates, the documentation may be obtained from the suppliers of the services. In the case of estimates of completion dates, the documentation may be actual contracts let, engineering schedules, or other evidence of commitments to complete the amenities.</P>
        <P>(7)
          <E T="03">ILSRP</E> means the Interstate Land Sales Registration Program.</P>
        <P>(8)
          <E T="03">Lot</E> means any portion, piece, division, unit, or undivided interest in land located in any state or foreign country, if the interest includes the right to the exclusive use of a specific portion of the land.</P>
        <P>(9)
          <E T="03">Owner</E> means the person or entity who holds the fee title to the land and has the power to convey that title to others.</P>
        <P>(10)
          <E T="03">Parent corporation</E> means that entity which ultimately controls the subsidiary, even though the control may <PRTPAGE P="261"/>arise through any series or chain of other subsidiaries or entities.</P>
        <P>(11)
          <E T="03">Principal</E> means any person or entity holding at least a 10 percent financial or ownership interest in the developer or owner, directly or through any series or chain of subsidiaries or other entities.</P>
        <P>(12)
          <E T="03">Rules</E> means all rules adopted pursuant to the Act, including the general requirements published in this part.</P>
        <P>(13)
          <E T="03">Sale</E> means any obligation or arrangement for consideration to purchase or lease a lot directly or indirectly. The terms “sale” or “seller” include in their meanings the terms “lease” and “lessor”.</P>
        <P>(14)
          <E T="03">Senior Executive Officer</E> means the individual of highest rank responsible for the day-to-day operations of the developer and who has the authority to bind or commit the developing entity to contractual obligations.</P>
        <P>(15)
          <E T="03">Site</E> means a group of contiguous lots, whether such lots are actually divided or proposed to be divided. Lots are considered to be contiguous even though contiguity may be interrupted by a road, park, small body of water, recreational facility, or any similar object.</P>
        <P>(16)
          <E T="03">Start of construction</E> means breaking ground for building a facility, followed by diligent action to complete the facility.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.2</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.3</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General applicability.</SUBJECT>

        <P>Except in the case of an exempt transaction, a developer may not sell or lease lots in a subdivision, making use of any means or instruments of transportation or communication in interstate commerce, or of the mails, unless a Statement of Record is in effect in accordance with the provisions of this part. In non-exempt transactions, the developer must give each purchaser a printed Property Report, meeting the requirements of this part, in advance of the purchaser's signing of any contract or agreement for sale or lease. Information collection requirements contained in this part have been approved by the Office of Management and Budget under the provisions of 44 U.S.C. 3501 <E T="03">et seq.</E> and have been assigned OMB Control No. 3170-0012.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.4</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Exemptions—general.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The exemptions available under §§ 1010.5 through 1010.16 are not applicable when the method of sale, lease or other disposition of land or an interest in land is adopted for the purpose of evasion of the Act.</P>
        <P>(b) With the exception of the sales or leases which are exempt under § 1010.5, the anti-fraud provisions of the Act (15 U.S.C. 1703(a)(2)) apply to exempt transactions. The anti-fraud provisions make it unlawful for a developer or agent to employ any device, scheme, or artifice to:</P>
        <P>(1) Defraud;</P>
        <P>(2) To obtain money or property by means of any untrue statement of a material fact, or</P>
        <P>(3) To omit to state a material fact necessary in order to make the statements made not misleading, with respect to any information pertinent to the lot or subdivision; or</P>
        <P>(4) To engage in any transaction, practice, or course of business which operates or would operate as a fraud or deceit upon a purchaser.</P>
        <P>(c) The anti-fraud provisions of the Act require that certain representations be included in the contract in transactions which are not exempt under § 1010.5. Specifically, the Act requires that if a developer or agent represents that roads, sewers, water, gas or electric service or recreational amenities will be provided or completed by the developer, the contract must stipulate that the services or amenities will be provided or completed. See § 1011.15(f).</P>
        <P>(d) Eligibility for exemptions available under §§ 1010.5 through 1010.14 is self-determining. With the exception of the exemptions available under §§ 1010.15 and 1010.16, a developer is not required to file notice with or obtain the approval of the Director in order to take advantage of an exemption. If a developer elects to take advantage of an exemption, the developer is responsible for maintaining records to demonstrate that the requirements of the exemption have been met.</P>

        <P>(e) A developer may present evidence, or otherwise discuss, in an informal hearing before the Office of Nonbank Supervision, the Bureau's position on <PRTPAGE P="262"/>the jurisdiction or non-exempt status of a particular subdivision.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.5</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statutory exemptions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>A listing of the statutory exemptions is contained in 15 U.S.C. 1703. In accordance with 15 U.S.C. 1703(a)(2), if the sale involves a condominium or multi-unit construction, a presale clause conditioning the sale of a unit on a certain percentage of sales of other units is permissible if it is legally binding on the parties and is for a period not to exceed 180 days. However, the 180-day provision cannot extend the 2-year period for performance. The permissible 180 days is calculated from the date the first purchaser signs a sales contract in the project or, if a phased project, from the date the first purchaser signs the first sales contract in each phase.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.6</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>One hundred lot exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The sale of lots in a subdivision is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act if, since April 28, 1969, the subdivision has contained fewer than 100 lots, exclusive of lots which are exempt from jurisdiction under § 1010.5. In the sale of lots in the subdivision that are not exempt under § 1010.5, the developer must comply with the Act's anti-fraud provisions, set forth in § 1010.4(b) and (c).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.7</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Twelve lot exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The sale of lots is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act if, beginning with the first sale after June 20, 1980, no more than twelve lots in the subdivision are sold in the subsequent twelve-month period. Thereafter, the sale of the first twelve lots is exempt from the registration requirements if no more than twelve lots were sold in each previous twelve month period which began with the anniversary date of the first sale after June 20, 1980.</P>
        <P>(b) A developer may apply to the Director to establish a different twelve month period for use in determining eligibility for the exemption and the Director may allow the change if it is for good cause and consistent with the purpose of this section.</P>
        <P>(c) In determining eligibility for this exemption, all lots sold or leased in the subdivision after June 20, 1980, are counted, whether or not the transactions are otherwise exempt. Sales or leases made prior to June 21, 1980, are not considered in determining eligibility for the exemption.</P>
        <P>(d) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.8</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Scattered site subdivisions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The sale of lots in a subdivision consisting of noncontiguous parts is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act if:</P>
        <P>(1) Each noncontiguous part of the subdivision contains twenty or fewer lots; and</P>
        <P>(2) Each purchaser or purchaser's spouse makes a personal, on-the-lot inspection of the lot purchased prior to signing a contract.</P>
        <P>(b) For purposes of this exemption, interruptions such as roads, parks, small bodies of water or recreational facilities do not serve to break the contiguity of parts of a subdivision.</P>
        <P>(c) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.9</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Twenty acre lots.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The sale of lots in a subdivision is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act if, since April 28, 1969, each lot in the subdivision has contained at least twenty acres. In determining eligibility for the exemption, easements for ingress and egress or public utilities are considered part of the total acreage of the lot if the purchaser retains ownership of the property affected by the easement.</P>
        <P>(b) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.10</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Single-family residence exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> The sale of a lot which meets the requirements specified under paragraphs (b) and (c) of this section is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Subdivision requirements.</E> (1) The subdivision must meet all local codes and standards.</P>

        <P>(2) In the promotion of the subdivision there must be no offers, by direct mail or telephone solicitation, of gifts, <PRTPAGE P="263"/>trips, dinners or use of similar promotional techniques to induce prospective purchasers to visit the subdivision or to purchase a lot.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Lot requirements.</E> (1) The lot must be located within a municipality or county where a unit of local government or the state specifies minimum standards in the following areas for the development of subdivision lots taking place within its boundaries:</P>
        <P>(i) Lot dimensions.</P>
        <P>(ii) Plat approval and recordation.</P>
        <P>(iii) Roads and access.</P>
        <P>(iv) Drainage.</P>
        <P>(v) Flooding.</P>
        <P>(vi) Water supply.</P>
        <P>(vii) Sewage disposal.</P>
        <P>(2) Each lot sold under the exemption must be either zoned for single-family residences or, in the absence of a zoning ordinance, limited exclusively by enforceable covenants or restrictions to single-family residences. Manufactured homes, townhouses, and residences for one-to-four family use are considered single-family residences for purposes of this exemption provision.</P>

        <P>(3) The lot must be situated on a paved street or highway which has been built to standards established by the state or the unit of local government in which the subdivision is located. If the roads are to be public roads they must be acceptable to the unit of local government that will be responsible for maintenance. If the street or highway is not complete, the developer must post a bond or other surety acceptable to the municipality or county in the full amount of the cost of completing the street or highway to assure completion to local standards. For purposes of this exemption, <E T="03">paved</E> means concrete or pavement with a bituminous surface that is impervious to water, protects the base and is durable under the traffic load and maintenance contemplated.</P>
        <P>(4) The unit of local government or a homeowners association must have accepted or be obligated to accept the responsibility for maintaining the street or highway upon which the lot is situated. In any case in which a homeowners association has accepted or is obligated to accept maintenance responsibility, the developer must, prior to signing of a contract or agreement to purchase, provide the purchaser with a good faith written estimate of the cost of carrying out the responsibility over the first ten years of ownership.</P>
        <P>(5) At the time of closing, potable water, sanitary sewage disposal, and electricity must be extended to the lot or the unit of local government must be obligated to install the facilities within 180 days following closing. For subdivisions which will not have a central water or sewage disposal system, there must be assurances that an adequate potable water supply is available year-round and that the lot is approved for the installation of a septic tank.</P>
        <P>(6) The contract of sale must require delivery within 180 days after the signing of the sales contract of a warranty deed, which at the time of delivery is free from monetary liens and encumbrances. If a warranty deed is not commonly used in the jurisdiction where the lot is located, a deed or grant which warrants that the seller has not conveyed the lot to another person may be delivered in lieu of a warranty deed. The deed or grant used must warrant that the lot is free from encumbrances made by the seller or any other person claiming by, through, or under the seller.</P>
        <P>(7) At the time of closing, a title insurance binder or title opinion reflecting the condition of title must be in existence and issued or presented to the purchaser showing that, subject only to exceptions which are approved in writing by the purchaser at the time of closing, marketable title to the lot is vested in the seller.</P>
        <P>(8) The purchaser or purchaser's spouse must make a personal, on-the-lot inspection of the lot purchased prior to signing a contract or agreement to purchase.</P>
        <P>(d) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.11</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Manufactured home exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The sale of a lot is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act when the following eligibility requirements are met:</P>

        <P>(1) The lot is sold as a homesite by one party and a manufactured home is <PRTPAGE P="264"/>sold by another party and the contracts of sale:</P>
        <P>(i) Obligate the sellers to perform, contingent upon the other seller carrying out its obligations so that a completed manufactured home will be erected on a completed homesite within two years after the date the purchaser signed the contract to purchase the lot;</P>
        <P>(ii) Provide that all funds received by the sellers are to be deposited in escrow accounts independent of the sellers until the transactions are completed;</P>
        <P>(iii) Provide that funds received by the sellers will be released to the buyer upon demand if the lot on which the manufactured home has been erected is not conveyed within two years; and</P>
        <P>(iv) Contain no provisions which restrict the purchaser's remedy of bringing suit for specific performance.</P>
        <P>(2) The homesite is developed in conformance with all local codes and standards, if any, for manufactured home subdivisions.</P>
        <P>(3) At the time of closing:</P>
        <P>(i) Potable water and sanitary sewage disposal are available to the homesite and electricity has been extended to the lot line;</P>
        <P>(ii) The homesite is accessible by roads;</P>
        <P>(iii) The purchaser receives marketable title to the lot; and</P>
        <P>(iv) Other common facilities represented in any manner by the developer or agent to be provided are completed or there are letters of credit, cash escrows or surety bonds in the form acceptable to the local government in an amount equal to 100 percent of the estimated cost of completion. Corporate bonds are not acceptable for purposes of the exemption.</P>
        <P>(4) For purposes of this section, a manufactured home is a unit receiving a label in conformance with U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) regulations implementing the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974 (42 U.S.C. 5401).</P>
        <P>(b) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.12</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Intrastate exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Eligibility requirements.</E> The sale of a lot is exempt from the registration requirements of the Act if the following requirements are met:</P>
        <P>(1) The sale of lots in the subdivision after December 20, 1979, is restricted solely to residents of the state in which the subdivision is located unless the sale is exempt under § 1010.5, § 1010.11, or § 1010.13.</P>
        <P>(2) The purchaser or purchaser's spouse makes a personal on-the-lot inspection of the lot to be purchased before signing a contract.</P>
        <P>(3) Each contract:</P>
        <P>(i) Specifies the developer's and purchaser's responsibilities for providing and maintaining roads, water and sewer facilities and any existing or promised amenities;</P>
        <P>(ii) Contains a good faith estimate of the year in which the roads, water and sewer facilities and promised amenities will be completed; and</P>
        <P>(iii) Contains a non-waivable provision giving the purchaser the opportunity to revoke the contract until at least midnight of the seventh calendar day following the date the purchaser signed the contract. If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract must reflect the requirements of the longer period.</P>
        <P>(4) The lot being sold is free and clear of all liens, encumbrances and adverse claims except the following:</P>
        <P>(i) Mortgages or deeds of trust which contain release provisions for the individual lot purchased if:</P>
        <P>(A) The contract of sale obligates the developer to deliver, within 180 days, a warranty deed (or its equivalent under local law), which at the time of delivery is free from any monetary liens or encumbrances; and</P>
        <P>(B) The purchaser's payments are deposited in an escrow account independent of the developer until a deed is delivered.</P>

        <P>(ii) Liens which are subordinate to the leasehold interest and do not affect the lessee's right to use or enjoy the lot.<PRTPAGE P="265"/>
        </P>
        <P>(iii) Property reservations which are for the purpose of bringing public services to the land being developed, such as easements for water and sewer lines.</P>
        <P>(iv) Taxes or assessments which constitute liens before they are due and payable if imposed by a state or other public body having authority to assess and tax property or by a property owners' association.</P>
        <P>(v) Beneficial property restrictions that are mutually enforceable by the lot owners in the subdivision. Restrictions, whether separately recorded or incorporated into individual deeds, must be applied uniformly to every lot or group of lots. To be considered beneficial and enforceable, any restriction or covenant that imposes an assessment on lot owners must apply to the developer on the same basis as other lot owners. Developers who maintain control of a subdivision through a Property Owners' Association, Architectural Control Committee, restrictive covenant or otherwise, shall transfer such control to the lot owners no later than when the developer ceases to own a majority of total lots in, or planned for, the subdivision. Relinquishment of developer control shall require affirmative action, usually in the form of an election based upon one vote per lot.</P>
        <P>(vi) Reservations contained in United States land patents and similar Federal grants or reservations.</P>
        <P>(5) Prior to the sale the developer discloses in a written statement to the purchaser all qualifying liens, reservations, taxes, assessments and restrictions applicable to the lot purchased. The developer must obtain a written receipt from the purchaser acknowledging that the statement required by this subparagraph was delivered to the purchaser.</P>
        <P>(6) Prior to the sale the developer provides in a written statement good faith estimates of the cost to the purchaser of providing electric, water, sewer, gas and telephone service to the lot. The estimates for unsold lots must be updated every two years or more frequently if the developer has reason to believe that significant cost increases have occurred. The dates on which the estimates were made must be included in the statement. The developer must obtain a written receipt from the purchaser acknowledging that the statement required by this subparagraph was delivered to the purchaser.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Intrastate Exemption Statement.</E> To satisfy the requirements of paragraphs (a)(5) and (6) of this section, an Intrastate Exemption Statement containing the information prescribed in each such paragraph shall be given to each purchaser. A State-approved disclosure document may be used to satisfy this requirement if all the information required by paragraphs (a)(5) and (6) of this section is included in this disclosure. In such a case, the developer must obtain a written receipt from the purchaser and comply with all other requirements of the exemption. To be acceptable for purposes of the exemption, the statement(s) given to purchasers must contain neither advertising nor promotion on behalf of the developer or subdivision nor references to the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection or the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau. A sample Intrastate Exemption Statement is included in the exemption guidelines.</P>
        <P>(c) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.13</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) exemption.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Eligibility requirements.</E> The sale of a lot which meets the following requirements is exempt from registration requirements of the Act:</P>
        <P>(1) The lot is in a subdivision which contains fewer than 300 lots and has contained fewer than 300 lots since April 28, 1969.</P>
        <P>(2) The lot is located within a Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) as defined by the Office of Management and Budget and characterized in paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(3) The principal residence of the purchaser is within the same MSA as the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(4) The purchaser or purchaser's spouse makes a personal on-the-lot inspection of the lot to be purchased prior to signing a contract or agreement.</P>
        <P>(5) Each contract:<PRTPAGE P="266"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Specifies the developer's and purchaser's responsibilities for providing and maintaining roads, water and sewer facilities and any existing or promised amenities;</P>
        <P>(ii) Contains a good faith estimate of the year in which the roads, water and sewer facilities and promised amenities will be completed;</P>
        <P>(iii) Contains a nonwaivable provision giving the purchaser the opportunity to revoke the contract until at least midnight of the seventh calendar day following the date the purchaser signed the contract, or, if the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract must reflect the requirements of the longer period.</P>

        <P>(6) The lot being sold must be free and clear of liens such as mortgages, deeds of trust, tax liens, mechanics' liens, or judgments. For purposes of this exemption, the term <E T="03">liens</E> does not include the following:</P>
        <P>(i) Mortgages or deeds of trust which contain release provisions for the individual lot purchased if:</P>
        <P>(A) The contract of sale obligates the developer to deliver, within 180 days, a warranty deed (or its equivalent under local law), which at the time of delivery is free from any monetary liens or encumbrances; and</P>
        <P>(B) The purchaser's payments are deposited in an escrow account independent of the developer until a deed is delivered.</P>
        <P>(ii) Liens which are subordinate to the leasehold interest and do not affect the lessee's right to use or enjoy the lot.</P>
        <P>(iii) Property reservations which are for the purpose of bringing public services to the land being developed, such as easements for water and sewer lines.</P>
        <P>(iv) Taxes or assessments which constitute liens before they are due and payable if imposed by a state or other public body having authority to assess and tax property or by a property owners' association.</P>
        <P>(v) Beneficial property restrictions that are mutually enforceable by the lot owners in the subdivision. Restrictions, whether separately recorded or incorporated into individual deeds, must be applied uniformly to every lot or group of lots. To be considered beneficial and enforceable, any restriction or covenant that imposes an assessment on lot owners must apply to the developer on the same basis as other lot owners. Developers who maintain control of a subdivision through a Property Owners' Association, Architectural Control Committee, restrictive covenants, or otherwise, shall transfer such control to the lot owners no later than when the developer ceases to own a majority of total lots in, or planned for, the subdivision. Relinquishment of developer control shall require affirmative action, usually in the form of an election based upon one vote per lot.</P>
        <P>(vi) Reservations contained in United States land patents and similar Federal grants or reservations.</P>
        <P>(7) Before the sale the developer gives a written MSA Exemption Statement to the purchaser and obtains a written receipt acknowledging that the statement was received. A sample MSA Exemption Statement is included in the exemption guidelines. A State-approved disclosure document may be used to satisfy this requirement if all of the information required by this section is included. The statement(s) given to purchasers must contain neither advertising nor promotion on behalf of the developer or the subdivision nor references to the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection or the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau. In descriptive and concise terms, the statement that the developer must give the purchaser shall disclose the following:</P>
        <P>(i) All liens, reservations, taxes, assessments, beneficial property restrictions which are enforceable by other lot owners in the subdivision, and adverse claims which are applicable to the lot to be purchased.</P>

        <P>(ii) Good faith estimates of the cost to the purchaser of providing electric, water, sewer, gas and telephone service to the lot. The estimates for unsold lots must be updated every two years, or more frequently if the developer has reason to believe that significant cost increases have occurred. The dates on which the estimates were made must be included in the statement.<PRTPAGE P="267"/>
        </P>
        <P>(8) The developer executes and gives to the purchaser a written instrument designating a person within the state of residence of the purchaser as the developer's agent for service of process. The developer must also acknowledge in writing that it submits to the legal jurisdiction of the state in which the purchaser or lessee resides.</P>
        <P>(9) The developer executes a written affirmation for each sale made under this exemption. By January 31 of each year, the developer submits to the Director a copy of the executed affirmation for each sale made during the preceding calendar year or a master affirmation in which are listed all purchasers' names and addresses and the identity of the lots purchased. Individual affirmations must be available for the Director's review at all times during the year. The affirmation must be in the form provided in section I of the appendix to this part: Form for Developer's Affirmation for Land Sale.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Metropolitan Statistical Area.</E> Metropolitan Statistical Areas are defined by the Office of Management and Budget generally on the basis of population statistics reported in a census. To determine whether a subdivision is located within an MSA and the boundaries of an MSA, contact the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs, Office of Management and Budget, 726 Jackson Place NW., Washington, DC 20503.</P>
        <P>(c) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.14</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemptions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Eligibility requirements.</E> The following transactions are exempt from the registration requirements of the Act unless the Director has terminated the exemption in accordance with paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(1) The sale of lots, each of which will be sold for less than $100, including closing costs, if the purchaser will not be required to purchase more than one lot.</P>
        <P>(2) The lease of lots for a term not to exceed five years if the terms of the lease do not obligate the lessee to renew.</P>
        <P>(3) The sale of lots to a person who is engaged in a bona fide land sales business.</P>
        <P>(4) The sale of a lot to a person who owns the contiguous lot which has a residential, commercial or industrial building on it.</P>
        <P>(5) The sale of real estate to a government or government agency.</P>
        <P>(6) The sale of a lot to a person who has leased and resided primarily on the lot for at least the year preceding the sale.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Termination.</E> If the Director has reasonable grounds to believe that exemption from the registration requirements in a particular case is not in the public interest, the Director may, after issuing a notice and giving the respondent an opportunity to request a hearing within fifteen days of receipt of the notice, terminate eligibility for exemption. The basis for issuing a notice may be the conduct of the developer or agent, such as unlawful conduct or insolvency, or adverse information about the lots or real estate that should be disclosed to the purchasers. Proceedings will be governed by § 1012.238.</P>
        <P>(c) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.15</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemption—multiple site subdivision—determination required.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> (1) The sale of lots contained in multiple sites of fewer than 100 lots each, offered pursuant to a single common promotional plan, is exempt from the registration requirements.</P>

        <P>(2) For purposes of this exemption, the sale of lots in an individual site that exceeds 99 lots is not exempt from registration. Likewise, the sale of lots in a site containing fewer than 100 lots, where the developer either owns contiguous land or holds an option or other evidence of intent to acquire contiguous land which, when taken cumulatively, would or could result in one site of 100 or more lots, is not exempt from registration. Furthermore, the sale of lots that are within a subdivision established by a separate developer is not exempt from registration by this provision.<PRTPAGE P="268"/>
        </P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Eligibility requirements.</E> The sale of each lot must meet the following requirements to be eligible for this exemption.</P>
        <P>(1) The lot is sold “as is” with all advertised improvements and amenities completed and in the condition advertised.</P>
        <P>(2) The lot is in conformance with all local codes and standards.</P>
        <P>(3) The lot is accessible, both legally and physically. For lots which are advertised or otherwise represented as “residential,” either primary or secondary, with any inference that a permanent or temporary dwelling unit of any description (excluding collapsible tents) can be built or installed, physical access must be available by automobile, pick-up truck or equivalent “on-road” vehicle.</P>
        <P>(4) At the time of closing, a title insurance binder or title opinion reflecting the condition of title must be issued to the purchaser showing that, subject only to exceptions approved in writing by the purchaser at the time of closing, marketable title is vested in the seller.</P>
        <P>(5) Each contract or agreement and any promissory notes:</P>
        <P>(i) Contain the non-waivable provision found in section II of the appendix to this part: Language Notifying Buyer of Option to Cancel Contract in bold face type (which must be distinguished from the type used for the rest of the document) on the face or signature page above all signatures. If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state or local law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract must reflect the requirement of the longer period rather than the seven days. The revocation provisions may not be limited or qualified in the contract or other document by requiring a specific type of notice or by requiring that notice be given at a specified place.</P>
        <P>(ii) Obligate the developer to deliver, within 180 days, a warranty deed (or its equivalent under local law) for the lot which at the time of delivery is free from any monetary liens or encumbrances.</P>
        <P>(6) The purchaser or purchaser's spouse makes a personal on-the-lot inspection of the lot to be purchased before signing a contract.</P>
        <P>(7) The purchaser's payments are deposited in an escrow account independent of the developer until a deed is delivered.</P>
        <P>(8) Prior to the purchaser signing a contract or agreement of sale, the developer discloses in a written Lot Information Statement all liens, reservations, taxes, assessments, easements and restrictions applicable to the lot purchased (see paragraph (b)(11) of this section).</P>
        <P>(9) Prior to the purchaser signing a contract or agreement of sale, the developer discloses in a written Lot Information Statement the name, address and telephone number of the local governmental agency or agencies from which information on permits or other requirements for water, sewer and electrical installations can be obtained. This Statement will also contain the name, address and telephone number of the suppliers which would or could provide the foregoing services.</P>
        <P>(10) The lot sale must comply with the anti-fraud provisions of 12 CFR 1010.4(b) and (c) and the sales practices and standards in §§ 1011.10 through 1011.28.</P>
        <P>(11) A written Lot Information Statement must be delivered to, and acknowledged by, each purchaser prior to his or her signing a contract or agreement of sale, and must contain the information shown in the format below. The Statement must be typed or printed in at least 10 point font. A copy of the acknowledgement will be maintained by the developer for three years and will be made available to ILSRP upon request. If the Statement is not delivered as required, the contract or agreement of sale may be revoked and a full refund paid, at the option of the purchaser, within two years of the signing date and the contract or agreement of sale will clearly provide this right. A sample format for the Statement is provided in section III of the appendix to this part: Sample Lot Information Statement and Sample Receipt.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Request for Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption.</E> (1) The developer must file a request for the Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption. The request must be <PRTPAGE P="269"/>accompanied by a filing fee of $500 (prepared in accordance with § 1010.35(a)) and a sample Lot Information Statement, substantially in the form set forth in section IV of the appendix to this part: Request for Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption.</P>
        <P>(2) This exemption will become effective upon issuance of an Exemption Order by the Director.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Annual Report.</E> (1) By January 31 of each year the developer will send a report to the Director listing each site and its location available for a sale pursuant to the exemption during the preceding year and indicate the number of lot sales made in each site. The report will describe any changes in the information provided in the Request for the Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption or contain a statement that there are no changes.</P>
        <P>(2) The Annual Report must be accompanied by a filing fee of $100.</P>
        <P>(3) The Annual Report must be signed and dated by the developer, attesting to its completeness and accuracy.</P>
        <P>(4) Failure to submit the Annual Report within ten days after the receipt of notice from the Director will automatically terminate eligibility for the exemption as of the Report due date.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Termination.</E> If, subsequent to the issuance of an Exemption Order, the Director has reasonable grounds to believe that exemption from the registration requirements in the particular case is not in the public interest, the Director may, after issuing a notice and giving the respondent an opportunity to request a hearing within fifteen days of receipt of the notice, terminate the exemption order. The basis for issuing a notice may be apparent omissions or misrepresentations in the documents submitted to the Director, the conduct of the developer or agent, such as unlawful conduct or insolvency, or adverse information about the real estate that should be disclosed to purchasers. Proceedings will be governed by § 1012.238.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.16</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Regulatory exemption—determination required.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> The Director may exempt from the registration requirements of the Act any subdivision or lots in a subdivision by issuing an order in writing if it is determined that registration is not necessary in the public interest and for the protection of purchasers on the basis of the small amount or limited character of the offering and the requirements contained in paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Eligibility requirements.</E> An exemption order may be issued at the discretion of the Director on the basis of the small amount or limited character of the offering if the following requirements are met:</P>
        <P>(1) The subdivision or sales substantially meet the requirements of one of the exemptions available under this chapter.</P>
        <P>(2) Each contract:</P>
        <P>(i) Specifies the developer's and purchaser's responsibilities for providing and maintaining roads, water and sewer facilities and any existing or promised amenities;</P>
        <P>(ii) Contains a good faith estimate of the year in which the roads, water and sewer facilities and promised amenities will be completed;</P>
        <P>(iii) Contains a non-waivable provision giving the purchaser the opportunity to revoke the contract until at least midnight of the seventh calendar day following the date the purchaser signed the contract. If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract must reflect the requirements of the longer period.</P>
        <P>(iv) Contains a provision that obligates the developer to deliver to the purchaser within 180 days of the date the purchaser signed the sales contract, a warranty deed, or its equivalent under local law, which at the time of delivery is free from any monetary liens or encumbrances.</P>
        <P>(3) The purchaser or purchaser's spouse makes a personal on-the-lot inspection of the lot to be purchased before signing a contract.</P>
        <P>(4) The developer files a request for an exemption order and supporting documentation in accordance with paragraphs (c) and (d) of this section and submits a filing fee of $500.00 in accordance with § 1010.35(a) of this part. This fee is not refundable.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Request.</E> The request for an Exemption Order must be substantially in <PRTPAGE P="270"/>the format set forth in section V of the appendix to this part: Request for Regulatory Exemption Order.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Supporting documentation.</E> A request for an exemption order must be accompanied by the following documentation:</P>
        <P>(1) A plat of the entire subdivision with the lots subject to the exemption request delineated thereon.</P>
        <P>(2) A copy of the contract to be used.</P>
        <P>(3) A clear and specific statement detailing how the proposed sales of lots subject to the exemption request substantially complies with one of the available exemption provisions.</P>
        <P>(4) A description of the method by which the lots have been and will be promoted and to which population centers the promotion has been and will be directed.</P>
        <P>(e) The sale must also comply with the anti-fraud provisions of § 1010.4(b) and (c) of this part.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Termination.</E> If, subsequent to the issuance of an exemption order, the Director has reasonable grounds to believe that exemption from the registration requirements in the particular case is not in the public interest, the Director may, after issuing a notice and giving the respondent an opportunity to request a hearing within fifteen days of receipt of the notice, terminate the exemption order. The basis for issuing a notice may be apparent omissions or misrepresentations in the documents submitted to the Director, the conduct of the developer or agent, such as unlawful conduct or insolvency, or adverse information about the real estate that should be disclosed to purchasers. Proceedings will be governed by § 1012.238.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.17</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Advisory opinion.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> A developer may request an opinion from the Director as to whether an offering qualifies for an exemption or is subject to the jurisdiction of the Act.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Requirements.</E> All requests for Advisory Opinions must be accompanied by the following:</P>
        <P>(1) A $500.00 filing fee submitted in accordance with § 1010.35(a). This fee is not refundable.</P>
        <P>(2) A comprehensive description of the conditions and operations of the offering. There is no prescribed format for submitting this information, but the developer should at least cite the applicable statutory or regulatory basis for the exemption or lack of jurisdiction and thoroughly explain how the offering either satisfies the requirements for exemption or falls outside the purview of the Act.</P>
        <P>(3) An affirmation as set forth in section VI of the appendix to this part: Developer's Affirmation for Advisory Opinion.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.18</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>No Action Letter.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) If the sale of lots is subject to the registration requirements of the Act but the circumstances of the sale are such that no affirmative action to enforce the registration requirements is needed to protect the public interest or prospective purchasers, the Director may issue a No Action Letter.</P>
        <P>(b) To obtain a No Action Letter a developer must submit a request which includes a thorough description of the proposed transaction, the property involved, and the circumstances surrounding the sale.</P>
        <P>(c) The issuance of a No Action Letter will not affect any right which a purchaser has under the Act, and it will not limit future action by the Director if there is evidence to show that affirmative action is necessary to protect the public interest or prospective purchasers. In no event will a No Action Letter be issued after the sale has occurred.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.19</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.20</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Requirements for registering a subdivision—Statement of Record—filing and form.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Filing.</E> In order to register a subdivision and receive an effective date, the developer or owner of the subdivision must file a Statement of Record with the Director. The official address to be used is: CFPB Interstate Land Sales, c/o: Armedia LLC, 8221 Old Courthouse Road, Suite 206, Vienna, VA 22182. When the Statement of Record is filed, a fee in the amount set out in § 1010.35(b) must be paid in accordance with § 1010.35(a).</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Form.</E> The Statement of Record shall be in the format specified in <PRTPAGE P="271"/>§ 1010.100 and shall be completed in accordance with the instructions in §§ 1010.102, 1010.105 through 1010.118, 1010.200, 1010.208 through 1010.216 and 1010.219. It shall be supported by the documents required by §§ 1010.208 through 1010.216 and 1010.219. It shall include any other information or documents which the Director may require as being necessary or appropriate for the protection of purchasers.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">State filings.</E> A Statement of Record submitted under the provisions of 12 CFR part 1010, subpart C—Certification of Substantially Equivalent State Law, shall consist of the materials designated by the Certification Agreement between the Director and the certified state in which the subdivision is located.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.21</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effective dates.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> The effective date of an initial, consolidated or amended Statement of Record is the 30th day after the filing of the latest amendatory material unless the Director notifies the developer in writing prior to such 30th day that:</P>
        <P>(1) The effective date has been suspended in accordance with § 1010.45(a), or</P>
        <P>(2) An earlier effective date has been determined.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Suspension of effective date by developer.</E> (1) A developer, or owner, may request that the effective date of its Statement of Record be suspended, provided there are no administrative proceedings pending against either of them at the time the request is submitted. The request must include any consolidations or amendments which have been made to the initial Statement of Record. Forms for this purpose will be furnished by the Director upon request.</P>
        <P>(2) Upon acceptance by the Director, the effectiveness of the Statement of Record shall be suspended as of the date the request was executed by the developer or owner.</P>
        <P>(3) The suspension shall continue until the developer, or owner, submits all amendments necessary to bring the registration into full compliance with the Regulations which are in effect on the date of the amendments and the Director allows those amendments to become effective.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.22</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statement of record—initial or consolidated.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Initial Statement of Record.</E> (1) Except in the case of exempt transactions, an initial Statement of Record shall be filed, and an effective date issued, prior to selling or leasing any lot in a subdivision.</P>
        <P>(2) If a developer buys from another developer 100 or more lots from an existing registration, the new developer, or owner, may have to submit a new initial Statement of Record and receive an effective date covering the acquired lots prior to selling or leasing any of those lots.</P>
        <P>(3) Changes in principals due to a sale of stock in a corporation or changes in partners or joint venturers which are accomplished in accordance with the partnership or joint venture agreement but which do not cause a change in the title to the land in the subdivision may be submitted as an amendment.</P>
        <P>(4) Any initial Statement of Record must be accompanied by a fee, as specified in § 1010.35(b), based upon the number of lots sought to be registered.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Consolidated Statement of Record.</E> (1) If the developer intends to sell or lease additional lots as part of the same common promotional plan with lots already registered, a consolidated Statement of Record may be submitted for the additional lots. A fee, as specified in § 1010.35(b) and based on the number of additional lots, must accompany the submission. The additional lots may not be sold or leased until a new effective date is issued.</P>
        <P>(2) If the additional lots are simply the result of a replatting of lots previously registered and enumerated in the Property Report and do not include any additional land, the change may be made by an amendment. However, the amendment must be accompanied by a fee, as specified in § 1010.35(b), based on the number of additional lots.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Consolidated Statement of Record—Form.</E> A consolidated Statement of Record shall contain the elements listed in paragraphs (c)(1) through (4) of this section. Pages having no changes and documents in previous submissions which apply equally to the additional <PRTPAGE P="272"/>lots may be included by reference. However, the developer may, at its option, submit the entire format for an initial filing, including copies of previously submitted documents, to expedite the examination process.</P>
        <P>(1) Those pages of the Property Report portion and Additional Information and Documentation portion which contain changes which have occurred since the last effective submission, and</P>
        <P>(2) A recapitulation or listing of each of the section headings, and subheadings if necessary, of the Additional Information and Documentation portion. Each item of the listing shall contain a statement as to whether or not any change is made in the section; whether any new or additional information is being submitted and, if documentation is added by cross reference, the previous submission in which that documentation may be found, and</P>
        <P>(3) Documentation to support the additional lots (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> plat maps, topographic maps and general plan to reflect new lots, title information, permits for additional facilities, financial assurances of completion of additional facilities, financial statements) or updated or expanded documents in support of previous submissions, and</P>
        <P>(4) The affirmation required by § 1010.219.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Consolidated Statement of Record amends prior Statement of Record.</E> A Consolidated Statement of Record shall contain all applicable information for all registered lots in the subdivision except those deleted pursuant to other provisions in these regulations. The resulting Property Report shall be used for all sales in the subdivision, except for those transactions which are exempt from the provisions of the Act or which have been granted an exempt status by the Director, unless the Director has specifically authorized the use of multiple Property Reports.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Initial Statement of Record—when prior approval to submit is required.</E> In those subdivisions where there is a disparity between the lots already registered and those sought to be registered because of location, terrain, proposed use of the lots or the amenities to be furnished or available, the developer may present a resume of the differences and request the Director's permission to file a separate initial Statement of Record for the additional lots. Upon consideration of the facts submitted, the Director may allow such a procedure.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Lots which have been deleted from registration.</E> Should the developer, for any reason, delete by amendment any registered lots from an effective Statement of Record, those lots must be reregistered by a consolidation and a new effective date issued, before they can be sold or leased. An appropriate fee must accompany the submission.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Lots sold to individual purchasers.</E> It is not necessary to delete from the registration those lots which have been sold to individual purchasers for their own use.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.23</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Amendment—filing and form.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Filing.</E> If any change occurs in any representation of material fact required to be stated in an effective Statement of Record, an amendment shall be filed. The amendment shall be filed within 15 days of the date on which the developer knows, or should have known, that there has been a change in material fact.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Form.</E> An amendment shall include by reference the prior Statement of Record except for any changes in material fact. A change in material fact shall be specifically described and supported by the same documentation which would be required for an initial submission. Any amendment shall be accompanied by:</P>
        <P>(1) A letter from the developer giving a clear and concise description of the purpose and significance of the amendment and referring to the section and page of the Statement of Record which is being amended, and</P>
        <P>(2) All pages of the Statement of Record, which have been amended, retyped in the required format to reflect the changes. The ILSRP number of the Statement of Record shall appear at the top of each page of the material submitted.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Amendments to suspended filings.</E> Developers wishing to reactivate a suspended filing shall file the following:</P>

        <P>(1) Any amendments necessary to bring the filing into compliance, submitted in accordance with paragraphs (a) and (b) of this section;<PRTPAGE P="273"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) An activity report in the form prescribed by § 1010.310; and</P>
        <P>(3) An amendment fee, if required under § 1010.35(d)(2).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§§ 1010.24-1010.28</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.29</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of property report—misstatements, omissions or representation of Bureau approval prohibited.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Nothing in these regulations shall be construed to authorize or approve the use of a property report containing any untrue statement of a material fact or omitting to state a material fact required to be stated therein. Nor shall anything in these regulations be construed to authorize or permit any representation that the Property Report is prepared or approved by the Director, ILSRP or the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.35</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Payment of fees.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Method of payment.</E> (1) Each fee must be paid by:</P>
        <P>(i) Certified check, cashier's check, or postal money order made payable to the Treasurer of the United States, with the registration number, when known, and the name, of the subdivision on the face of the check, and mailed to an address specified by the Director; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Electronic payment in a manner specified by the Director.</P>
        <P>(2) Information regarding the current mailing address or electronic payment procedures is available from: Office of Nonbank Supervision, Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection,1700 G Street NW., Washington, DC 20006.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Fees for registration.</E> The fee for each initial and consolidated registration is set forth in section VII of the appendix to this part: Initial and Consolidated Registration Fee Schedule.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Fee for Exemption Order or Advisory Opinion.</E> The filing fee for an Exemption Order or an Advisory Opinion (§ 1010.16 or § 1010.17) is $500. This fee is not refundable.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Amendment fee.</E> (1) A fee of $800 is charged when an Annual Activity Report reflects an annual ending inventory of 101 or more unsold registered lots.</P>
        <P>(2) A fee of $800 is charged for an amendment to reactivate a Statement of Record subsequent to its suspension, unless the developer has 100 or fewer unsold lots included in the Statement of Record.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.45</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Suspensions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Suspension notice—prior to effective date.</E> (1) If it appears to the Director that a Statement of Record or an amendment is on its face incomplete or inaccurate in any material respect, the Director shall so advise the developer, by issuing a suspension notice, within a reasonable time after the filing of such materials but prior to the time the materials would otherwise be effective.</P>
        <P>(2) A suspension notice issued pursuant to this subsection shall suspend the effective date of the Statement of Record or the amendment. It shall continue in effect until 30 days, or such earlier date as the Director may determine, after the necessary amendments are submitted which correct all deficiencies cited in the notice.</P>
        <P>(3) Upon receipt of a suspension notice, the developer has 15 days in which to request a hearing. If a hearing is requested, it shall be held within 20 days of the receipt of the request by the Director.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Suspension orders—subsequent to effective date.</E> (1) A notice of proceedings to suspend an effective Statement of Record may be issued to a developer if the Director has reasonable grounds to believe that an effective Statement of Record includes an untrue statement of a material fact, or omits a material fact required by the Act or rules and regulations, or omits a material fact which is necessary to make the statements therein not misleading. The Director may, after notice, and after opportunity for a hearing requested pursuant to § 1012.220 within 15 days of receipt of such notice, issue an order suspending the Statement of Record. In the event that a suspension order is issued, such order shall remain in effect until the developer has amended the Statement of Record or otherwise complied with the requirements of the order. When the developer has complied with the requirements of the order, the Director shall so declare and thereupon the suspension order shall cease to be effective.<PRTPAGE P="274"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) If the Director undertakes an examination of a developer or its records to determine whether a suspension order should be issued, and the developer fails to cooperate with the Director or obstructs, or refuses to permit the Director to make such examination, the Director may issue an order suspending the Statement of Record. Such order shall remain in effect until the developer has complied with the requirements of the order. When the developer has complied with the requirements of the order, the Director shall so declare and thereupon the suspension order shall cease to be effective. In accordance with the procedure described in § 1012.235, a hearing may be requested.</P>
        <P>(3) Upon receipt of an amendment to an effective Statement of Record, the Director may issue an order suspending the Statement of Record until the amendment becomes effective if the Director has reasonable grounds to believe that such action is necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of purchasers. In accordance with the procedure described in § 1012.235, a hearing may be requested.</P>
        <P>(4) Suspension orders issued pursuant to this subsection shall operate to suspend the Statement of Record as of the date the order is either served on the developer or its registered agent or is delivered by certified or registered mail to the address of the developer or its authorized agent.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—Reporting Requirements</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.100</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Statement of Record—format.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The Statement of Record consists of two portions; the Property Report portion and the Additional Information and Documentation portion.</P>
        <P>(b) General format. The Statement of Record shall be prepared in accordance with the format set forth in section VIII of the appendix to this part: Property Report:</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.101</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.102</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General instructions for completing the Statement of Record.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Paper and type.</E> The Statement of Record shall be on good quality, unglazed white or pastel paper. Letter size paper, approximately 8<FR>1/2</FR> x 11 inches in size, will be used for the Property Report portion and legal size paper, approximately 8<FR>1/2</FR> x 14 inches in size, will be used for the Additional Information and Documentation portion. Side margins shall be no less than 1 inch and no greater than 1<FR>1/2</FR> inches. Top and bottom margins shall be no less than 1 inch. In the preparation of the charts to be included in the Property Report, the developer may vary from the above margin requirements or print the charts lengthwise on the required size paper if such measures are necessary to make the charts readable. The Statement of Record shall be prepared in an easily readable, uniform font.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Numbering and dating.</E> Each page of the Statement of Record as submitted to ILSRP shall be numbered and shall include the date of typing or preparation in the lower right hand corner, except in the final printed version of the Property Report portion.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Signing.</E> The Statement of Record shall be signed by the senior executive officer of the developer or a designated agent.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Printing.</E> The Statement of Record and, insofar as practical, all papers and documents filed as a part thereof, shall be printed, lithographed, photocopied, typewritten or prepared by any similar process which, in the opinion of the Director, produces copies suitable for a permanent record. Irrespective of the process used, all copies of any such materials shall be clear and easily readable.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Headings, subheadings, captions, introductory paragraphs, warnings.</E> Property Report subject “headings” are those descriptive introductory words which appear immediately after section numbers 1010.106 through 1010.116 (<E T="03">e.g.</E> § 1010.108 has “General Information” and § 1010.111 has “Utilities”). Each such heading shall be printed in <PRTPAGE P="275"/>the Property Report in underlined capital letters and centered at the top of a new page. Section numbers shall not be printed in the Property Report. Property Report subheadings are those descriptive introductory words which appear in italics in the regulations at the beginning of paragraphs designated by paragraph letters (a), (b), (c) etc. An example of a subheading is “water” found immediately after the paragraph letter (a) in § 1010.111. These subheadings will be printed in the Property Report only if they are relevant to the subject subdivision. If printed these subheadings shall be capitalized and shall begin at the left hand margin of the page. Property Report “captions” are those descriptive introductory words which appear in italics in the Regulations at the beginning of subparagraphs designated by numbers (1), (2), (3), etc. An example of such captions is “Sales Contract and Delivery of Deed” found immediately after the subparagraph number “(1)” in § 1010.109(b). These captions are to be printed in the Property Report only if they are applicable to the subject subdivision. If printed, these captions shall be centered on the page from the side margins, and shall have only the first letter of each word capitalized. Headings and subheadings will be used in the Property Report in accordance with the sample page appearing in § 1010.102. Introductory paragraphs will follow headings if they are applicable and necessary for a readable entry into the subject matters, but note, the introductory paragraphs for “Title to the Property and Land Use” are to be used in every case as provided in § 1010.109(a)(1). Subheadings and captions which do not apply to the subdivision should be omitted from the Property Report portion and answered “not applicable” in the Additional Information and Documentation portion, unless specifically required to be included elsewhere in these instructions. Warnings shall be printed substantially as they appear in the instructions in §§ 1010.105 through 1010.118. They shall be printed in capital letters and enclosed in a box as shown on the sample page in § 1010.102. The paragraphs in the Property Report portion need not be numbered. A sample page is set forth in section IX of the appendix to this part: Sample Page for Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Language style.</E> All information given in the Property Report portion shall be stated in narrative form using plain, concise, everyday language which can be readily understood by purchasers who are unfamiliar with real estate transactions. Excessively long paragraphs should be avoided. Keep them as brief as possible. Use separate paragraphs for different points discussed. Disclose all pertinent facts. Potential consequences to a purchaser must be made clear even though not specifically asked for in the format and the instructions. In the Property Report the pronouns “you” and “your” shall generally be used in referring to the prospective purchaser and the pronouns “we,” “us,” and “our” shall generally be used in referring to the developer. The Director specifically reserves the right to require modification of the text when the narrative does not meet the standards of this section.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Format of the Additional Information and Documentation portion of the Statement of Record.</E> The supporting information and documentation required by these regulations shall be identified by affixing a tab on the right side of the cover sheet of the required information or documentation and by identifying on the tab the section number of the Statement of Record instructions to which the information or documentation corresponds. This information or documentation shall then be placed immediately after the page(s) on which the section number and answers for that section appear. If the data in a document is applicable to more than one section of instructions, the developer may substitute as a document in the second case a statement incorporating the earlier document. Deeds, title policies, subdivision plats or maps and other documentary information required to be contained in the Additional Information and Documentation portion of the Statement of Record need not be on the same size paper as the Statement of Record but, if larger, shall be folded to a size no larger than 8<FR>1/2</FR> x 14 inches. Supporting documents shall be inserted into the binding in such a manner as to permit <PRTPAGE P="276"/>them to be examined without the necessity of removing them from the binding. This may be accomplished by proper folding or through the use of envelopes.</P>
        <P>(h) <E T="03">Binding.</E> The Statement of Record shall be bound with the Property Report portion on top, including any documents which may be required to be attached when delivered to the purchaser, followed by the Additional Information and Documentation portion.</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Advertising and promotional material.</E> No advertising, or promotional material or statements which are self-serving on behalf of the developer or owner may be included in the Statement of Record or resulting Property Report.</P>
        <P>(j) <E T="03">Additional information.</E> (1) In addition to the information expressly required to be stated in the Statement of Record, there shall be added, and the Director may require, such further material information, documentation and certification as may be necessary in the public interest and for the protection of purchasers or necessary in order to make the statements not misleading in the light of circumstances under which they are made.</P>
        <P>(2) The instructions are not all inclusive. The developer shall include any other facts which would have a bearing upon the use by the purchaser of any of the facilities, services or amenities; which would cause or result in additional expenses to the purchaser; which would have an effect upon the use and enjoyment of the lot by the purchaser for the purpose for which it is sold or which would adversely affect the value of the lot.</P>
        <P>(k) <E T="03">Modification of format or content.</E> The Director may require or permit modification to the content and format of the Property Report to include additional information, to modify or omit required information, or to change the sequence or position of information when such changes are deemed to be in the public interest or for the protection of purchasers.</P>
        <P>(l) <E T="03">Required documentation.</E> Where the documentation required by the Statement of Record cannot be obtained, the Director may permit the best available alternative documentation to be substituted.</P>
        <P>(m) <E T="03">Final version of property report.</E> On the date that a Statement of Record becomes effective, the Property Report portion shall become the Property Report for the subject subdivision. The version of the Property Report delivered to prospective lot purchasers shall be verbatim to that found effective by the Director and shall have no covers, pictures, emblems, logograms or identifying insignia other than as required by these regulations. It shall meet the same standards as to grade of paper, type size, margins, style and color of print as those set herein for the Statement of Record, except where required otherwise by these regulations. However, the date of typing or preparation of the pages and the ILSRP number shall not appear in the final version. If the final version of the Property Report is commercially printed, or photocopied by a process which results in a commercial printing quality, and is bound on the left side, both sides of the pages may be used for printed material. If it is typed or photocopied by a process which does not result in a clear and legible product on both sides of the page or is bound at the top, printing shall be done on only one side of the page. Three copies of the final version of the Property Report, in the exact form in which it is delivered to prospective lot purchasers, shall be sent to ILSRP Office within 20 days of the date on which the Statement of Record, amendment, or consolidation is allowed to become effective by the Director. If a Property Report in a foreign language is used as required by § 1011.25(g), three copies of that Property Report together with copies of the translated documents shall be furnished the Director within 20 days of the date on which the advertising is first used. A Property Report prepared pursuant to these regulations shall not be distributed to potential lot purchasers until after the Statement of Record of which it is a part or any amendment to that Statement of Record has been made effective by the Director.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Developer obligated improvements.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) If the developer represents either orally or in writing that it will provide <PRTPAGE P="277"/>or complete roads or facilities for water, sewer, gas, electricity or recreational amenities, it must be contractually obligated to do so (see § 1011.15(f)), and the obligation shall be clearly stated in the Property Report. While the developer may disclose relevant facts about completion, the obligation to complete cannot be conditioned, other than as provided for in § 1011.15(f), and an estimated completion date (month and year) must be stated in the Property Report. However, a developer that has only tentative plans to complete may so state in the Property Report, provided that the statement clearly identifies conditions to which the completion of the facilities are subject and states that there are no guarantees the facilities will be completed.</P>
        <P>(b) If a party other than the developer is responsible for providing or completing roads or facilities for water, sewer, gas, electricity or recreational amenities, that entity shall be clearly identified in the Property Report under the categories described in § 1010.110, § 1010.111 or § 1010.114, as applicable. A statement shall be included in the proper section of the Property Report that the developer is not responsible for providing or completing the facility or amenity and can give no assurance that it will be completed or available for use.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.104</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.105</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cover page.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The cover page of the Property Report shall be prepared in accordance with the following directions:</P>
        <P>(a) The margins shall be at least 1 inch.</P>
        <P>(b) The next 3 inches shall contain a warning, centered, in <FR>1/2</FR> inch capital letters in red type with <FR>1/4</FR> inch space between the lines which reads as follows: “READ THIS PROPERTY REPORT BEFORE SIGNING ANYTHING”.</P>
        <P>(c) The remainder of the page shall contain the language set forth in section X of the appendix to this part: Language for Warning on Cover Page of Property Report beginning <FR>1/4</FR>-inch below the last line of the warning.</P>
        <P>(d)(1) If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the Cover Page must reflect the requirements of the longer period, rather than the seven days.</P>
        <P>(2)(i) If a deed is not delivered within 180 days of the signing of the contract or agreement of sale or unless certain provisions are included in the contract or agreement, the purchaser is entitled to cancel the contract within two years from the date of signing the contract or agreement.</P>
        <P>(ii) The deed must be a warranty deed, or where such a deed is not commonly used, a similar deed legally acceptable in the jurisdiction where the lot is located. The deed must be free and clear of liens and encumbrances.</P>
        <P>(iii) The contract provisions are:</P>
        <P>(A) A legally sufficient and recordable lot description; and</P>
        <P>(B) A provision that the seller will give the purchaser written notification of purchaser's default or breach of contract and the opportunity to have at least 20 days from the receipt of notice to correct the default or breach; and</P>
        <P>(C) A provision that, if the purchaser loses rights and interest in the lot because of the purchaser's default or breach of contract after 15% of the purchase price, exclusive of interest, has been paid, the seller shall refund to the purchaser any amount which remains from the payments made after subtracting 15% of the purchase price, exclusive of interest, or the amount of the seller's actual damages, whichever is the greater.</P>
        <P>(iv) If a deed is not delivered within 180 days of the signing of the contract or if the necessary provisions are not included in the contract, the following statement shall be used in place of any other rescission language: “Under Federal law you may cancel your contract or agreement of sale any time within two years from the date of signing.”</P>

        <P>(e) At the time of submission, the developer may indicate its intention to comply with the red printing by an illustration or by a statement to that effect.<PRTPAGE P="278"/>
        </P>
        <P>(f) The “Date of This Report” shall be the date on which the Director allows the Statement of Record to become effective and shall not be entered until the submission has become effective.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.106</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Table of contents.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The second page(s) shall consist of a Table of Contents which lists the headings in the Property Report, the major subheadings, if any, and the page on which they appear. An example is set forth in section XI of the appendix to this part: Sample Entry in Table of Contents for Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Use of “You” and “We.”</E> At the end of the Table of Contents insert the following remark: “In this Property Report, the words “you” and “your” refer to the buyer. The words “we,” “us” and “our” refer to the developer.”</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.107</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Risks of buying land.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The next page shall be headed “Risks of Buying Land” and shall contain the paragraphs listed in section XII of the appendix to this part: Required Paragraphs for Risks of Buying Land.</P>
        <P>(b) Warnings. If the instructions of the Director require any warnings to be included in the Property Report portion, the following statement shall be added beneath the “Risks of Buying Land” under a heading “Warnings”: “Throughout this Property Report there are specific warnings concerning the developer, the subdivision or individual lots. Be sure to read all warnings carefully before signing any contract or agreement.” Both the heading, “Warnings,” and the statement shall be printed in capital letters and enclosed in a box.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Insert and complete the format set forth in section XIII of the appendix to this part: Format for General Information.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.109</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Title to the property and land use.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General instructions.</E> (1) Below the heading “Title to the Property and Land Use” insert the introductory paragraphs set forth in section XIV of the appendix to this part: Paragraphs to be included in the General Report—Title to the Property and Land Use.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Information to be provided.</E> After the above introductory paragraphs provide the information required by the following instructions and questions. Follow a general form identical to the sample page set forth in section IX of the appendix to this part: Sample Page for Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Method of sale:</E> (1) <E T="03">Sales contract and delivery of deed.</E> (i) Will the buyer sign a purchase money or installment contract or similar instrument in connection with the purchase of the lot? When will a deed be delivered?</P>
        <P>(ii) If an installment contract is used, include the following, or substantially the same, language in the disclosure narrative under “Method of Sale”: “If you fail to make your payments required by the contract, you may lose your lot and all monies paid.”</P>
        <P>(iii) If, at the time of a credit sale, the developer gives the buyer a deed to the lot, what type of security must the buyer give the seller?</P>
        <P>(iv) If the lots are to be sold on the basis of an installment contract, can the developer or the owner of the subdivision or their creditors encumber the lots under contract? If so, include the following warning in the disclosure narrative under the caption “Sales contract and delivery of deed”: “The (indicate subdivision developer, owner, or their creditors) can place a mortgage on or encumber the lots in this subdivision after they are under contract. This may cause you to lose your lot and any monies paid on it.”</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Type of deed.</E> What type of deed will be used to convey title to lots in the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Quitclaim deeds.</E> If a quitclaim deed is to be given to lot purchasers insert the below warning, or a warning which is substantially the same, in the disclosure narrative below the caption “Quitclaim Deeds.” This particular warning may be deleted at the direction of the Director if an acceptable attorney's opinion is submitted with the Statement of Record which indicates that a quitclaim deed has a meaning in the jurisdiction where the subdivision is located which is substantially contrary to the effect of this warning. This warning shall be phrased substantially <PRTPAGE P="279"/>as follows: “The Quitclaim deed used to transfer title to lots in this subdivision gives you no assurance of ownership of your lot.”</P>
        <P>(4) <E T="03">Oil, gas, and mineral rights.</E> If oil, gas or mineral rights have been reserved, insert the following statement or one substantially the same in the narrative answer under the caption “oil, gas, and mineral rights”: “The (indicate oil, gas, or mineral rights) to (state which lots) in this subdivision will not belong to the purchaser of those lots. The exercise of these rights could affect the use, enjoyment and value of your lot.”</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Encumbrances, mortgages and liens</E>—(1) <E T="03">In general.</E> State whether any of the lots or common facilities which serve the subdivision, other than recreation facilities, are subject to a blanket encumbrance, mortgage or lien. If yes, identify the type of encumbrance (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> deed of trust, mortgage, mechanics liens), the holder of the lien, and the lots covered by the lien. If any blanket encumbrance, mortgage, or lien is not current in accordance with its terms, so indicate.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Release provisions.</E> (i) Explain the effect of any release provisions of any blanket encumbrance, mortgage or lien and include the one of the following statements that pertains.</P>
        <P>(A) If the release clauses are not included in a recorded instrument, insert the statement set forth in section XV of the appendix to this part: Statement on Release Provisions, or one substantially the same in the disclosure narrative below under the caption “Release Provisions.”</P>
        <P>(B) If the developer or subdivision owner states that the release provisions are recorded and that the lot purchaser may pay the release price of the mortgage, the statement shall be supported by documentation supplied in § 1010.209. If the purchaser may pay the release fee, state the amount of the release fee and inform the purchaser that the amount may be in addition to the contract payments unless there is a bona fide trust or escrow arrangement in which the purchaser's payments are set aside to pay the release price before any payments are made to the developer.</P>
        <P>(C)(<E T="03">1</E>) If there are no provisions in the blanket encumbrance for release of an individual purchaser's lot from a blanket encumbrance, include the warning set forth in section XVI of the appendix to this part: Warning for Release Provisions or a warning substantially the same, in the disclosure narrative under the “Release Provisions” caption.</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) If the provisions for release of individual lots from the blanket encumbrance may be exercised only by the developer insert the following statement, or one substantially the same, in the disclosure narrative under the “Release Provisions” caption: “The release provisions in the (state the type of encumbrance) on (indicate all or particular lots) in this subdivision may be exercised only by us. Therefore, if we default on the (state type of encumbrance) before obtaining a release of your lot, you may lose your lot and any money you have paid for it.”</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Recording the contract and deed</E>—(1) <E T="03">Method or purpose of recording.</E> (i) State what protection, if any, recording of deeds and contracts gives a lot purchaser in your jurisdiction.</P>
        <P>(ii) If the sales contract or deed may be recorded, so state. Also state whose responsibility it is to record the contract or deed.</P>
        <P>(iii) If the developer or subdivision owner will not have the sales contract officially acknowledged or if the applicable jurisdiction will not record sales contracts, state that sales contracts will not be recorded and why they will not be recorded.</P>

        <P>(iv) If at, or immediately after, the signing of a contract, the contract or a deed transfer to the buyer is not recorded by the developer or owner or if title to the lot is not otherwise transferred of record to a trust, or if other sufficient notice of transfer or sale is not placed of record, then the developer shall include the warning set forth in section XVII of the appendix to this part: Method and Purpose of Recording Warning, or substantially the same warning in the disclosure narrative under the caption “Method and Purpose of Recording.” The reference to contracts shall be deleted from the above warning if the answer to paragraph (d)(1)(i) of this section indicates <PRTPAGE P="280"/>that recording of a contract in the subject jurisdiction does not protect the purchaser from claims of later purchasers or creditors of anyone having an interest in the land.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Title insurance.</E> If the developer does not deliver a title insurance policy to the buyer, state that the purchaser should obtain an attorney's opinion of title or a title insurance policy which will describe the rights of ownership which are being acquired in the lot. Recommend that an appropriate professional should interpret the opinion or policy.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Payments</E>—(1) <E T="03">Escrow.</E> If purchasers' deposits, down payments, or installment payments are to be placed in a third party controlled escrow or similar account, describe the arrangement including the name and address of the escrow holder or similar person. If there is no such arrangement, insert the statement set forth in section XVIII of the appendix to this part: Escrow Statement. The questions regarding an escrow agreement or similar protection may be answered affirmatively only if the money is under the control of an independent third party, allowing a purchaser to receive a return of all money paid in the event of the developer's failure to convey title or the developer's default on any obligation which would otherwise result in the purchaser's loss of that money.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Prepayments.</E> Explain any prepayment penalties or privileges in everyday language.</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Default.</E> What are the developer's or subdivision owners' remedies against a defaulted purchaser?</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Restrictions on the use of your lot</E>—(1) <E T="03">Restrictive covenants</E> (i) Have any restrictive covenants been recorded against the land in the subdivision? If so, do they contain items which require the purchaser to secure permissions, approvals or take any other action prior to using or disposing of his lot (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> architectural control, developer's right of first refusal, building deadlines, etc.)? If any of these or similar items are included, explain their meaning and effect upon the purchaser.</P>
        <P>(ii) If any restrictive covenants are to be used and if they have not been recorded, how will they be imposed? Include a statement to the effect that the restrictive covenants have not been recorded; that there is no assurance they will be applied uniformly; that they may be changed and that they may be difficult to enforce. If no restrictive covenants will be imposed, include a statement to the effect that, since there are no restrictive covenants on the use of the lots, they may be used for purposes which could adversely affect the use and enjoyment of surrounding lots.</P>
        <P>(iii) If there are restrictive covenants, whether recorded or unrecorded, the following statement shall be made: “A complete copy of these restrictions is available upon request.”</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Easements.</E> (i) Are there easements which may have an effect on the purchaser's building or lot use plans (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> large drainage easements along lot lines, high voltage electric transmission lines, pipe lines or drainage easements which encroach upon the building area of the lot or inhibit its use)?</P>
        <P>(ii) Is the subdivision subject to any type of flood control or flowage easements?</P>
        <P>(iii) If the answer to either (2)(i) or (2)(ii) is in the affirmative, identify the affected lots and state the effect upon the use of the lots.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Plats, zoning, surveying, permits and environment</E>—(1) <E T="03">Plats</E> (i) Have the subdivision plans and plats of specific units been approved by the regulatory authorities? If the approvals have not been obtained, include a warning to the effect that regulatory authorities have not approved the proposed plats; that they may require significant alterations before they will approve them and they may not allow the land to be used for the purpose for which it is being sold.</P>

        <P>(ii) Have plats covering the lots in this Report been recorded? If so, where are they recorded? If they have not been recorded, is the description of the lots given in this Report legally adequate for the conveyance of land in the jurisdiction where the subdivision is located? If it is not, include a statement to the effect that the description of the lots is not legally adequate for the conveyance of the lots and that it will not be until the plat is recorded.<PRTPAGE P="281"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Zoning.</E> For what purpose may the lots be used (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> single family homes, camping, commercial)? Does this use conform to local zoning requirements and the restrictive covenants?</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Surveying.</E> Has each lot been surveyed and is each lot marked for identification? If not, and the purchaser is responsible for the expense, state the estimated cost.</P>
        <P>(4) <E T="03">Permits.</E> Must the purchaser obtain a building permit before beginning construction on his lot? Where is the permit obtained? Are any other permits necessary to use the lot for the purpose for which it is sold or for construction in connection with its use?</P>
        <P>(5) <E T="03">Environment.</E> Has there been any environmental impact study prepared which considers the effect of the subdivision on the environment? If a study has been prepared, summarize any adverse conclusions and refer the lot buyer to the proper State Clearinghouse for complete information. If a study has not been prepared, include a statement that “No determination has been made as to the possible adverse effects the subdivision may have upon the environment and surrounding area.” If the developer does not know whether an environmental impact study has been prepared, or the name and location of the Office where any study made can be found, inquiry should be made to the State or Area Clearinghouse established under the authority of title IV of the Intergovernmental Cooperation Act of 1968.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.110</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Roads.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Access to the subdivision.</E> (1) Is access to the subdivision provided by public or private roads? What type of surface do they have? How many lanes? What is the width of the wearing surface?</P>
        <P>(2) Who is responsible for their maintenance? What is the cost to the purchaser, if any? Are any improvements contemplated? If so, when will they begin and when will they be completed? At whose expense?</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Access within the subdivision.</E> (1) How have legal and physical access by conventional automobile been or will they be, provided to the lots (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> road on recorded easement; right of way dedicated to the public; right of way dedicated to use of lot owners)?</P>
        <P>(2) Who is responsible for the road construction? Is there any construction cost to the purchaser? Is there any financial assurance of completion? If there is no financial assurance of completion, enter a warning to the effect that no funds have been set aside in an escrow or trust account and there are no other financial arrangements to assure completion of the roads.</P>
        <P>(3) How many lanes do the interior roads have? What is the estimated starting date of construction (month and year); the present percentage of construction now complete; the present surface; the estimated completion date (month and year) and what is the final surface to be? If there are separate units or sections in the subdivision which will have different completion dates or different surfaces, the chart in section XIX of the appendix to this part: Road Chart shall be used rather than a narrative paragraph.</P>
        <P>(4) Who is responsible for road maintenance? If the roads are to be maintained by a public authority, a property owners' association or some other entity at some time in the future, who is responsible for their maintenance during the interim period? What is the cost to the purchaser during the interim period and after acceptance for permanent maintenance? Will they be maintained so as to provide access to the lots on a year round basis? If not, include a warning which informs the purchaser that access may not be available year round. Identify the months when access may not be available to lots. If there are no arrangements for maintenance, include a warning to the effect that purchasers are responsible for maintaining the roads and that, if maintenance is not performed, the roads may soon deteriorate and access may become difficult or impossible.</P>
        <P>(5) If estimated completion dates given in prior Statements of Record have not been met, state that previous dates have not been met and give the previous dates. Underline the answer. If the roads are 100 percent completed, no dates are needed.</P>

        <P>(6) Complete the chart in section XX of the appendix to this part: Nearby <PRTPAGE P="282"/>Communities Chart by listing the county seat (identify) and at least two nearby communities. Include at least one community of significant size which offers general services.</P>
        <P>(7) If the purchasers will be individually responsible for providing access to their lots and for maintaining that access, what is the estimated cost of construction and maintenance?</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.111</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Utilities.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Water.</E> (1) How is water to be supplied to the individual lots (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> central system or individual wells)? Of the following items only those which apply to the subdivision need be included.</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Individual system.</E> (A) If water is to be supplied by an individual private well, cistern or other individual system, what are the total estimated costs of the system, including but not limited to, the costs of installation, storage, any treatment facilities and other necessary equipment?</P>
        <P>(B) If individual cisterns or similar storage tanks are to be used, state where water to fill them can be secured; the cost of the water, and its delivery costs for a supply sufficient to serve the monthly needs of a family of four living in a house on a year-round basis. Include a statement to the effect that water stored for extended periods tends to become stale and may acquire an unpleasant taste or odor.</P>
        <P>(C) If individual wells are to be used and if the sales contract contains no provisions for refund or exchange in the event a productive well cannot be installed, include a statement to the effect that there is no assurance a productive well can be installed and, if it cannot, no refund of the purchase price of the lot will be made.</P>
        <P>(D) If individual wells or individual cisterns are to be used, include a brief statement to the effect that the purity and chemical content of the water cannot be determined until each individual well or source of water is completed and tested.</P>
        <P>(E) If there have been no hydrological surveys in connection with the use of individual wells or sources of hauled water for cisterns, include a warning to the effect that there is no assurance of a sufficient supply of water for the anticipated population.</P>
        <P>(F) Is a permit required to install the individual system to be used? If so, from whom and where is the permit secured? State the cost of a permit.</P>
        <P>(ii) <E T="03">Central system.</E> (A) If water is to be provided by a central system, who is the supplier? What is the supplier's address?</P>
        <P>(B) Will the water mains be extended in front of, or adjacent to, each lot? When will construction begin? What is the present percentage of completion of the water mains and central supply plant? When will service be available to the individual lots? If the central system is not complete and there are separate units or sections of the subdivision included in the Statement of Record which have different completion dates, then the starting date for construction (month and year), the percentage of construction now complete and the estimated service availability date (month and year) shall be set forth in the chart in section XXI of the appendix to this part: Water Chart Form rather than in a narrative paragraph.</P>
        <P>(C) What is the present capacity of the central plant (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> how many connections can be supplied)? If the capacity is not sufficient to serve all lots in the Statement of Record and is to be expanded in phases, what is the time-table for each phase to be in service and what will trigger the beginning of the expansion for each phase? If an entity other than the developer or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer will supply the water for the central system; if the operation of that entity is supervised by a governmental agency and if that entity states it can supply the anticipated population of the development, then information as to the capacity of the plant and a hydrological survey is not necessary. If the entity does not indicate it can supply enough water for the anticipated population or if the capacity of any central system is not sufficient to serve all lots in the Statement of Record, include a warning which describes the limitations and sets forth the number of lots which can now be served.</P>

        <P>(D) Have there been any hydrological surveys to determine that a sufficient source of water is available to serve <PRTPAGE P="283"/>the anticipated population of the subdivision? Has the water in the central system been tested for purity and chemical content? If so, did the results show that the water meets all standards for a public water supply? If there have been no hydrological surveys showing a sufficient supply of water or no tests for purity and chemical content for the central system, include a warning to the effect that there is no assurance of a sufficient supply or that the water is drinkable.</P>
        <P>(E) Is there any financial assurance of completion of the central system and any future expansion? If not, include a warning to the effect that no funds have been set aside in an escrow or trust account nor have any other financial arrangements been made to assure completion of the water system.</P>
        <P>(F) If the developer or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer operates the central system, have all permits been obtained from the proper agencies for the construction, use and operation of the central system? If not, include a warning to the effect that the required permits, approvals or licenses for construction, operation or use of the water system have not been obtained, therefore there is no assurance the system can be constructed or used.</P>
        <P>(G) If previous completion dates given in prior Statements of Record have not been met, state that previous completion dates have not been met and give the previous dates. Underline the answer. If the central water system is 100 percent completed, no dates are needed.</P>
        <P>(H) Is the purchaser to pay any construction costs, one-time connection fees, availability fees, special assessments or deposits for the central system? If so, what are the amounts? If not, state that there are no charges other than use fees. If the purchaser will be responsible for construction costs of the water mains, state the cost to install the mains to the most remote lot covered by this report.</P>
        <P>(I) If a purchaser wishes to use a lot prior to the date central water is available to it, may the purchaser install an individual system? If so, include the information required for individual systems in § 1010.111(a)(1)(i). Will the purchaser be required to discontinue use of any individual system and connect to the central system when service is available to the lot? If the purchaser is not required to connect to the central system, must any construction costs, connection fees, availability fees, special assessments or deposits in connection with the central system still be paid? If an individual system may not be installed, so state and indicate water will not be available until the central system is extended to the lot.</P>
        <P>(J) If connection to the system is voluntary and not all purchasers elect to use the system, will the cost to those who do use the system be increased? If so, include a statement to the effect that connection to the central system is voluntary and those who use the system may have to pay a disproportionate share of the cost of the system and its operation.</P>
        <P>(K) If the developer is to construct the system and will later turn it over to a property owners' association for operation and maintenance, state the estimated date and conditions of the conveyance and if it will be conveyed free and clear of any encumbrance. If there is a charge or if the association must assume an encumbrance, state the estimated amount of either and the terms for retirement of either obligation.</P>
        <P>(L) If the supplier of water is other than a governmental agency or an entity which is regulated and supervised by a governmental agency, state that neither the operation of the water system nor the rates are regulated by a public authority.</P>
        <P>(M) The warning “We do not own or operate the central water system so we cannot assure its continued availability for your use” shall be included unless:</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) The central water system is owned and operated by the developer, or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer, or</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) The central water system is owned and operated by a governmental agency or by an entity which is regulated and supervised by a governmental agency.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Sewer.</E> (1) What methods of sewage disposal are to be used (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> central system, comfort stations or individual on-site systems such as septic tanks, <PRTPAGE P="284"/>holding tanks, etc.) in the subdivision? Of the following items, only those which apply to the subdivision need be included.</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Individual systems.</E> (A) If individual systems are to be used, have the local authorities given general approval to the use of these systems in the subdivision or have they given specific approval for each lot? Are permits necessary? From whom and where are they obtained? Must testing of the lot be done prior to the issuance of a permit? State the cost of a permit and the estimated costs of the system and any necessary tests.</P>
        <P>(B) If holding tanks are to be used, state whether pumping and hauling service is available and the estimated monthly costs of that service for a family of four living in a house on a year-round basis.</P>
        <P>(C) If each and every lot has not been approved for the use of an individual on-site system, include a warning to the effect that there is no assurance permits can be obtained for the installation and use of individual on-site systems. If the sales contract contains no provisions for refund or exchange in the event a permit cannot be obtained, include a statement to the effect that there is no assurance an individual on-site system can be installed and, if it cannot, no refund of the purchase price of the lot will be made.</P>
        <P>(D) If no permit is required for the installation and use of individual on-site systems, explain whether this may have an effect upon the purchaser or the availability of construction or permanent financing.</P>
        <P>(E) If the developer has knowledge that permits for the installation of individual on-site systems have been denied; that there have been unsatisfactory percolation tests or that systems have not operated satisfactory in the subdivision, state the number of these rejections, unsatisfactory tests or operations.</P>
        <P>(ii) <E T="03">Comfort stations.</E> (A) If comfort stations are to be used, how many lots will be served by each station? When will construction be started? When will the station or stations be completed and ready for use? Have the necessary permits been obtained for the construction and use of comfort stations? If the necessary permits have not been obtained, include a warning that the necessary permits, approvals or licenses have not been obtained for the construction and use of the comfort stations; therefore there is no assurance they can be constructed or used. If there are comfort stations located in different units and having different completion dates, the chart found in section XXII of the appendix to this part: Comfort Station Chart shall be used to show the estimated construction starting date (month and year), the present percentage of completion and the date on which they will be used rather than a narrative paragraph.</P>
        <P>(B) Who is to construct the comfort stations? Is there any financial assurance of their completion? If not, include a warning to the effect that no funds have been set aside in an escrow or trust account nor have any other financial arrangements been made to assure completion of the comfort stations and there is no assurance the facilities will be completed.</P>
        <P>(C) Who will be responsible for maintenance of the comfort stations? Is there any cost to the purchaser for construction, use or maintenance?</P>
        <P>(iii) <E T="03">Central system.</E> (A) If a central sewage treatment and collection system is being installed, who is responsible for construction of the system? Will the sewer mains be installed in front of, or adjacent to, each lot? When will construction be started (month and year)? When will service be available (month and year)? Who will own and operate the system? Give the name and address of the entity.</P>

        <P>(B) What is the present percentage of completion and the present capacity of the system (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> number of connections which can be served)? If the present capacity is not sufficient to serve all lots in the Statement of Record and it is to be expanded in phases, what is the time-table for expansion and what will trigger that expansion? If the central system is not complete and there are separate units or sections of the subdivision which have different service availability dates, the chart found in section XXIII of the appendix to this part: Sewer Chart shall be used to show the construction starting date (month <PRTPAGE P="285"/>and year); the percentage of completion and service availability date (month and year) in each unit or section rather than a narrative paragraph. If sewage treatment facilities are to be supplied by an entity which is regulated by a governmental agency and which is not the developer or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer and the entity has stated it can serve the anticipated population of the development, then information on capacity need not appear.</P>
        <P>(C) If the developer or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer operates the central system, have all necessary permits been obtained for the construction, operation and use of the central system? Do these permits limit the number of connections or homes which the system may serve? If the permits have not been obtained, enter a warning to the effect that the necessary permits, approvals or licenses have not been obtained for the central sewage system; therefore there is no assurance that the system can be completed, operated or used.</P>
        <P>(D) If the system cannot now serve all lots included in the Statement of Record, either because the supplier of the service has not stated it can and will serve all lots or if construction has not reached a stage where all lots can be served or permits to serve all lots have not been obtained, include a warning which states that all lots cannot now be served; the number which can be served and the reason for the lack of capacity.</P>
        <P>(E) Will the purchaser pay any construction costs, special assessments, one time connection fees or availability fees? What are the amounts of these charges? If the purchaser is to pay construction costs of the sewer mains, state the cost of installation of the mains to the most remote lot in this Report.</P>
        <P>(F) If the purchaser wishes to use the lot prior to the date central sewer service is available, may the purchaser install an individual system? If so, include the information on individual systems required by § 1010.111(b)(1)(i). Will the purchaser be required to discontinue use of the individual system and connect to the central system when service is available? If the purchaser is not required to connect to the central system, must the purchaser still pay any construction costs, connection fees, availability fees, or special assessments? If the purchaser may not install an individual system, so state and indicate service will not be available until the central system reaches the lot.</P>
        <P>(G) If connection to the system is voluntary and not all purchasers elect to use the system, will the cost to those who do use the system be increased? If so, include a statement to the effect that connection to the central system is voluntary and those who use the system may have to pay a disproportionate share of the cost of the system and its operation.</P>
        <P>(H) Is there any financial assurance of completion of the central system and any future expansion? If not, include a warning that no funds have been set aside in an escrow or trust account nor have any other financial arrangements been made to assure the completion of the central system; therefore there is no assurance that it will be completed.</P>
        <P>(I) If previous completion dates given in prior Statements of Record have not been met, state that previous dates have not been met and give the previous dates. Underline the answer. If the central sewage treatment and collection system are 100 percent completed, no dates are needed.</P>
        <P>(J) If the developer is to construct the system and will later turn it over to a property owners' association for operation and maintenance, state the date of the transfer and whether there will be any charge for the conveyance and if it will be conveyed free and clear of any encumbrance. If there is a charge or if the association must assume an encumbrance, state the estimated amount of either and the terms for retirement of either obligation.</P>
        <P>(K) If the owner or operator of the central sewer system is other than a governmental agency or an entity which is regulated and supervised by a governmental agency, state that neither the operation of the sewer system nor the rates are regulated by a public authority.</P>

        <P>(L) The warning “We do not own or operate the central sewer system so we <PRTPAGE P="286"/>cannot assure its continued availability for your use.” shall be included unless:</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) The central sewer system is owned and operated by the developer, or an affiliate or subsidiary of the developer, or</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) The central sewer system is owned and operated by a governmental agency or by an entity which is regulated and supervised by a governmental agency.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Electricity.</E> (1) Who will provide electrical services to the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(2) Have primary electrical service lines been extended in front of, or adjacent to, all of the lots? If not, when (month and year) or under what conditions will construction begin and when will service be available? If they have not been installed, who is responsible for their construction? If electrical service lines have not been extended in front of, or adjacent to, all lots and there are separate units or sections having different service availability dates, the chart found in section XXIV of the appendix to this part: Electric Service Chart shall be used rather than a narrative paragraph.</P>
        <P>(3) If construction of the lines or service to the ultimate consumer is provided by an entity other than a publicly regulated utility, who provides, or will provide, the service? Who will be responsible for maintenance? What is the assurance of completion? If service is not provided by a publicly regulated utility, what charges or assessments will the purchaser pay?</P>
        <P>(4) If the primary service lines have not been extended in front of, or adjacent to each lot, will the purchaser be responsible for any construction costs? If so, what is the utility company's policy and charges for extension of primary lines? Based on that policy, what would be the cost to the purchaser for extending primary service to the most remote lot in this Report?</P>

        <P>(5) If electrical service will not be provided, what is an alternate source (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> generators, etc.) and what are the estimated costs?</P>
        <P>(6) If the lines are to be installed by some entity other than a publicly regulated utility and if there is no financial assurance of completion, include a warning to the effect that no funds have been set aside in an escrow or trust account nor have any other financial arrangements been made to assure construction of the electric lines.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Telephone.</E> (1) Is telephone service now, or will it be, available? Who will furnish the service?</P>
        <P>(2) Have the service lines been extended in front of, or adjacent to, each of the lots? If not, when, and under what conditions, will construction be started and when will service be available (month and year)?</P>
        <P>(3) If the service lines have not been extended in front of, or adjacent to, each lot, will the purchaser be responsible for any construction costs? If so, what is the utility company's policy and charges for extension of service lines? Based on that policy, what would be the cost to the purchaser of extending service lines to the most remote lot in this Report?</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Fuel or other energy source.</E> (1) What fuel, or other energy source, will be available for heating, cooking, etc. in the subdivision? If other than electricity is to be used, describe the availability of the fuel or other energy source. Give the name and address of the supplier. If the fuel is natural gas, when will the mains be installed to the lots? What is the cost to the purchaser for installation fees and connection fees? If oil or propane gas will be used, include the cost of a storage tank.</P>
        <P>(2) [Reserved]</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.112</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Financial information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The information required by paragraphs (b) and (c) of this section need appear only if the answer to the question is an affirmative one.</P>
        <P>(b) Has the developer had a deficit in retained earnings or experienced an operating loss during the last fiscal year or, if less than a year old, since its formation? If so, include a statement to the effect that this may affect the developer's ability to complete promised facilities and to discharge financial obligations. This statement may be omitted if:</P>

        <P>(1) All facilities, utilities and amenities proposed to be completed by the developer in the Property Report and sales contract have been completed so that the lots included in the Statement of Record are immediately usable for <PRTPAGE P="287"/>the purpose for which they are sold, or if:</P>
        <P>(2) The developer is contractually obligated to the purchaser to complete all facilities, utilities and amenities promised by it in the Statement of Record, and:</P>
        <P>(i) The developer has made financial arrangements, such as the posting of surety bonds (corporate or individual notes or bonds are not acceptable), irrevocable letters of credit, escrow or trust accounts, to assure that the facilities, utilities and amenities will be completed by the dates set out in the Property Report or contract;</P>
        <P>(ii) The sales contract provides for delivery of a deed within 180 days of the signing of the contract which conveys title free of any mortgage or lien, or the developer has filed an assurance of title agreement with ILSRP as outlined in § 1010.212(e); and</P>
        <P>(iii) Any down payments or deposits are held in an escrow or trust account.</P>
        <P>(c) If the developer's financial statements have been audited, did the accountant qualify the opinion or decline to give an opinion? If so, why was the opinion qualified or declined?</P>
        <P>(d) The following statement shall appear: “A copy of our financial statements for the period ending _____ is available from us upon request.”</P>
        <P>(e) The information furnished in § 1010.212(b) may necessitate a warning as to costs and/or feasibility of the completion of the subdivision.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.113</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Local services.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Fire protection.</E> Describe the availability of fire protection and indicate whether it is available year round.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Police protection.</E> Describe the availability of police protection.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Schools.</E> State whether elementary, junior high and senior high schools are available to residents of the subdivision. Is school bus transportation available from within the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Hospital.</E> Give the name and location of the nearest hospital and state whether ambulance service is available.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Physicians and dentists.</E> State the location of the nearest physicians' and dentists' offices.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Shopping facilities.</E> State the location of the nearest shopping facilities.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Mail service.</E> If there is no mail service to the subdivision, describe the arrangements the purchasers must make to receive mail service.</P>
        <P>(h) <E T="03">Public transportation.</E> Is there public transportation available in the subdivision or to nearby towns? If not, give the location of the nearest public transportation and the distance from the subdivision.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.114</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recreational facilities.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Recreational facilities to be covered.</E> Unless otherwise indicated, all information required by paragraphs (b) and (c) of this section shall be provided for only those recreational facilities which</P>
        <P>(1) The developer is contractually responsible to provide or complete and which are:</P>
        <P>(i) Within, adjacent or contiguous to the subdivision, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Maintained substantially for the use of lot owners; or</P>
        <P>(2) For which a third party is responsible and which are:</P>
        <P>(i) Within, adjacent or contiguous to the subdivision, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Maintained substantially for the use of lot owners.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Recreational facility chart.</E> Complete the chart found in section XXV of the appendix to this part: Recreational Facility Chart in accordance with the instructions which follow it. This chart shall immediately follow the § 1010.114 heading. Limit the chart to facilities provided essentially for use of lot buyers.</P>
        <P>(1) <E T="03">Facility.</E> Identify each recreational facility. Identify closely related facilities (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> swimming pool and bathhouse) separately only if their availability dates differ. If any recreational facility is not owned by the developer, insert a warning below the chart phrased substantially as follows: “We do not own the (name of facility or facilities) so we can not assure its (their) continued availability.”</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Percent complete.</E> State the present percentage of completion of construction for each recreational facility.</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Estimated date of start of construction.</E> Insert the estimated date of the start of construction for the facility (month and year).<PRTPAGE P="288"/>
        </P>
        <P>(4) <E T="03">Estimated date available for use.</E> If the construction of the facility is not complete or if it is not available to lot owners for its intended use, indicate the estimated date (month and year) that the facility will be available for use. If the “estimated date available for use” for any facility has been amended to delay it to a later date, indicate such delay in a statement immediately below the chart. Underline the response. This statement shall include the name of the facility and the prior estimated availability date, and it shall be referenced to the appropriate facility listed on the chart by use of an asterisk or other appropriate symbol. If a facility is 100 percent completed and in use, no date is needed.</P>
        <P>(5) <E T="03">Financial assurance of completion.</E> If the construction of the facility is not complete, state whether there is any financial assurance of completion. If none, state “none.” If such exists, state the type of assurance (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> bond, escrow, or trust). If no documentation for such assurance has been provided in § 1010.214 of the Statement of Record, then do not indicate such assurance on the chart, but in place of such assurance on the chart state “none.”</P>
        <P>(6) <E T="03">Buyer's annual cost or assessments.</E> State the lot buyer's annual cost or assessments for using the facility. These costs should include any applicable property owners' association assessment, and the developer's maintenance assessment. If the cost information is lengthy, you may use an asterisk or other appropriate symbol and include the cost information in a paragraph below the chart.</P>
        <P>(c) Information to be provided below the recreational facility chart and related warnings.</P>
        <P>(1) <E T="03">Constructing the facilities.</E> If the facilities are not complete, indicate who is responsible for the construction of the facilities. Indicate whether the purchaser will be required to pay any of the cost of construction of these facilities (estimate and disclose such cost, if any).</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Maintaining the facilities.</E> Indicate who is responsible for the operation and maintenance of these facilities.</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Facilities which will be leased to lot purchasers.</E> If no facilities covered here will be leased to a Property Owners' Association or other lot owners in the subject subdivision, omit this caption and any information requested under it from the Property Report. If such leases exist or are anticipated, state which facilities are or will be leased and indicate the term of the lease. Also, state whether the lot owners will have an opportunity to terminate or ratify the lease after control of the Property Owners' Association is turned over to them. Indicate whether the owner of a recreational facility leased to the Property Owners' Association or other lot owners may encumber it and whether the holders of such encumbrances may acquire the leased facilities and not honor the lease. Indicate whether the lease payments may be increased on an escalating or other basis and what costs or expenses, if any, will be borne by the owner. State whether the lease can be assigned or sublet. State how the lease can be terminated.</P>
        <P>(4) <E T="03">Transfer of the facilities.</E> If there are presently any liens or mortgages on any of these recreational facilities, describe such liens or mortgages. If the developer, or owner of the subdivision, their principals, or subsidiaries, intend to transfer the title of a listed recreational facility in the future, explain at what time, by what type of conveyance, and to whom such transfer will be made. Disclose any adverse effects on, or cost to, lot purchasers which may be caused by such transfer. If any facility is to be transferred to lot owners as a Property Owners' Association or otherwise, state whether the facility will be transferred free and clear of all liens and encumbrances. If not, state the amount of the encumbrance to be assumed and disclose any contractual conditions on such transfer which relate to lot purchasers.</P>
        <P>(5) <E T="03">Permits.</E> If the necessary permits have not been obtained for the construction and/or use of the facilities, identify the facilities for which such permits have not been obtained and include the following statement, or one substantially the same, in the narrative under the caption “Permits”: “The (identify the permit or license) has not been obtained and therefore there is no assurance that the lot owners will be able to use the (identify the facility).”<PRTPAGE P="289"/>
        </P>
        <P>(6) <E T="03">Who may use the facilities.</E> Indicate who will be permitted to use the recreational facilities (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> lot owners, their guests, employees of developer, general public). If the general public will be permitted to use the facilities include the following statement in the narrative under the caption “Who may use the facilities”: “The (identify the facility) is open to use by the general public and their use of the facility may limit use of it by lot owners.”</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.115</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Subdivision characteristics and climate.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General topography.</E> What is the general topography and the major physical characteristics of the land in the subdivision? State the percentage of the subdivision which is to remain as natural open space and as developed parkland. Are there any steep slopes, rock outcroppings, unstable or expansive soil conditions, etc., which will necessitate the use of special construction techniques to build on, or use, any lot in the subdivision? If so, identify the lots affected, and describe the techniques recommended. If any lots in the subdivision have a slope of 20%, or more, include a warning that “Some lots in this subdivision have a slope of 20%, or more. This may affect the type and cost of construction.”</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Water coverage.</E> Are any lots, or portions of any lots, covered by water at any time? What lots are affected? When are they covered by water? How does this affect their use for the purpose for which they are sold? Can the condition be corrected? At what cost to the purchaser?</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Drainage and fill.</E> Identify the lots which require draining or fill prior to being used for the purpose for which they are being sold. Who will be responsible for any corrective action? If the purchaser is responsible, what are the estimated costs?</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Flood plain.</E> Is the subdivision located within a flood plain or an area designated by any Federal, state or local agency as being flood prone? What lots are affected? Is flood insurance available? Is it required in connection with the financing of any improvements to the lot? What is the estimated cost of the flood insurance?</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Flooding and soil erosion.</E> (1) Does the developer have a program which provides, or will provide, at least minimum controls for soil erosion, sedimentation or periodic flooding throughout the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(2) If there is a program, describe it. Include in the description information as to whether the program has been approved by the appropriate government officials; when it is to start; when it is to be completed (month and year); whether the developer is obligated to comply with the program and whether there is any financial assurance of completion.</P>
        <P>(3) If there is no program or if the program has not been approved by the appropriate officials or if the program does not provide minimum protection, include a statement to the effect that the measures being taken may not be sufficient to prevent property damage or health and safety hazards. A minimum program will usually provide for:</P>
        <P>(i) Temporary measures such as mulching and seeding of exposed areas and silt basins to trap sediments in runoff water, and</P>
        <P>(ii) Permanent measures such as sodding and seeding in areas of heavy grading or cut and fill along with the construction of diversion channels, ditches, outlet channels, waterway stabilizers and sediment control basins.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Nuisances.</E> Are there any land uses which may adversely affect the subdivision (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> unusual or unpleasant noises or odors, pollutants or nuisances such as existing or proposed industrial activity, military installations, airports, railroads, truck terminals, race tracks, animal pens, noxious smoke, chemical fumes, stagnant ponds, marshes, slaughterhouses and sewage treatment facilities)? If any nuisances exist, describe them. If there are none, state there are no nuisances which affect the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Hazards.</E> (1) Are there any unusual safety factors which affect the subdivision (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> dilapidated buildings, abandoned mines or wells, air or vehicular traffic hazards, danger from fire or explosion or radiation hazards)? Is the developer aware of any proposed plans for construction which may create a nuisance or safety hazard or adversely affect the subdivision? If there are any <PRTPAGE P="290"/>existing hazards or if there is any proposed construction which will create a nuisance or hazard, describe the hazard or nuisance. If there are no existing or possible future hazards, state that there are none.</P>

        <P>(2) Is the area subject to natural hazards or has it been formally identified by any Federal, state or local agency as an area subject to the frequent occurrence of natural hazards (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> tornadoes, hurricanes, earthquakes, mudslides, forest fires, brush fires, avalanches, flash flooding)? If the jurisdiction in which the subdivision is located has a rating system for fire hazard, state the rating assigned to the land in the subdivision and explain its meaning.</P>
        <P>(h) <E T="03">Climate.</E> What are the average temperature ranges, summer and winter, for the area in which the subdivision is located (<E T="03">i.e.,</E> high, low and mean)? What is the average annual rainfall and snowfall?</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Occupancy.</E> How many homes are occupied on a full- or part-time basis as of (date of submission)?</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.116</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Property Owners' Association.</E> (1) Will there be a property owners' association for the subdivision? Has it been formed? What is its name? Is it operating? If not yet formed, when will it be formed? Who is responsible for its formation?</P>
        <P>(2) Does the developer exercise, or have the right to exercise, any control over the Association because of voting rights or placement of officers or directors? For how long will this control last?</P>
        <P>(3) Is membership in the association voluntary? Will non-member lot owners be subject to the payment of dues or assessments? What are the association dues? Can they be increased? Are members subject to special assessments? For what purpose? If membership in the association is voluntary and if the association is responsible for operating or maintaining facilities which serve all lot owners, include the following statement: “Since membership in the association is voluntary, you may be required to pay a disproportionate share of the association costs or it may not be able to carry out its responsibilities.”</P>
        <P>(4) What are the functions and responsibilities of the association? Will the association hold architectural control over the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(5) Are there any functions or services that the developer now provides at no charge for which the association may be required to assume responsibility in the future? If so, will an increase in assessments or fees be necessary to continue these functions or services?</P>
        <P>(6) Does the current level of assessments, fees, charges or other income provide the capability for the association to meet its present, or planned, financial obligations including operating costs, maintenance and repair costs and reserves for replacement? If not, how will any deficit be made up?</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Taxes.</E> (1) When will the purchaser's obligation to pay taxes begin? To whom are the taxes paid? What are the annual taxes on an unimproved lot after the sale to a purchaser? If the taxes are to paid to the developer, include a statement that “Should we not forward the tax funds to the proper authorities, a tax lien may be placed against your lot.”</P>
        <P>(2) If the subdivision is encompassed within a special improvement district or if a special district is proposed, describe the purpose of the district and state the amount of assessments. Describe the purchaser's obligation to retire the debt.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Violations and litigations.</E> This information need appear only if any of the questions are answered in the affirmative. Unless the Director gives prior approval for it to be omitted, a brief description of the action and its present status or disposition shall be given.</P>

        <P>(1) With respect to activities relating to or in violation of a Federal, state or local law concerned with the environment, land sales, securities sales, construction or sale of homes or home improvements, consumer fraud or similar activity, has the developer, the owner of the land or any of their principals, officers, directors, parent corporation, subsidiaries or an entity in which any of them hold a 10% or more financial interest, been:<PRTPAGE P="291"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Disciplined, debarred or suspended by any governmental agency, or is there now pending against them an action which could result in their being disciplined, debarred or suspended or,</P>
        <P>(ii) Convicted by any court, or is there now pending against them any criminal proceedings in any court? ILSRP suspension notices on pre-effective Statements of Record and amendments need not be listed.</P>
        <P>(2) Has the developer, the owner of the land, any principal, any person holding a 10% or more financial or ownership interest in either, or any officer or director of either, filed a petition in bankruptcy? Has an involuntary petition in bankruptcy been filed against it or them or have they been an officer or director of a company which became insolvent or was involved, as a debtor, in any proceedings under the Bankruptcy Act during the last 13 years?</P>
        <P>(3) Is the developer or any of its principals, any parent corporation or subsidiary, any officer or director a party to any litigation which may have a material adverse impact upon its financial condition or its ability to transfer title to a purchaser or to complete promised facilities? If so, include a warning which describes the possible effects which the action may have upon the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Resale or exchange program.</E> (1) Are there restrictions which might hinder lot owners in the resale of their lots (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> a prohibition against posting signs, limitations on access to the subdivision by outside brokers or prospective buyers; the developer's right of first refusal; membership requirements)? If so, briefly explain the restrictions.</P>
        <P>(2) Does the developer have an active resale program? If the answer is “no,” include the following statement: “We have no program to assist you in the sale of your lot.”</P>
        <P>(3) Does the developer have a lot exchange program? If the answer is “yes,” describe the program; state any conditions and indicate if the program reserves a sufficient number of lots to accommodate all those wishing to participate. If there is no program or if sufficient lots are not reserved, include one of the following statements as applicable: “We do not have any provision to allow you to exchange one lot for another” or “We do not have a program which assures that you will be able to exchange your lot for another.”</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Unusual situations.</E> This topic need appear only if one or more of the following cases apply to the subdivision, then only the applicable subject, or subjects, will appear.</P>
        <P>(1) <E T="03">Leases.</E> What is the term of the lease? Is it renewable? Is it recordable? Can creditors of the developer, or owner, acquire title to the property without any obligation to honor the terms of the lease? Are the lease payments a flat sum or are they graduated? Can the lessee mortgage or otherwise encumber the leasehold? Will the lessee be permitted to remove any improvements which have been installed when the lease expires or is terminated?</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Foreign subdivision.</E> (i) Is the owner or developer of the subdivision a foreign country corporation? If legal action is necessary to enforce the contract, must it be taken in the courts of the country where the subdivision is located?</P>
        <P>(ii) Does the country in which the subdivision is located have any laws which restrict, in any way, the ownership of land by aliens? If so, what are the restrictions?</P>
        <P>(iii) Must an alien obtain a permit or license to own land, build a home, live, work or do business in the country where the subdivision is located? If so, where is such permit or license secured; for how long is it valid and what is its cost?</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Time sharing.</E> (i) How is title to be conveyed? How many shares will be sold in each lot? How is use time allocated? How are taxes, maintenance and utility expenses divided and billed? How are voting rights in any Association apportioned? Are there management fees? If so, what are their amounts and how are they apportioned?</P>

        <P>(ii) Is conveyance of any portion of the lot contingent upon the sale of the remaining portions? Is the initial buyer responsible for any greater portion of the expense than his normal share until the remaining interests are <PRTPAGE P="292"/>sold? If the purchase of any of the portions is financed, will the default of one owner have any effect upon the remaining owners?</P>
        <P>(4) <E T="03">Memberships.</E> (i) Does the purchaser receive any interest in title to the land? What is the term of the membership? Is it renewable? What disposition is made of the membership in the event of the death of the member? Are the lots individually surveyed and the corners marked? If not, how does the member identify the area which the member is entitled to use? What is the approximate square footage the member is entitled to use? Are there different classes of membership? How are the different classes identified and what are the differences between them?</P>
        <P>(ii) If the member does not receive any interest in the title to the land, include a warning to the effect that “you receive no interest in the title to the land but only the right to use it for a certain period of time.”</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Equal opportunity in lot sales.</E> State whether or not the developer is in compliance with title VIII of the Civil Rights Act of 1968 by not directly or indirectly discriminating on the basis of race, color, religion, sex, national origin, familial status, and handicap in any of the following general areas: Lot marketing and advertising, rendering of lot services, and in requiring terms and conditions on lot sales and leases. An affirmative answer cannot be given if the developer, directly or indirectly, because of race, color, religion, sex, national origin, familial status, or handicap is:</P>
        <P>(1) Refusing to sell or lease lots after the making of a bona fide offer or to negotiate for the sale or lease of lots or is otherwise making unavailable or denying a lot to any person, or</P>
        <P>(2) Discriminating against any person in the terms, conditions or privileges in the sale or leasing of lots or in providing services or facilities in connection therewith, or</P>
        <P>(3) Making, printing, publishing or causing to be made, printed or published any notice, statement or advertisement with respect to the sale or leasing of lots that indicates any preference, limitation or discrimination against any person, or</P>
        <P>(4) Representing to any person that any lot is not available for inspection, sale or lease when such lot is in fact available, or</P>
        <P>(5) For profit, inducing or attempting to induce any person to sell or lease any lot by representations regarding the entry or non-entry into the neighborhood of a person or persons of a particular race, color, religion, sex, national origin, familial status, or handicap.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Listing of lots.</E> Provide a listing of lots which shall consist of a description of the lots included in the Statement of Record by the names or number of the section or unit, if any; the block number, if any; and the lot numbers. The lots shall be listed in the most efficient and concise manner. If the filing is a consolidation, the listing shall include all lots registered to date in the subdivision, except any which have been deleted by amendment.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.117</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cost sheet, signature of Senior Executive Officer.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Cost sheet—Format.</E> (1) The cost sheet shall be prepared in accordance with the format found in section XXVI of the appendix to this part: Cost Sheet Format and paragraph (a)(2) of this section.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Cost sheet instructions.</E> (i) All amounts for cost sheet items will be entered before the purchaser signs the receipt. However, any costs that are identical for all lots may be pre-printed.</P>
        <P>(ii) If a central water or sewer system will be used in all or part of the subdivision and a private system in all or other parts, then the portion that does not apply to the purchaser's lot shall be crossed out.</P>

        <P>(iii) If individual private systems may be used prior to the availability of service from any central system and the purchaser is not required to connect to any central system, both figures may be entered or only the highest cost figures may be used with a parenthetical explanation or footnote. If the purchaser is required to connect to any central system and discontinue the use of his private system when central service is available, both cost figures shall be given, together with an explanation or footnote.<PRTPAGE P="293"/>
        </P>
        <P>(iv) If there is a one time, lump sum “availability fee” which is assessed to the purchaser in connection with a central utility, include under “other” and identify.</P>
        <P>(v) Dues and assessments need be included only if they are involuntary regardless of use.</P>
        <P>(vi) At the discretion of the Director, where there is extreme diversity in the figures for different areas of the subdivision, variations may be permitted as to whether the figures will be printed, entered manually, or a range of costs used or any combination of these features.</P>
        <P>(vii) The estimated annual taxes shall be based upon the projected valuation of the lot after sale to a purchaser.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Signature of the Senior Executive Officer.</E> The Senior Executive Officer or a duly authorized agent shall sign the property report. Facsimile signatures may be used for purposes of reproduction of the property report.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.118</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Receipt, agent certification, and cancellation page.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Format.</E> The receipt, agent certification and cancellation page shall be prepared in accordance with the sample found in section XXVII of the appendix to this part: Sample Receipt, Agent Certification and Cancellation Page.</P>
        <P>(b) The original and one copy of this executed page shall be attached to the Property Report delivered to prospective purchasers. After the purchaser has signed the receipt and the salesman has signed the certification, the copies can be retained by the developer for a period of three years from the date of execution or the term of the contract, whichever is the longer. Upon demand by the Director, the developer shall, without delay, make the copies of these receipts and certifications available for inspection by the Director or the developer shall forward to the Director any of the receipts and certifications, or copies thereof, as the Director may specify.</P>
        <P>(c) If the transaction takes place through the mails, the cost figures shall be entered and the person most active in dealing with the prospective purchaser shall sign the certification prior to mailing the Property Report to the purchaser. Otherwise, the certification shall be executed in the presence of the purchaser.</P>
        <P>(d) The date of Report appearing on the receipt shall be the same as that appearing on the cover sheet of the Property Report.</P>
        <P>(e) Notification of cancellation by mail shall be considered given at the time post-marked.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.200</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Instructions for Statement of Record, Additional Information and Documentation.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The Additional Information and Documentation portion of the Statement of Record shall contain the statements and documents required in §§ 1010.208 through 1010.219. Each section number and its associated heading and each paragraph letter or number and their associated subheadings or captions must appear in this portion. Following each heading, subheading, or caption printed in this portion, the registrant shall insert an appropriate response. If a heading, subheading, or caption does not apply to the subdivision, it shall be followed by the words “not applicable”. Immediately after the page(s) on which the section number and answers for that section appear, insert the information or documents which support that section. In addition to the statements and documentation expressly required there shall be added any further material, information, documentation and certifications as may be necessary in the public interest and for the protection of purchasers or to cause the statements made to be not misleading in the light of the circumstances under which they are made.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§§ 1010.201-1010.20</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT> [Reserved]</SUBJECT>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.208</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Administrative information.</E> (1) State whether the material represents an initial Statement of Record or a consolidated Statement of Record. If it is a consolidated Statement of Record, identify the original ILSRP number assigned to the initial Statement of Record. State whether subsequent Statements of Record will be submitted for additional lots in the subdivision.<PRTPAGE P="294"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) Has the developer submitted a request for an exemption for the subdivision?</P>
        <P>(3) List the states in which registration has been made by the developer for the sale of lots in the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(4) If any state listed in paragraph (a)(3) of this section has not permitted a registration to become effective or has suspended the registration or prohibited sales, name the state involved and give the reasons cited by the state for their action.</P>
        <P>(5) State whether the developer has made, or intends to make, a filing with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) which is related in any way to the subdivision. If a filing has been made with the SEC, give the SEC identification number; identify the prospectus by name; date of filing and state the page number of the prospectus upon which specific reference to the subdivision is made. Any disciplinary action taken against the developer by the SEC should be disclosed in §§ 1010.116 and 1010.216.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Subdivision information.</E> (1) If this is a consolidated Statement of Record, state the number of lots being added, the number of lots in prior Statements of Record and the new total number of lots. The Director must be able to reconcile the numbers stated here with the title evidence; the plat maps and the disclosure in § 1010.108.</P>
        <P>(2) State the number of acres represented by the lots in this Statement of Record. If this is a consolidated Statement of Record, state the number of acres being added, the number of acres in prior Statements of Record and the new total number of acres. State the total acreage owned in the subdivision, the number of acres under option or similar arrangement for acquisition of title to the land and the total acreage to be offered pursuant to the same common promotional plan.</P>
        <P>(3) State whether any lots have been sold in this subdivision since April 28, 1969, and prior to registration with ILSRP. If they were sold pursuant to an exemption, identify the exemption provision and state whether an advisory opinion, exemption order or exemption determination was obtained with respect to those lots sales. Give the ILSRP number assigned to the exemption, if any.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Developer information.</E> (1) State the name, address, Internal Revenue Service number and telephone number of the owner of the land. If the owner is other than an individual, name the type of legal entity and list the interest, and extent thereof, of each principal. Identify the officers and directors.</P>
        <P>(2) If the developer is not the owner of the land, state the developer's name, address, Internal Revenue Service number and telephone number. If the developer is other than an individual, name the type of legal entity and list the interest, and the extent thereof, of each principal. Identify the officers and directors.</P>
        <P>(3) If you wish to appoint an authorized agent, state the agent's name, address and telephone number and scope of responsibility. This shall be the party designated by the developer to receive correspondence, service of process and notice of any action taken by ILSRP. In all Statements of Record, including those for foreign subdivisions, the authorized agent shall be a resident of the United States. A change of the authorized agent will require an appropriate amendment.</P>
        <P>(4) State whether the owner of the land, the developer, its parent, subsidiaries or any of the principals, officers or directors of any of them are directly or indirectly involved in any other subdivision containing 100 or more lots. If so, identify the subdivision by name, location, and ILSRP number, if any.</P>
        <P>(5) State whether the owner or developer is a subsidiary corporation. If either the owner or developer is a subsidiary corporation or if any of the principals of the owner or developer are corporate entities, name the parent and/or corporate entity and state the principals of each to the ultimate parent entity.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Documentation.</E> (1) Submit a copy of the property report, subdivision report, offering statement or similar document filed with the state or states with which the subdivision has been registered.</P>

        <P>(2) Submit a copy of a general plan of the subdivision. This general plan must consist of a map, prepared to scale, and <PRTPAGE P="295"/>it must identify the various proposed sections or blocks within the subdivision, the existing or proposed roads or streets, and the location of the existing or proposed recreational and/or common facilities. In an initial filing, this map must at least show the area included in the Statement of Record. In a consolidated Statement of Record, show areas being added, as well as the areas previously registered. If a map of the entire subdivision is submitted with the initial Statement of Record, and if no substantial changes are made when material for a consolidated Statement of Record is submitted, the original map may be included by reference.</P>
        <P>(3)(i) If the developer is a corporation, submit a copy of the articles of incorporation, with all amendments; a copy of the certificate of incorporation or a certificate of a corporation in good standing and, if the subdivision is located in a state other than the one in which the original certificate of corporation was issued, a certificate of registration as a foreign corporation with the state where the subdivision is located.</P>
        <P>(ii) If the developer is a partnership, unincorporated association, joint stock company, joint venture or other form of organization, submit a copy of the articles of partnership or association and all other documents relating to its organization.</P>
        <P>(iii) If the developer is not the owner of the land, submit copies of the above documents for the owner.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.209</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Title and land use.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">General information.</E> (1) State whether the developer has reserved the right to exchange or withdraw lots after a purchaser has signed a sales contract (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> for prior sales, failure to pass credit check). If yes, indicate this authority and make reference to the applicable paragraph in the sales contract or other document.</P>
        <P>(2) State whether there is a provision giving purchasers an option to exchange lots. If yes, indicate this and make reference to the applicable paragraph in the sales contract or other document.</P>
        <P>(3) State whether the developer knows of any instruments not of record which, if recorded, would affect title to the subdivision. If yes, copies of these instruments shall be submitted, except that copies of unrecorded contracts for sales of lots in the subdivision need not be submitted.</P>
        <P>(4)(i) Identify the Federal, State, and local agencies or similar organizations which have the authority to regulate or issue permits, approvals or licenses which may have a material effect on the developer's plans with respect to the proposed division of the land, and any existing or proposed facilities, common areas or improvements to the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(ii) Describe or identify the land or facilities affected; the permit, approval or license required; and indicate whether the permit, approval or license has been obtained by the developer.</P>
        <P>(iii) If no agency regulates the division of the land or issues any permits, approvals or licenses with respect to improvements, so state.</P>
        <P>(iv) Answers must specifically cover the areas of environmental protection; environmental impact statements; and construction, dredging, bulkheading, etc. that affect bodies of water within or around the subdivision. Also include licenses or permits required by water resources boards, pollution control boards, river basin commissions, conservation agencies or similar organizations.</P>
        <P>(5) State whether it is unlawful to sell lots prior to the final approval and recording of a plat map in the jurisdiction where the subdivision is located.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Title evidence.</E> (1) Submit title evidence that specifically states the status of the legal and equitable title to the land comprising the lots covered by the Statement of Record and any common areas or facilities disclosed in the Property Report. Title evidence need not be submitted for those common areas and facilities which are not owned by the developer.</P>

        <P>(2) Acceptable title evidence shall be dated no earlier than 20 business days preceding the date of the filing of the Statement of Record with the Director. Previously issued title evidence may be updated to the date referred to in the preceding sentence by endorsements or attorneys' opinions of title.<PRTPAGE P="296"/>
        </P>
        <P>(3) The developer shall amend the title evidence to reflect the change in status of title of any previously registered, reacquired lots unless their status is at least as marketable as they were when first offered for sale by the developer as registered lots.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Forms of acceptable title evidence.</E> (1) An original or a copy of a signed owner's or mortgagee's policy of title insurance, title commitment, certificate of title or similar instrument issued by a title company authorized by law to issue such instruments in the state in which the subdivision is located. Title evidence that limits insurance or negligence liability to amounts less than the market value of the subject land at the time of its acquisition by the subdivision owner is not acceptable;</P>
        <P>(2) A legal opinion stating the condition of title, prepared and signed by an attorney at law experienced in the examination of titles and a member of the Bar in the state in which the property is located. The title opinion may be based on a Torrens land registration system certificate of title, or similar instrument, provided it meets all general title evidence requirements of this section and a copy of the registration certificate of title is submitted. Title opinions that limit negligence liability to amounts less than the market value of the subject land at the time of its acquisition by the subdivision owner are not acceptable.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Title searches.</E> The required evidence of the status of title shall be based on a search of all public records which may contain documents affecting title to the land or the developer's ability to deliver marketable title. The search must cover a period which is required or generally considered adequate for insuring marketability of title in the jurisdiction in which the subdivision is located. Such search shall include an examination of at least the documents listed in paragraphs (d)(1) through (5) of this section. This search may be accomplished through the use of a title insurance company title plant, the information in which is based on current searches of the appropriate and necessary documents, including as a minimum those listed immediately above. For any attorney's title opinion based on Torrens certificates of title, the title search need only go beyond the original time of registration of the certificate of title for those types of encumbrances which were not conclusively settled by the proceedings at the time of such registration. In such cases, the required statement shall clearly reflect the documents and periods searched.</P>
        <P>(1) The records of the recorder of deeds or similar authority;</P>
        <P>(2) U.S. Internal Revenue Liens;</P>
        <P>(3) The records of the circuit, probate, or other courts including Federal courts and bankruptcy or reorganization proceedings which have jurisdiction to affect the title to the land;</P>
        <P>(4) The tax records;</P>
        <P>(5) Financing statements filed pursuant to the Uniform Commercial Code or similar law. If it is held that the financing statements do not affect the title of the land, include a statement of the legal authority for that opinion.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Items to be included in the title evidence.</E> The acceptable title evidence must include the following information, instruments and statements and need not be repeated or duplicated elsewhere in the Statement of Record.</P>

        <P>(1) A legal description of the land on which the lots, common areas, and facilities covered by the title evidence are located. This legal description shall be adequate for conveying land in the jurisdiction in which the subdivision is located. If this legal description is based on a recorded plat, the lot numbers, recording place, book name, book number, and page number shall be stated in the description. If this legal description is given by metes and bounds, the title evidence shall include or be accompanied by a certified statement of the preparer of the title evidence, a licensed attorney, or an engineer or surveyor, indicating that all subject lots, common areas, and common facilities are encompassed within the metes and bounds description in the evidence. If at any time after the submission of the legal description required above, the description of the subject land is changed or found to be in error, a correcting amendment shall be made to the Statement of Record.<PRTPAGE P="297"/>
        </P>
        <P>(2) The name of the person(s) or other legal entity(ies) holding fee title to the property described.</P>
        <P>(3) The name of any person(s) or other legal entity(ies) holding a leasehold estate or other interest of record in the property described.</P>
        <P>(4) A listing of any and all exceptions or objections to the title, estate or interest of the person(s) or legal entity(ies) referred to in paragraph (e)(2) or (3) of this section, including any encumbrances, easements, covenants, conditions, reservations, limitations or restrictions of record. Any reference to exceptions or objections to title shall include specific references to the instruments in the public records upon which they are based. When an objection or exception to title affects less than all of the property covered by this Statement of Record, the title evidence shall specifically note what portion of the property is so affected.</P>
        <P>(5) Copies of all instruments in the public records specifically referred to in paragraph (e)(4) of this section. Abstracts of such instruments are acceptable if prepared by an attorney or professional or official abstractor qualified and authorized by law to prepare and certify such abstracts and if the abstracts contain a material portion of the recorded instruments sufficient to determine the nature and effect of such instruments. Also include copies of any release provisions, relating to encumbrances on the property described, which are not included in the documents otherwise required by this section.</P>
        <P>(6) If an attorney's title opinion has been submitted pursuant to this section which has been based on a Torrens land registration certificate of title, submit a copy of such certificate.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Supplemental title information.</E> (1) If there is a holder of an ownership interest in the land other than the developer, submit a copy of any documentation which evidences the developers' authorization to develop and/or sell the land.</P>
        <P>(2) Submit copies of any trust deeds, deeds in trust, escrow agreements or other instruments which purport to protect the purchaser in the event of default or bankruptcy by the developer on any instrument or instruments which create a blanket encumbrance upon the property unless they have been previously provided as part of “title evidence” submitted pursuant to paragraph (e) of this section.</P>
        <P>(3)(i) Submit copies of all forms of contracts or agreements and notes to be used in selling or leasing lots. The contracts or agreements, including promissory notes, must contain the following language in boldface type (which must be distinguished from the type used for the rest of the contract) on the face or signature page above all signatures: “You have the option to cancel your contract or agreement of sale by notice to the seller until midnight of the seventh day following the signing of the contract or agreement. If you did not receive a Property Report prepared pursuant to the rules and regulations of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, in advance of your signing the contract or agreement, the contract or agreement of sale may be cancelled at your option for two years from the date of signing.”</P>
        <P>(ii) If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of state law or the Act, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract or agreement must reflect the requirements of the longer period, rather than the seven days. This language shall be consistent with that shown on the cover page (see § 1010.105).</P>
        <P>(iii) The revocation provisions may not be limited or qualified in the contract or other document by requiring a specific type of notice or by requiring that notice be given at a specified place.</P>
        <P>(iv) If it is represented that the developer will provide or complete roads or facilities for waters, sewer, gas, electric service or recreational amenities, the contract must contain a provision that the developer is obligated to provide or complete such roads, facilities and amenities (see § 1011.15(f)).</P>
        <P>(4) Submit copies of deeds and leases by which the developer will lease or convey title to the lots to purchasers or lessees.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Plat maps, environmental studies and restrictions</E>—(1) <E T="03">Plat maps.</E> (i) In those jurisdictions where it is unlawful to sell lots prior to final approval and recording of the plat, and in those <PRTPAGE P="298"/>cases where a plat has been recorded, submit a copy of the recorded plat. This plat should be an exact copy of the recorded document. It should reflect the signatures of the approving authorities and bear a stamp or notation by the recorder of deeds, or similarly constituted officer, as to the recording data.</P>
        <P>(ii) If the plat has not been approved by the local authorities nor recorded, and if it is not unlawful to sell lots prior to final approval and recording, submit a map which has been prepared to scale and which shows the proposed division of the land, the lot dimensions and their relation to proposed or existing streets and roads. The map shall contain sufficient engineering data to enable a surveyor to locate the lots.</P>
        <P>(iii) Whether recorded or unrecorded, the plat or map should show:</P>
        <P>(A) The dimensions of each lot, stated in the standard unit of measure acceptable for such purposes in the political subdivision where the land is located.</P>
        <P>(B) A clear delineation of each of the lots and any common areas or facilities.</P>
        <P>(C) Any encroachments or rights-of-way on, over, or under the land, or a notation of these items together with the identity of the lots affected.</P>
        <P>(D) The courses, distances and monuments, natural or otherwise, of the land's boundaries; contiguous boundaries and identification or ownership of adjoining land and names of abutting streets, ways, etc.</P>
        <P>(E) The location of the section or unit encompassing the lots in relationship to the larger tract, or tracts, in the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(F) The delineation of any flood plains or flood control easements affecting any of the lots.</P>
        <P>(iv) The plat, or map shall be prepared by a licensed surveyor or engineer.</P>
        <P>(v) If all lots on each page of the plat are not included in the Statement of Record with which the plat or map is submitted, then the lots which are to be included in the Statement of Record shall be identified on the plat or map; a legend describing the method of identification shall be entered on the face of the plat or map and the number of lots so identified entered in the lower right hand corner of the plat map. The Director must be able to reconcile the totals of these numbers with the information given in §§ 1010.108 and 1010.208 of the Statement of Record and the title evidence.</P>
        <P>(2) <E T="03">Environmental impact study.</E> If the developer is aware of any environmental impact study which considers the effect of the subdivision on the environment, submit a summary of that study.</P>
        <P>(3) <E T="03">Restrictions or covenants.</E> Submit a copy of any recorded or proposed restrictions or covenants for the subdivision if not submitted elsewhere in this Statement of Record. A copy of these restrictions or covenants shall be delivered to a prospective purchaser upon request. A supply shall be maintained at whatever place or places as will be necessary to allow immediate delivery upon request.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.210</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Roads.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) State the estimated cost to the developer of the proposed road system.</P>
        <P>(b) If the developer is to complete any roads providing access to the subdivision, submit copies of any bonds or escrow agreements which have been posted to guarantee completion thereof.</P>
        <P>(c) Submit copies of any bonds or escrow agreements which have been posted to assure completion of the roads within the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(d) If the interior roads are to be maintained by a public authority, submit a copy of a letter from that authority which states that the roads have been, or the conditions upon which they will be, accepted for maintenance and when.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.211</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Utilities.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Water.</E> (1) State the estimated cost to the developer of the central water system.</P>

        <P>(2) If water is to be supplied by a central system, furnish a letter from the supplier that it will supply the water. If the system is operated by a governmental division or by an entity whose operations are regulated by a governmental agency but which is not affiliated with or under the control of the developer, the letter shall include a <PRTPAGE P="299"/>statement that the supply of water will be sufficient to serve the anticipated population of the subdivision or how many homes or connections it can and will serve and that the water is tested at regular intervals and has been found to meet all standards for a public water supply.</P>
        <P>(3) If the water is to be supplied by individual wells, by an entity which is not regulated by a governmental agency, by the developer or by an entity which is affiliated with or controlled by the developer, submit a copy of any engineers' reports or hydrological surveys which indicate there is a sufficient supply of water to serve the anticipated population of the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(4) If the supplier of water is not in one of the categories in paragraph (a)(2) of this section, submit a copy of a letter or report from a cognizant health officer, or from a private laboratory licensed by the state to perform tests and issue reports on water, to the effect that the water was found to meet all drinking water standards required by the state for a public water system.</P>
        <P>(5) If any bond, escrow agreement or other financial assurance of the completion of the central system, including any phases which are to be constructed in the future, has been posted by the developer or an entity not regulated by a government agency, furnish a copy of the document.</P>
        <P>(6) Furnish a copy of any permits which have been obtained by the developer or any entity affiliated with or under the control of the developer in connection with the construction and operation of the central system. If a permit is required to install individual wells, submit a letter from the proper authority which states the requirements for obtaining the permit and that there is no objection to the use of individual wells in the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(7) Furnish a copy of any membership agreement or contract which allows or requires lot owners to use the central water system. If this document is furnished elsewhere in the Statement of Record, reference to it may be made here.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Sewer.</E> (1) State the estimated cost to the developer of the central sewer system.</P>
        <P>(2) If sewage disposal is to be by individual on-site systems, furnish a letter from the local health authorities giving general approval to the use of these systems in the subdivision or giving specific approval for each and every lot.</P>
        <P>(3) If sewage disposal is to be through a central system which is owned and operated by a governmental division, or by an entity whose operations are regulated by a governmental agency but which is not affiliated with, or under the control of, the developer, furnish a letter from the entity that it will provide this service and that its treatment facilities have the capacity to serve the anticipated population of the subdivision or how many homes or connections it can and will serve.</P>
        <P>(4) Furnish a copy of any permits obtained by the developer or any entity affiliated with or under the control of the developer, for the construction and operation of the central sewer system or construction and use of any other method of sewage disposal contemplated for the subdivision except those to be obtained by individual lot owners at a later date.</P>
        <P>(5) If any bond, escrow agreement or other financial assurance of the completion of the central system or other system for which the developer is responsible, and any future expansion, has been posted, furnish a copy of the document.</P>
        <P>(6) Furnish a copy of any membership agreement of contract which allows, or requires, the lot owners to use the central system. If this document is furnished elsewhere in the Statement of Record, it may be included here by reference.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Electricity.</E> Give an estimate of the total construction cost to be expended by the developer and submit any instrument providing financial assurance of completion of the facilities which has been posted by the developer.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Telephone.</E> Give an estimate of the total construction cost to be expended by the developer and submit a copy of any instrument providing financial assurance of the completion of the facilities which has been posted by the developer.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="300"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.212</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Financial information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Financing of improvements.</E> Describe the financing plan that is to be used in financing on-site or off-site improvements proposed in the Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(b) Complete the following format (If the subdivision or common promotional plan contains, or will contain, 1000 or more lots, furnish this information in its entirety. If the subdivision or common promotional plan contains, or will contain, less than 1,000 lots, only paragraphs (b)(3)(iii) and (iv) of this section need be completed.)</P>
        <P>(1) Estimated date for full completion of amenities</P>
        <P>(2) Projected date for complete sell out of subdivision</P>
        <P>(3) Cost and expense recap for lots included in this Statement of Record:</P>
        <P>(i) Land acquisition cost or current fair market value of land.</P>
        <P>(ii) Development and improvement costs (include the estimated cost of such items as roads, utilities, and amenities which the developer will incur).</P>
        <P>(iii) Estimated marketing and advertising costs.</P>
        <P>(iv) Estimated sales commission.</P>
        <P>(v) Interest (include cost in financing the land purchase, improvements, or other borrowings).</P>
        <P>(vi) Estimated other expenses (include general costs, administrative costs, profit, etc.).</P>
        <P>(vii) Total.</P>
        <P>(4) Total land sales revenue:</P>
        <P>(i) Estimated total land sales income.</P>
        <P>(ii) Estimated other income.</P>
        <P>(iii) Total income.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Financial statements.</E> (1) Submit a copy of the developer's financial statements for the last full fiscal year. These statements shall be prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles as prescribed by the Financial Accounting Standards Board and generally accepted auditing standards as prescribed by the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, and shall be audited by an independent licensed public accountant. They shall include a balance sheet, a statement of profit and loss, a statement of changes in financial condition and a certified opinion by the accountant. The statements shall be no more than six months old on the date the Statement of Record is submitted.</P>
        <P>(2) If the audited statements are more than six months old at the date of submission of the Statement of Record, or if the last full fiscal year has ended within the last 90 days and audited Statements are not yet available, the developer may submit a copy of the audited statements for the previous full fiscal year and supplement them with unaudited, interim statements so that the financial information is no more than six months old on the date that the Statement of Record is submitted. The interim statements may be prepared by company personnel but must contain a balance sheet, a statement of profit and loss and a statement of changes in financial condition and be prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Annual report.</E> (1) Each year after the initial effective date, the developer shall submit a copy of its latest financial statements. These statements must meet the standards set out in § 1010.212(c)(1), unless the developer has qualified for an exception under § 1010.212(e), and must be submitted within 120 days after the close of the developer's fiscal year.</P>
        <P>(2) If a developer has submitted its latest statements with a consolidated filing since the close of its fiscal year and prior to the end of the 120 day period, a second submission of the statements to comply with this section is not necessary.</P>
        <P>(3) If the developer no longer has an active sales program on the date this report is due, the information set forth in § 1010.310(c)(7)(iii) may be furnished in lieu of this report.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Exceptions.</E> (1) If the developer does not have audited financial statements and the criteria in one of the following exceptions are met, statements need not be audited and certified but must meet all of the other requirements set forth in paragraphs (c)(1) and (2) of this section.</P>

        <P>(2) The term “conveys title free of any mortgage or lien” in these exceptions is not intended to prohibit the taking of an instrument as security for <PRTPAGE P="301"/>the lot purchase price after title is conveyed. For the purposes of these exceptions, these definitions shall apply:</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Deed</E> shall mean a warranty deed, or its equivalent, which conveys title free and clear of liens and encumbrances.</P>
        <P>(ii) <E T="03">Assurance of Title Agreement</E> shall mean a legal arrangement whereby the purchaser is guaranteed a deed upon payment of no more than the full purchase price of the lot (<E T="03">e.g.</E> subdivision trust). In addition to a copy of any Assurance of Title Agreement, the Director may require additional documentation such as an attorney's opinion letter to assure that the purchaser's title is fully protected.</P>
        <P>(iii) <E T="03">Date of contract</E> shall mean the date on which the contract or agreement is signed by the purchaser.</P>
        <P>(iv) <E T="03">Escrow or trust account as to down payments and deposits</E> shall mean an account, established in accordance with local real estate laws or regulations, which assures the return to the purchaser of any monies paid in the event title is not delivered to the purchaser in accordance with the terms of the contract.</P>
        <P>(3) The exceptions are:</P>
        <P>(i) The aggregate sales price of all lots offered pursuant to a common promotional plan equals $500,000.00 or less; or</P>
        <P>(ii) Each of the following conditions of paragraphs (e)(3)(ii)(A) and (B) of this section are met, plus the conditions of one of paragraphs (e)(3)(ii)(C), (D), or (E) of this section:</P>
        <P>(A) Down payments and deposits are held in an escrow or trust account.</P>
        <P>(B) The contract provides for delivery of a deed which conveys title free of any mortgage or lien within 180 days of the signing of the contract. (In lieu of delivery of a deed, the developer may submit to ILSRP an Assurance of Title Agreement.)</P>
        <P>(C) The aggregate sales prices of all lots offered pursuant to a common promotional plan is at least $500,000 but less than $1,500,000.</P>
        <P>(D) All facilities, utilities and amenities proposed by the developer in the Property Report or sales contract have been completed so that the lots in the Statement of Record are immediately usable for the purpose for which they are sold.</P>
        <P>(E)(<E T="03">1</E>) The developer is contractually obligated to the purchaser to complete all facilities, utilities and amenities proposed by the developer in the Property Report and sales contract so that all lots included in the Statement of Record will be usable for the purpose for which they are sold by the dates set out in the Property Report, and;</P>
        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>) The developer has made financial arrangements, such as the posting of surety bonds (corporate bonds or individual notes or bonds are not acceptable), irrevocable letters of credit or the establishment of escrow or trust accounts, which assure completion of all facilities, utilities and amenities proposed by the developer in the Property Report or contract.</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Newly-formed entity.</E> If the developer is newly formed or has not had any significant operating experience, an audited or unaudited balance sheet and statements of receipts and disbursements of funds may be submitted.</P>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">Use of parent company statements.</E> (1) If the developer is a subsidiary company and does not have audited financial statements, the Director may permit the use of the audited and certified statements of the parent company: <E T="03">Provided,</E> That those statements are accompanied by an unconditional guaranty that the parent shall perform and fulfill the obligations of the subsidiary. If this procedure is adopted, the developer shall submit the following:</P>
        <P>(i) The audited and certified financial statements of the parent company, together with interim statements if necessary, which comply with § 1010.212(c).</P>
        <P>(ii) A properly executed guaranty in a form acceptable to the Director.</P>
        <P>(2) In cases described in paragraph (g)(1) of this section, the disclosure information required in § 1010.112 shall be appropriately amended to reference the parent company and not the developer and must include a statement to the effect that the developer's parent company (insert name) has entered into an unconditional guaranty to perform and fulfill the obligations of the developer.</P>
        <P>(h) <E T="03">Opinions.</E> If the accountant qualifies or disclaims his opinion, the Director may accept the statements and require such additional disclosure as the <PRTPAGE P="302"/>Director deems necessary in the public interest or for the protection of purchasers.</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Copies for prospective purchasers.</E> Copies of the financial statements filed with the Statement of Record shall be made available to prospective purchasers upon request. A supply of the latest submitted statements shall be maintained at whatever place, or places, as is necessary to allow immediate delivery upon request by a prospective purchaser. These statements shall contain financial information only and shall not include any promotional material such as that usually set forth in annual reports.</P>
        <P>(j) <E T="03">Change from audited to unaudited statements.</E> (1) Developers who file audited statements must continue with audited statements throughout the duration of the registration unless, at a later date, the developer submits amendments which demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Director that it then qualifies for an exception from audited statements under paragraph (e)(3)(ii) of this section. For purposes of paragraph (e)(3)(ii)(C) of this section, the Director will consider the aggregate sales prices of only the lots yet to be sold, and may consider whether any additions to the subdivisions or reacquisitions of lots already sold would be likely to cause the dollar limits to be exceeded.</P>
        <P>(i) The aggregate sales prices of the lots yet to be sold in the subdivision has been reduced to less than $1,500,000.00, and that it will not exceed this amount through further additions to the subdivision, or through the reacquisition of lots already sold, and;</P>
        <P>(ii) The sales contract provides for delivery of a deed within 120 days of the date of the contract which conveys title free and clear of any mortgage or lien or the developer files an Assurance of Title Agreement with ILSRP, and;</P>
        <P>(iii) Any down payments or deposits are held in an escrow or trust account, or;</P>
        <P>(iv) The developer then qualifies for exception (e)(3)(iii) or (iv) of this section.</P>
        <P>(2) The Director may allow a developer, who has made sales prior to registration, to submit unaudited statements under the provisions of paragraph (j)(1)(i) of this section. The developer must demonstrate to the satisfaction of the Director that the acceptance of unaudited statements would not be a detriment to the public interest or to the protection of purchasers.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.214</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Recreational facilities.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Submit a synopsis of the proposed plans and estimated cost of any proposed or partially constructed recreational facility disclosed in § 1010.114. This item should include the general dimensions and a brief description of the facility but it should not include blueprints or similar technical materials.</P>
        <P>(b) Submit a copy of any bond or escrow arrangements to assure completion of the recreational facilities disclosed in § 1010.114 which are not structurally complete.</P>
        <P>(c) Submit a copy of the lease for any leased recreational facility.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.215</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Subdivision characteristics and climate.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Submit <E T="03">two</E> copies of a current geological survey topographic map, or maps, of the largest scale available from the U.S. Geological Survey with an outline of the entire subdivision and the area included in this Statement of Record clearly indicated. Photo copies made by the developer are not acceptable. Do not shade the areas on the maps which have been outlined.</P>
        <P>(b) If drainage facilities are proposed but not yet completed, submit a synopsis of the developer's proposed plans that includes a description of the system of collecting surface waters; a description of the steps to be taken to control erosion and sedimentation and the estimated cost of the drainage facilities.</P>
        <P>(c) Submit copies of any bonds, escrow or trust accounts or other financial assurance of completion of the drainage facilities.</P>
        <P>(d) State whether the jurisdiction in which the subdivision is located has a system for rating the land for fire hazards.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.216</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional information.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Property Owners' Association.</E> (1) If the association has been formed as a <PRTPAGE P="303"/>legal entity, submit a copy of the articles of association, bylaws or similar documents, and a copy of the charter or certificate of incorporation.</P>
        <P>(2) If the developer exercises any control over the association, state whether any contracts have been executed between the association and the developer or any affiliate or principal of the developer. If there have been, briefly summarize the terms of the contracts, their purpose, their duration and the method and rate of payment required by the contract. State whether the association may modify or terminate the contracts after the owners assume control of the association.</P>
        <P>(3) State whether there is any agreement which would require the association to reimburse the developer, its affiliates or successors for any attorney's fees or costs arising from an action brought against them by the association or individual property owners regardless of the outcome of the action.</P>
        <P>(4) If the answer to paragraph (a)(2) or (a)(3) of this section is in the affirmative, disclosure may be required in § 1010.116(a) at the discretion of the Director.</P>
        <P>(5) Submit a copy of any membership agreement or similar document.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Price range, type of sales and marketing.</E> (1) State the price range of lots in the subdivision.</P>
        <P>(2) State the type of sales to be made, <E T="03">i.e.,</E> contract for deed, cash, deed with security instrument, etc.</P>
        <P>(3) Describe the methods of advertising and marketing to be used for the subdivision. The description should include, but need not be limited to, information on such matters as to:</P>
        <P>(i) Whether the developer will employ his own sales force or will contract with an outside group;</P>
        <P>(ii) Whether wide area telephone solicitation will be employed;</P>
        <P>(iii) Whether presentations will be made away from the immediate vicinity of the subdivision and/or if prospective purchasers will be furnished transportation from distant cities to the subdivision;</P>
        <P>(iv) Whether mass mailing techniques will be used and gifts offered to those who respond.</P>
        <P>(4) For any subdivision that meets any of the criteria in paragraphs (b)(4)(i) through (iii) of this section, submit a copy of any advertising or promotional material that is, or has been, used for the subdivision. Amendments to reflect changes in advertising or promotional material need be filed only when there is a material change related to one of the above factors. Depending upon the content of the material submitted, the Director may require additional warnings in the Property Report portion. This requirement applies to any subdivision that:</P>
        <P>(i) Mentions or refers to recreational facilities which are not disclosed in § 1010.114, or;</P>
        <P>(ii) Promotes the sale of lots based on the investment potential or expected profits, or;</P>
        <P>(iii) Contains information which is in conflict with that disclosed in this Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Violations and litigation.</E> (1) Submit a copy of the complaint(s), the answer(s) and the decision(s) for any litigation listed in § 1010.116(c).</P>
        <P>(2) If it is indicated in § 1010.116(c) that the developer or any of the parties involved in the subdivision are, or have been, the subject of any bankruptcy proceedings, furnish a copy of the schedules of liabilities and assets (or a recap of those schedules); the petition number; the date of the filing of the petition; names and addresses of the petitioners, trustee and counsel; the name and location of the court where the proceedings took place and the status or disposition of the petition. Explain, briefly, the cause of the action.</P>
        <P>(3) Furnish a copy of any orders issued in connection with any violations listed in § 1010.116(c).</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Resale or exchange program.</E> (1) If it is stated in § 1010.116(d)(3) that there is an exchange program which provides sufficient lots to satisfy all requests for exchange, describe the method used to determine the number of lots required; state whether these lots have been reserved or set aside; whether additional lots will be provided if the lots available for exchange are exhausted and the source of any additional lots.</P>
        <P>(2) [Reserved]</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Unusual situations</E>—(1) <E T="03">Foreign subdivisions.</E> If the subdivision is located outside the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of <PRTPAGE P="304"/>Puerto Rico or the territories or possession of the United States, the Statement of Record shall be submitted in the English language and all supporting documents, including copies of any laws which restrict the ownership of land by aliens, shall be submitted in their original language and shall be accompanied by a translation into English.</P>
        <P>(2) [Reserved]</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.219</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Affirmation.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The affirmation set forth in section XXVIII of the appendix to this part: Affirmation of Senior Executive Officer shall be executed by the senior executive officer or a duly authorized agent:</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.310</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Annual report of activity.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) As an integral part of the Statement of Record, the developer shall file with the Director an Annual Report of Activity on any initial or consolidated registration not under suspension. For this purpose, only one Annual Report of Activity will be expected for subdivisions on which developers have filed consolidations. For registrations certified by a state as provided for in § 1010.500, a developer need file only one Annual Report of Activity for any registration for which the ILSRP number is the same (alphabetic designators indicate that the registration has been treated as a consolidation).</P>
        <P>(b) The report shall be submitted within 30 days of the annual anniversary of the effective date of the initial Statement of Record.</P>
        <P>(c) The report shall contain the following information:</P>
        <P>(1) Subdivision name and address.</P>
        <P>(2) Developer's name, address and telephone number.</P>
        <P>(3) Agent's name, address and telephone number.</P>
        <P>(4) Interstate Land Sales Registration number.</P>
        <P>(5) The date on which the initial filing first became effective.</P>
        <P>(6) The number of registered lots, parcels or units which are unsold as of the date on which the report is due.</P>
        <P>(7) One of the following:</P>
        <P>(i) A statement that the developer is still engaged in land sales activity at the subject subdivision and that there have been no changes in material fact since the last effective date was issued which would require an amendment to the Statement of Record; or</P>
        <P>(ii) A statement that the developer is still engaged in land sales activity at the subject subdivision, that material changes have occurred since the last effective date, and that corrected pages to the Property Report portion or Additional Information and Documentation portion of the Statement accompany the report; or</P>

        <P>(iii) A statement that the developer is no longer engaged in land sales activity at the subject subdivision, together with the reason the developer is no longer selling (<E T="03">e.g.,</E> all lots sold to the public or the remaining lots sold to another developer, along with the date of sale and the new developer's name, address and telephone number). A request may be made that the Statement of Record be voluntarily suspended. The request should be submitted in duplicate and will become effective upon the counter-signature of the Director (or an authorized Designee) with the duplicate being returned to the developer.</P>
        <P>(8) The report shall be dated and shall be signed by the senior executive officer of the developer on a signature line above his typed name and title. The senior executive officer's acknowledgement shall be attested to or certified by a notary public or similar public official authorized to attest or certify acknowledgements in the jurisdiction in which the report is executed.</P>
        <P>(d) If the report indicates that there are 101 or more registered lots, parcels or units remaining for sale, the report shall be accompanied by an amendment fee in the amount and form prescribed in § 1010.35.</P>
        <P>(e) Failure to submit the report when due shall be grounds for an action to suspend the effective Statement of Record.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Certification of Substantially Equivalent State Law</HD>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.500</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) This subpart establishes procedures and criteria for certifying state land sale or lease disclosure programs and State state land development standards programs. The purpose of <PRTPAGE P="305"/>State Certification is to lessen the administrative burden on the individual developer, arising where there are duplicative state and federal Federal registration and disclosure requirements, without affecting the level of protection given to the individual purchaser or lessee. If the Director determines that a state has adopted and is effectively administering a program that gives purchasers and lessees the same level of protection given to them by the Interstate Land Sales Registration Program, then the Director shall certify that state. Developers who accomplish an effective registration with a state in which the land is located after the Director has certified the state may satisfy the registration requirements of the Director by filing with the Director materials designated by agreement with certified states in lieu of the federal Federal Statement of Record and Property Report.</P>
        <P>(b) A state that is certified by the Director shall be known as the situs certified state for all land located within its borders.</P>
        <P>(c) After a developer is effectively registered with the Director through a certified state, the Director has the same authority over that developer as the Director has over developers who file directly with the Director. This includes the authority to subpoena information and to examine, evaluate and suspend a developer's registration under sections 1407(d) and (e) of the Act and § 1010.45(b)(1) and (b)(2) of these regulations.</P>
        <P>(d) The prohibitions against the use of the Property Report contained in § 1010.29 apply to state disclosure materials and substantive development standards. In addition, for purposes of this paragraph, references made to the Director, ILSRP and the Bureau in § 1010.29 will include a reference to the equivalent state officer or agency.</P>
        <P>(e) The Purchaser's Revocation Rights, Sales Practices and Standards rules contained in part 1011 of these regulations apply to developers who register with the Director through certified States. All of the rules in part 1011 apply, excepting the disclaimer statement in § 1011.50(a) which is modified to read as follows: “Obtain the Property Report or its equivalent, required by Federal and State law and read it before signing anything. No Federal or State agency has judged the merits or value, if any, of this property.”</P>
        <P>(f) Developers are obliged to pay filing fees as set forth in § 1010.35 of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.503</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Notice of certification.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) If the Director determines that a state qualifies for certification under § 1010.501(a) or (b), the Director shall so notify the state in writing. The state will be effectively certified under the section and as of the date specified in the notice.</P>
        <P>(b) If the Director determines that a state does not meet the standards for certification, the Director shall so notify the state in writing. The notice will specify particular changes in state law, regulations or administration that are needed to obtain certification. The Director shall not be bound in advance to certify a state that makes the suggested changes if other deficiencies become apparent at a later time.</P>

        <P>(c) The Director's final determination to accept or reject a State's Application for Certification of Land Sales Program shall be published in the <E T="04">Federal Register.</E>
        </P>
        <P>(d) A state's certification will remain in effect until it is voluntarily suspended by the state or withdrawn by the Director. A state can voluntarily suspend its certification by notifying the Director in writing. The suspension will take effect as of the date and time specified in the notice to the Director, or upon receipt by the Director if no date is specified. The Director may withdraw certification as provided in § 1010.505.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.504</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cooperation among certified states and between certified states and the Director.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) By filing an Application for Certification of State Land Sales Program pursuant to § 1010.502, a state agrees that, if it is certified by the Director, it will:</P>

        <P>(1) Accept for filing and allow to be distributed as the sole disclosure document, a disclosure document currently in effect in the situs certified state. Only those documents filed with the <PRTPAGE P="306"/>situs state after certification by the Director must automatically be accepted by other certified states;</P>
        <P>(2) Certify copies of all disclosure documents, amendments and consolidations filed with it by developers of land located within its borders for and as needed by developers required to submit certified copies to the Director and all other certified states. The certification shall indicate whether the documents are currently in effect. The certification should be in the format set forth in section XXIX of the appendix to this part: Form for Certification for Disclosure Documents.</P>
        <P>(3) Assist and cooperate with the Director and other certified states by requiring that developers of land within its borders amend disclosure documents if any change occurs in any representation of material fact required to be stated in the disclosure documents, including a change resulting from the developer's compliance with the requirements of the law in another certified state. The state shall require developers to send certified copies of the amended documents to the Director and requesting certified states. All amendments to such materials, which reflect changes in material facts regarding the subdivision, shall be submitted to the situs certified state authorities within 15 days of the date on which the developer knows, or should have known, of such change. Certified copies of the disclosure documents shall be submitted by the developer to the Director and the other certified states within 15 days after it becomes effective under the situs certified state laws.</P>
        <P>(4) Continue to effectively operate its Land Sales Program as that Program is described in the Application for Certification and as it was certified by the Director.</P>
        <P>(5) Assist and cooperate with the Director by monitoring the sales practices of developers registered with it directly or through another certified state, and by reporting to the Director any violations of the Act, including but not limited to the required contract provisions, revocation rights and anti-fraud provisions of 15 U.S.C. 1703, or the regulations.</P>
        <P>(b) A state required to accept the disclosure documents of another situs certified state pursuant to paragraph (a)(1) of this section, may, in its discretion, require the developer to furnish it with copies certified pursuant to paragraph (a)(2) of this section.</P>
        <P>(c) No state shall be prevented from establishing substantive or disclosure requirements which exceed the federal Federal standard provided that such requirements are not in conflict with the Act or these regulations. For example, a certified state may impose additional disclosure requirements on developers of land located within its borders but may not impose additional disclosure requirements on developers whose disclosure documents it is required to accept pursuant to paragraph (a)(1) of this section. However, a certified state may impose additional nondisclosure requirements on out of state developers even though the developer is registered in the certified state in which the land is located.</P>
        <P>(d) After a developer is effectively registered with a certified state through a situs certified state, either or both certified states may exercise full enforcement authorities and powers over that developer according to applicable law and regulations.</P>
        <P>(e) The Director shall cooperate with the certified states by offering a forum for nonbinding arbitration of disputes between two or more certified States arising out of the State Certification Program.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.505</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Withdrawal of state certification.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The Director shall periodically review the laws, regulations and administration thereof, of a certified state. If the Director finds that, taken as a whole, the laws, regulations or administration thereof, no longer meet the requirements of subpart C, then the Director may issue a notice to withdraw the certification of that state.</P>

        <P>(b) The notice of proceedings to withdraw a state's certification will be issued to the state by the Director pursuant to § 1012.236. The Director may, after notice and after an opportunity for a hearing, pursuant to § 1012.237, issue an order withdrawing certification. In the event that a withdrawal <PRTPAGE P="307"/>order is issued, the order shall remain in effect until the state has amended its laws, regulations or the administration thereof or has otherwise complied with the requirements of the order. When the state has complied with the requirements of the order, the Director shall so declare and the withdrawal order shall cease to be effective.</P>

        <P>(c) Withdrawal orders issued pursuant to this subsection will be effective as of the date the order is received by the state. The withdrawal order shall be published in the <E T="04">Federal Register.</E>
        </P>
        <P>(d) The rules of 12 CFR part 1080, unless otherwise specified in 12 CFR part 1012, subpart D, will generally apply to hearings on withdrawal of a state's certification.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.506</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>State/Federal filing requirements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) If the Director has certified a state under § 1010.501, the Director shall accept for filing disclosure materials or other acceptable documents which have been approved by the certified state within which the subdivision is located. Only those filings made by the developer with the state after the state was certified by the Director shall be automatically accepted by the Director.</P>
        <P>(2) Retroactive application of the effectiveness of state's certification to a specified date may be granted on a state-by-state basis, where the Director determines that retroactive application will not result in automatic federal Federal registration of any state filing that has not met the requirements of the certified state laws.</P>
        <P>(b) For a developer to be registered with the Director, the developer shall file with the Director a state certified copy of the Property Report or its equivalent, and any other documentation as stipulated in the Director's Notice of Certification to the state.</P>
        <P>(c) The documents and materials filed under paragraph (b) of this section will be automatically effective as the Federal Statement of Record and Property Report after these materials and the proper filing fee have been received by the Director.</P>
        <P>(d) The Director has authority pursuant to § 1010.45(b)(1) and (b)(2) to suspend individual filings which fail to meet the requirements of the certified state's law or regulations or the standards in the certification agreement whether or not the state agency has initiated a similar action.</P>
        <P>(e)(1) State accepted materials filed with the Director pursuant to this section must be amended to reflect any amendment to such materials made effective by the state. All amendments to such materials must be submitted to the Director within 15 days after becoming effective under the applicable state laws. Amendments are automatically effective upon their receipt by the Director and the provisions of § 1010.45(b)(1) and (2) apply to amendments filed under this section.</P>
        <P>(2) Amendments shall include or be accompanied by:</P>
        <P>(i) A letter from the developer giving a narrative statement fully explaining the purpose and significance of the amendment and referring to that section and page of the material which is being amended, and;</P>
        <P>(ii) A signed state acceptance certification substantially the same as that required by § 1010.504(a)(2).</P>
        <P>(f) If a certified state suspends the registration of a particular subdivision for any reason, the subdivision's federal Federal registration with the Director shall be automatically suspended as a result of the state action. No action need be taken by the Director to effect the suspension.</P>
        <P>(g) A state is certified only with regard to land located within the state borders. The Director is not required to accept filings which have been accepted by a certified state if the land which is the subject of the filing is not located within that certified state. For example, if State A is certified by the Director and State B is not, the Director is not required to accept filings from State B simply because State A accepts filings from State B.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.507</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effect of suspension or withdrawal of certification granted under § 1010.501(a): Full disclosure requirement.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) If a state certified under § 1010.501(a) suspends its own certification or has its certification withdrawn under § 1010.505, the Federal disclosure materials accepted and made <PRTPAGE P="308"/>effective by the Director, pursuant to § 1010.506, prior to the suspension or withdrawal shall remain in effect unless otherwise suspended by the Director.</P>
        <P>(b) In the event that there is a change in a material fact with regard to a subdivision that remains registered under the provisions of paragraph (a) of this section, the developer shall file a new registration with the Director meeting the requirements of the then applicable Federal registration regulations. Modifications of the Federal format may be used as specified by the Director.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.508</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Effect of suspension of certification granted under § 1010.501(b): Sufficient protection requirement.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) If a state certified under § 1010.501(b) suspends its own certification or has its certification withdrawn under § 1010.505, the effectiveness of the Federal disclosure materials accepted and made effective by the Director, pursuant to § 1010.506, prior to the suspension or withdrawal shall terminate ninety (90) days after the notice of withdrawal order is published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> as provided in § 1010.505(c).</P>
        <P>(b) At the end of the ninety day period, or during the ninety day period in the event that there is a change in material fact with regard to a subdivision that remains registered under the provisions of paragraph (a) of this section, the developer shall file a new registration with the Director meeting the requirements of the then applicable Federal registration regulations. Modifications of the Federal format may be used as specified by the Director.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.552</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) Materials filed with a state and accepted by the HUD Secretary as a Statement of Record prior to January 1, 1981, pursuant to 24 CFR 1010.52 through 1010.59 (as published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> on April 10, 1979) may continue in effect. However, developers must comply with the applicable amendments to the Federal Act and the regulations thereunder. In particular, see §§ 1010.558 and 1010.559, which require that the Property Report and contracts or agreements contain notice of purchaser's revocation rights. In addition see § 1011.15(f), which provides that it is unlawful to make any representations with regard to the developer's obligation to provide or complete roads, water, sewers, gas, electrical facilities or recreational amenities, unless the developer is obligated to do so in the contract.</P>
        <P>(b) If any such filing becomes inactive or suspended under the laws of the state, the registration with the Director shall be ineffective from that time.</P>
        <P>(c) Such Statement of Record may be suspended pursuant to § 1010.45.</P>
        <P>(d) The Director may refuse to accept any particular filing under this section when it is determined that acceptance is not in the public interest.</P>
        <P>(e) The Director may require such changes, additional information, documents or certification as the Director determines to be reasonably necessary or appropriate in the public interest.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.556</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—amendments and consolidations.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Amendments</E>—(1) <E T="03">General requirements.</E> State accepted materials, filed with the Director pursuant to § 1010.552, shall be amended to reflect any amendment to such materials made effective by the state or any change of a material fact regarding the subdivision. All amendments to such materials, which reflect changes in material facts regarding the subdivision, shall be submitted to the state authorities within 15 days of the date on which the developer knows, or should have known, of such change and to the Director within 15 days after it becomes effective under the applicable State laws. However, such amendment shall not be effective as a Federal registration until the Director has determined that the amendment meets all applicable requirements of these regulations.</P>
        <P>(2) Amendments shall include or be accompanied by:</P>

        <P>(i) A letter from the developer giving a narrative statement fully explaining the purpose and significance of the amendment and referring to that section and page of the Statement of Record which is being amended, and;<PRTPAGE P="309"/>
        </P>
        <P>(ii) All amended pages of the state accepted materials filed with the Director. These pages shall be copied together with their amendments. Each such page shall have its date of preparation in the lower right hand corner, and;</P>
        <P>(iii) A signed state acceptance certification, and;</P>
        <P>(iv) The appropriate fees as indicated in § 1010.35.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Consolidations</E>—(1) <E T="03">When consolidations allowed.</E> If lots are to be registered pursuant to § 1010.552 which are in the same common promotional plan with other lots already registered with the Director, then new consolidated state accepted materials including such lots may be filed with the Director as a Statement of Record following the format of the previously accepted filing.</P>
        <P>(2) Consolidated Statements of Record shall include or be accompanied by:</P>
        <P>(i) State accepted consolidation materials which are also acceptable to the Director as a Statement of Record (state property report inclusive). These state accepted consolidation materials shall cover all lots previously registered in the common promotional plan except those deleted pursuant to other provisions in these regulations. These materials shall also include information and items required for state accepted materials filed as an initial registration Statement of Record, except that, supporting documentation in materials previously made effective by the Director for other lots in the subject common promotional plan may be included incorporated by reference into the new consolidation materials submitted as a Statement of Record. However, such documentation may be incorporated by reference included only if it is applicable to the new consolidated lots as well as to the previously registered lots.</P>
        <P>(ii) A signed state acceptance certification.</P>
        <P>(iii) The appropriate fees as indicated in § 1010.35.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Effective date; state filing.</E> The effective dates of state materials filed as amendments and consolidated Statements of Record shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of § 1010.21.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.558</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—notice of revocation rights on property report cover page.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) The cover page on Property Reports for filings made with the Director pursuant to § 1010.552 shall be prepared in accordance with § 1010.105 and shall include the paragraphs set forth in section XXX of the appendix to this part: Language to be Included on Property Report Cover Page.</P>
        <P>(2) If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of State law, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the cover page must reflect the longer period, rather than the seven days.</P>
        <P>(b)(1) If a deed is not delivered within 180 days of the signing of the contract or agreement of sale or unless certain provisions are included in the contract or agreement, the purchaser is entitled to cancel the contract within two years from the date of signing the contract or agreement.</P>
        <P>(2) The deed must be a warranty deed, or where such a deed is not commonly used, a similar deed legally acceptable in the jurisdiction where the lot is located. The deed must be free and clear of liens and encumbrances.</P>
        <P>(3) The contract provisions are:</P>
        <P>(i) A legally sufficient and recordable lot description, and;</P>
        <P>(ii) A provision that the seller will give the purchaser written notification of purchaser's default or breach of contract and the opportunity to remedy the default or breach within 20 days of the notice; and</P>
        <P>(iii) A provision that, if the purchaser loses rights and interest in the lot because of the purchaser's default or breach of contract after 15 percent of the purchase price, exclusive of interest, has been paid, the seller shall refund to the purchaser any amount which remains from the payments made after subtracting 15 percent of the purchase price, exclusive of interest, or the amount of the seller's actual damages, whichever is the greater.</P>

        <P>(4) If a deed is not delivered within 180 days of the signing of the contract or if the necessary provisions are not included in the contract, the following statement shall be used in place of any other rescission language: “Under Federal law you may cancel your contract <PRTPAGE P="310"/>or agreement of sale any time within two years from the date of signing.”</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 1010.559</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Previously accepted state filings—notice of revocation rights in contracts and agreements.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a)(1) All contracts or agreements, including promissory notes used in sale of lots for filings made with the Director pursuant to § 1010.552, must contain the language set forth in section XXXI of the appendix to this part: Notice of Revocation Rights in boldface type (which must be distinguished from the type used for the rest of the contract) on the face or signature page above all signatures:</P>
        <P>(2) If the purchaser is entitled to a longer revocation period by operation of State law or the Act, that period becomes the Federal revocation period and the contract or agreement must reflect the longer period, rather than the seven days. The language shall be consistent with that shown on the Cover Page (see § 1010.558).</P>
        <P>(b) The above revocation provisions may not be limited or qualified in the contract or other document by requiring a specific type of notice or by requiring that notice be given at a specified place.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <APPENDIX>
        <EAR>Pt. 1010, App. A</EAR>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Appendix A to Part 1010—Standard and Model Forms and Clauses</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">I. <E T="03">Forms for Developer's Affirmation for Land Sale—</E>§ 1010.13(a)(9)</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Developer's Name</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Developer's Address</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Purchaser's Name(s)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Purchaser's Address(es) (including county)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Legal Description of Lot(s) Purchased</FP>

        <P>I hereby affirm that all of the requirements of the MSA exemption as set forth in 15 U.S.C. 1702(b)(8) and 12 CFR 1010.13 have been met in the sale or lease of the lot(s) described above.</P>

        <P>I also affirm that I submit to the jurisdiction of the Interstate Land Sales Full Disclosure Act with regard to the sale or lease cited above.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">(Date)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">(Signature of Developer or Authorized Agent)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">(Title)</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">II. <E T="03">Language Notifying Buyer of Option to Cancel Contract—</E>§ 1010.15(b)(5)(i)</HD>
        <P>You have the option to cancel your contract or agreement of sale by notice to the seller until midnight of the seventh day following the date of signing of the contract or agreement.</P>
        <P>If you did not receive a Lot Information Statement prepared pursuant to the rules and regulations of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection in advance of your signing the contract or agreement, the contract or agreement of sale may be cancelled at your option for two years from the date of signing.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">III. <E T="03">Sample Lot Information Statement and Sample Receipt—</E>§ 1010.15(b)(11)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Sample Format</HD>
        <P>(Use of the following headings and first paragraph are mandatory.)</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Lot Information Statement</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Important: Read Carefully Before Signing Anything</HD>
        <P>The developer has obtained a regulatory exemption from registration under the Interstate Land Sales Full Disclosure Act. One requirement of that exemption is that you must receive this Statement prior to the time you sign an agreement (contract) to purchase a lot.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Right To Cancel</HD>
        <P>(Under this heading the developer is to state the specific rescission rights provided for in the contract pursuant to 1010.15(b)(5)(i)).</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Risk of Buying Land</HD>
        <P>(Under this heading the developer is to list the following information:)</P>
        <P>There are certain risks in purchasing real estate that you should be aware of. The following are some of those risks:</P>
        <P>The future value of land is uncertain and dependent upon many factors. Do not expect all land to automatically increase in value.</P>
        <P>Any value which your lot may have will be affected if roads, utilities and/or amenities cannot be completed or maintained.</P>
        <P>Any development will likely have some impact on the surrounding environment. Development which adversely affects the environment may cause governmental agencies to impose restriction on the use of the land.</P>
        <P>In the purchase of real estate, many technical requirements must be met to assure that you receive proper title and that you will be able to use the land for its intended purpose. Since this purchase involves a major expenditure of money, it is recommended that you seek professional advice before you obligate yourself.</P>

        <P>If adequate provisions have not been made for maintenance of the roads or if the land is not served by publicly maintained roads, you <PRTPAGE P="311"/>may have to maintain the roads at your expense.</P>
        <P>If the land is not served by a central sewage system and/or water system, you should contact the local authorities to determine whether a permit will be given for an on-site sewage disposal system and/or well and whether there is an adequate supply of water. You should also become familiar with the requirements for, and the cost of, obtaining electrical service to the lot.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Developer Information</HD>

        <P>(Under this heading the developer is to list the following information:)
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Developer's Name:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Telephone Number:</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Lot Information</HD>


        <P>(Under this heading the developer is to list the following information:)
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Lot Location:</FP>

        <P>(Enter a statement disclosing all liens, reservations, taxes, assessments, easements and restrictions applicable to the lot. A copy of the restrictions may be attached in lieu of recitation.)</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Suppliers of Utilities and Issuers of Permits</HD>
        <P>(Under this heading the developer is to list the name, address and phone number of the appropriate governmental agency or agencies, if any, that will provide information on permits or other requirements for water, sewer and electrical installations. The information will also contain the name, address and telephone number of the suppliers of such utilities which can provide information to the purchaser on costs and availability of such services. A chart similar to the one below may be used to supply this information).</P>
        <P>Listed below are contact points for determining permit requirements, if any, and to obtain information on approximate costs and availability for the listed services:</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xl30,12,12" COLS="3" OPTS="L2,tp0,i1">
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1"/>
            <CHED H="1">Name, address and telephone number of</CHED>
            <CHED H="2">Governmental agency</CHED>
            <CHED H="2">Supplier</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Water</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Sewer</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Electricity</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <P>If misrepresentations are made in the sale of this lot to you, you may have rights under the Interstate Land Sales Full Disclosure Act. If you have evidence of any scheme, artifice or device used to defraud you, you may wish to contact: Office of Nonbank Supervision, Interstate Land Sales Registration Program, Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, 1700 G Street NW., Washington, DC 20006.</P>
        <P>(The Receipt is to be in the following form:)</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Sample Receipt for Lot Information Statement</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Purchaser (print or type):</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature of purchaser:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Street Address:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">City:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">State:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Zip:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of salesperson (print or type):</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature of salesperson:</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">IV. <E T="03">Request for Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption—</E>§ 1010.15(c)(1)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Request for Multiple Site Subdivision Exemption</HD>
        <P>Developer:
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Telephone No.:</FP>

        <P>Agent:
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Telephone No.:</FP>


        <P>(Insert a general description of the developer's method of operation.)</P>
        <P>I affirm that I am, or will be, the developer of the property and/or method of operation described above.</P>
        <P>I affirm that the lots in said property will be sold in compliance with all of the requirements of 12 CFR 1010.15.</P>

        <P>I further affirm that the statements contained in all documents submitted with this request for an Exemption Order are true and complete.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature:</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Title:</FP>


        <P>WARNING: 18 U.S.C. 1001 provides, among other things, that whoever knowingly and willingly makes or uses a document or writing containing any false, fictitious, or fraudulent statement or entry, in any matter within the jurisdiction of any department or agency of the United States, shall be fined not more than $10,000 or imprisoned for not more than 5 years or both.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">V. <E T="03">Request for Regulatory Exemption Order—</E>§ 1010.16(c)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">REQUEST FOR EXEMPTION ORDER</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Location (including county)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Developer</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Authorized Agent or President of Developer<PRTPAGE P="312"/>
        </FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Number of Lots Subject to Exemption Request</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Description of Lots (list lot and block number or other identifying designation)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>

        <P>I affirm that I am the developer or owner of the property described above or will be the developer or owner at the time the lots are offered for sale to the public, or that I am the agent authorized by the developer or owner to complete this statement.</P>

        <P>I further affirm that the statements contained in all documents submitted with the request for an exemption order are true and complete.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Date)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>

        <FP>(Signature of Developer, Owner or Authorized Agent)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Title)</FP>

        <P>WARNING: Section 15 U.S.C. 1717 provides: “Any person who willfully violates any of the provisions of this title or of the rules and regulations or any person who willfully, in a Statement of Record filed under, or in a Property Report issued pursuant to this title, makes any untrue statement of a material fact shall upon conviction be fined not more than $10,000.00 or imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">VI. <E T="03">Developer's Affirmation for Advisory Opinion—</E>§ 1010.17(b)(3)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">Developer's Affirmation</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Location (Including County and State)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Developer</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address of Developer</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Agent</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Address of Agent</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Number of Lots in Subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Number of Acres in Subdivision</FP>


        <P>I affirm that I am the developer or owner of the property described above or will be the developer or owner at the time the lots are offered for sale to the public, or that I am the agent authorized by the developer or owner to complete this statement.</P>

        <P>I further affirm that the statements contained in all documents submitted with the request for an Advisory Opinion are true and complete.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Date)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Signature)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Title);</FP>

        <P>WARNING: 15 U.S.C. 1717 provides: “Any person who willfully violates any of the provisions of this title or of the rules and regulations or any person who willfully, in a Statement of Record filed under, or in a Property Report issued pursuant to this title, makes any untrue statement of a material fact shall upon conviction be fined not more than $10,000.00 or imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">VII. <E T="03">Initial and Consolidated Registration Fee Schedule—</E>§ 1010.35(b)</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s30,8" COLS="2" OPTS="L2,tp0,i1">
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">Number of lots</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Fees</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">200 or fewer lots</ENT>
            <ENT>$800</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">201 or more lots</ENT>
            <ENT>1,000</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">VIII. <E T="03">Property Report for Statement of Record—</E>§ 1010.100(b)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Property Report</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD4">Heading and Section Number</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s30,8" COLS="2" OPTS="L0,tp0,p0,8/9,g1,t1,i1">
          <ROW EXPSTB="00">
            <ENT I="01">Cover Sheet </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.105</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Table of Contents </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.106</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Risks of Buying Land, Warnings </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.107</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">General Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.108</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Title and Land Use </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.109
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(a) General Instructions</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(b) Method of Sale</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(c) Encumbrances, Mortgages and Liens</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(d) Recording the Contract and Deed</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(e) Payments</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(f) Restrictions</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(g) Plats, Zoning, Surveying, Permits, Environment
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Roads </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.110</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Utilities </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.111
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(a) Water</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(b) Sewer</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(c) Electricity</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(d) Telephone</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(e) Fuel or other Energy Source</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Financial Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.112</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Local Services </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.113</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Recreational Facilities </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.114</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Subdivision Characteristics and Climate </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.115
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(a) General Topography</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(b) Water Coverage</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(c) Drainage and Fill</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(d) Flood Plain</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(e) Flooding and Soil Erosion</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(f) Nuisances</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(g) Hazards</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(h) Climate</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(i) Occupancy</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <PRTPAGE P="313"/>
            <ENT I="01">Additional Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.116
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(a) Property Owners' Association</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(b) Taxes</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(c) Violations and Litigation</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(d) Resale or Exchange Program</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(e) Unusual Situations</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">1. Leases</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">2. Foreign Subdivision</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">3. Time Sharing</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">4. Membership</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(f) Equal Opportunity in Lot Sales</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02" O="xl">(g) Listing of lots
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Cost Sheet </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.117</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Receipt, Agent Certification and Cancellation Page </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.118
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="01">
            <ENT I="21">ADDITIONAL INFORMATION AND DOCUMENTATION
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="00">
            <ENT I="01">General Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.208</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Title and Land Use </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.209</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Roads </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.210</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Utilities </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.211</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Financial Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.212</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Recreational Facilities </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.214</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Subdivision Characteristics </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.215</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Additional Information </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.216</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Affirmation </ENT>
            <ENT>1010.219
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="01">
            <ENT I="22">The Bureau's OMB control number for this information collection is: 3170-0012.</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">IX. <E T="03">Sample Page for Statement of Record</E>—1010.102(e)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">SAMPLE PAGE</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">ROADS</HD>
        <P>Here we discuss the roads that lead to the subdivision, those within the subdivision and the location of nearby communities.</P>
        <P>ACCESS TO THE SUBDIVISION.</P>
        <P>County road #43 leads to the subdivision. It has two lanes and the width of the wearing surface is 22 feet. It's paved with a macadam surface.</P>
        <P>This road is maintained by Bottineau County with County funds. No improvements are planned at this time.</P>
        <P>ACCESS WITHIN THE SUBDIVISION.</P>
        <P>The roads within the subdivision will be located on rights of way dedicated to the public.</P>
        <P>We are responsible for constructing the interior roads. There will be no additional cost to you for this construction.</P>
        <P>WE HAVE NOT SET ASIDE ANY FUNDS IN AN ESCROW OR TRUST ACCOUNT OR MADE ANY OTHER FINANCIAL ARRANGEMENTS TO ASSURE COMPLETION OF THE ROADS, SO THERE IS NO ASSURANCE WE WILL BE ABLE TO COMPLETE THE ROADS.</P>
        <P>At present, the roads are under construction and do not provide access to the lots in Units 2 and 3 during wet weather. The succeeding chart describes their present condition and estimated completion dates.</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xs50,r50,12,r50,xs50,xs50" COLS="6" OPTS="L2,tp0,i1">
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">UUnit</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated starting date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Percentage of construction now complete</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated completion date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Present <LI>surface</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Final surface</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">1</ENT>
            <ENT>February 2010</ENT>
            <ENT>50</ENT>
            <ENT>December 2010</ENT>
            <ENT>Gravel</ENT>
            <ENT>Asphalt.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">2</ENT>
            <ENT>August 2010</ENT>
            <ENT>0</ENT>
            <ENT>June 2011</ENT>
            <ENT>Dirt</ENT>
            <ENT>Do.</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">3</ENT>
            <ENT>April 2011</ENT>
            <ENT>0</ENT>
            <ENT>October 2011</ENT>
            <ENT>None</ENT>
            <ENT>Do.</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">X. <E T="03">Language for Warning on Cover Page of Property Report</E>—§ 1010.105(c)</HD>

        <P>This Report is prepared and issued by the developer of this subdivision. It is <E T="03">not</E> prepared or issued by the Federal Government.</P>
        <P>Federal law requires that you receive this Report prior to your signing a contract or agreement to buy or lease a lot in this subdivision. However, NO FEDERAL AGENCY HAS JUDGED THE MERITS OR VALUE, IF ANY, OF THIS PROPERTY.</P>
        <P>If you received this Report prior to signing a contract or agreement, you may cancel your contract or agreement by giving notice to the seller any time before midnight of the seventh day following the signing of the contract or agreement.</P>

        <P>If you did not receive this Report before you signed a contract or agreement, you may cancel the contract or agreement any time within two years from the date of signing.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of Developer</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date of This Report</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XI. <E T="03">Sample Entry in Table of Contents for Statement of Record</E>—§ 1010.106(a)</HD>
        <P>Title and Land Use # Page #</P>
        <P>Method of Sale</P>
        <P>Encumbrances, Mortgages and Liens</P>
        <P>Recording the Contract and Deed</P>
        <P>Payments</P>
        <P>Restrictions on the Use of Your Lot<PRTPAGE P="314"/>
        </P>
        <P>Plat Maps, Zoning, Surveying, Permits and Environment</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XII. <E T="03">Required Language for Risks of Buying Land</E>—§ 1010.107(a)</HD>
        <P>(1) The future value of any land is uncertain and dependent upon many factors. DO NOT expect all land to increase in value.</P>
        <P>(2) Any value which your lot may have will be affected if the roads, utilities and all proposed improvements are not completed. This paragraph may be omitted if all improvements have been completed or if no improvements are proposed.</P>
        <P>(3) Resale of your lot may be difficult or impossible, since you may face the competition of our own sales program and local real estate brokers may not be interested in listing your lot.</P>
        <P>(4) Any subdivision will have an impact on the surrounding environment. Whether or not the impact is adverse and the degree of impact, will depend on the location, size, planning and extent of development. Subdivisions which adversely affect the environment may cause governmental agencies to impose restrictions on the use of the land. Changes in plant and animal life, air and water quality and noise levels may affect your use and enjoyment of your lot and your ability to sell it.</P>
        <P>(5) In the purchase of real estate, many technical requirements must be met to assure that you receive proper title. Since this purchase involves a major expenditure of money, it is recommended that you seek professional advice before you obligate yourself.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XIII. <E T="03">Format for General Information</E>—§ 1010.108</HD>
        <P>“This Report covers __ lots located in ______ County, (<E T="03">State</E> ). See Page __ for a listing of these lots. It is estimated that this subdivision will eventually contain __ lots.”</P>
        <P>“The developer of this subdivision is:</P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Developer's Name)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Developer's Address)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Developer's telephone number)</FP>

        <P>“Answers to questions and information about this subdivision may be obtained by telephoning the developer at the number listed above.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XIV. <E T="03">Paragraphs to be included in the General Report—Title to the Property and Land Use</E>—§ 1010.109(a)(1)</HD>
        <P>“A person with legal title to property generally has the right to own, use and enjoy the property. A contract to buy a lot may give you possession but doesn't give you legal title. You won't have legal title until you receive a valid deed. A restriction or an encumbrance on your lot, or on the subdivision, could adversely affect your title.”</P>
        <P>“Here we will discuss the sales contract you will sign and the deed you will receive. We will also provide you with information about any land use restrictions and encumbrances, mortgages, or liens affecting your lot and some important facts about payments, recording, and title insurance.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XV. <E T="03">Statement on Release Provisions</E>—§ 1010.109(c)(2)(i)(A)</HD>
        <P>“The release provisions for the (indicate all or particular lots) have not been recorded. Therefore, they may not be honored by subsequent holders of the mortgage. If they are not honored, you may not be able to obtain clear title to a lot covered by this mortgage until we have paid the mortgage in full, even if you have paid the full purchase price of the lot. If we should default on the mortgage prior to obtaining a release of your lot, you may lose your lot and all monies paid.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XVI. <E T="03">Warning for Release Provisions</E>—§ 1010.109(c)(2)(i)(C)(<E T="03">1</E>)</HD>
        <P>“The (state type of encumbrance) on (indicate all or particular lots) in this subdivision does not contain any provisions for the release of an individual lot when the full purchase price of the lot has been paid. Therefore, if your lot is subject to this (state type of encumbrance), you may not be able to obtain clear title to your lot until we have paid the (state type of encumbrance) in full, even though you may have received a deed and paid the full purchase price of the lot. If we should default on the (state type of encumbrance) prior to obtaining a release, you may lose your lot and all monies paid.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XVII. <E T="03">Method and Purpose of Recording Warning</E>—§ 1010.109(d)(1)(iv)</HD>
        <P>“Unless your contract or deed is recorded you may lose your lot through the claims of subsequent purchasers or subsequent creditors of anyone having an interest in the land”.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XVIII. <E T="03">Escrow Statement—Disclosure</E> § 1010.109(e)(1)</HD>
        <P>“You may lose your (indicate deposit, down payment and/or installment payments) on your lot if we fail to deliver legal title to you as called for in the contract, because (they are/it is) not held in an escrow account which fully protects you.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XIX. <E T="03">Road Chart</E>—§ 1010.110(b)(3)</HD>
        <PRTPAGE P="315"/>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50" COLS="6" OPTS="L2,tp0,i1">
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">UUnit</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated starting date<LI>(month/year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Percentage of construction now complete</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated completion date<LI>(month/year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Present <LI>surface</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Final surface</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22"/>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XX. <E T="03">Nearby Communities Chart</E>—§ 1010.110(b)(6)</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s30,8" COLS="2" OPTS="L0,tp0,p1,8/9,i1">
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Nearby Communities</ENT>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Population</ENT>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Distance Over Paved Roads</ENT>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">Distance Over Unpaved Roads</ENT>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02">Total</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXI. <E T="03">Water Chart Form</E>—§ 1010.111(a)(1)(ii)(B)</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50" COLS="4" OPTS="L2,i1">
          <TTITLE>Water</TTITLE>
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">UUnit</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated starting date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Percentage of <LI>construction now </LI>
              <LI>complete</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated service availability date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22"/>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXII. <E T="03">Comfort Station Chart</E>—§ 1010.111(b)(1)(ii)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comfort Stations</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Unit</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Estimated Starting Date (month-year)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Percentage of Construction now complete</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Estimated Service Availability Date (month and year)</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXIII. <E T="03">Sewer Chart</E>—§ 1010.111(b)(1)(iii)(B)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Sewer</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Unit Estimated Starting Date (month/year)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Percentage of Construction now complete</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Estimated Service Availability Date (month/year)</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXIV. Electric Service Chart—§ 1010.111(c)(2)</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50" COLS="4" OPTS="L2,i1">
          <TTITLE>Electric Service</TTITLE>
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">UUnit</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated starting date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Percentage of <LI>construction complete</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated service availability date<LI>(month and year)</LI>
            </CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22"/>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXV. <E T="03">Recreational Facility Chart</E>—§ 1010.114(b)</HD>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50,xl50" COLS="6" OPTS="L2,tp0,i1">
          <BOXHD>
            <CHED H="1">Facility</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Percentage of <LI>construction now </LI>
              <LI>complete</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated date of start of construction<LI>(month/year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Estimated date <LI>available for use</LI>
              <LI>(month/year)</LI>
            </CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Financial assurance of completion</CHED>
            <CHED H="1">Buyer's annual cost or assessments</CHED>
          </BOXHD>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="22"/>
            <ENT/>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXVI. <E T="03">Cost Sheet Format</E>—§ 1010.117(a)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Cost Sheet</HD>
        <P>In addition to the purchase price of your lot, there are other expenditures which must be made.</P>
        <P>Listed below are the major costs. There may be other fees for use of the recreational facilities.</P>
        <P>All costs are subject to change.</P>
        <GPOTABLE CDEF="s30,r8" COLS="2" OPTS="L0,tp0,p0,8/9,g1,t1,i1">
          <ROW EXPSTB="01">
            <ENT I="21">Sales Price</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="00">
            <ENT I="01">Cash Price of lot</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW RUL="n,s">
            <ENT I="01">Finance Charge</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02">Total</ENT>
            <ENT>$
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="01">
            <ENT I="21">Estimated one-time charges
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="00">
            <ENT I="01">1. Water connection fee/installation or private well</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">2. Sewer connection fee/installation of private on-site sewer system</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">3. Construction costs to extend electric and/or telephone services</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW RUL="n,s">
            <ENT I="01">4. Other (Identify)</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01"/>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="02">Total of estimated sales price and one-time charges</ENT>
            <ENT>$
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="01">
            <PRTPAGE P="316"/>
            <ENT I="21">Estimated monthly/annual charges, exclusive of utility use fees
            </ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW EXPSTB="00">
            <ENT I="01">1. Taxes—Average unimproved lot after sale to purchaser</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
          <ROW>
            <ENT I="01">2. Dues and assessments</ENT>
            <ENT>$</ENT>
          </ROW>
        </GPOTABLE>

        <P>The information contained in this Property Report is an accurate description of our subdivision and development plans.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>Signature of Senior Executive Officer</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXVII. <E T="03">Sample Receipt, Agent Certification and Cancellation Page</E>—§ 1010.118(a)</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Receipt, Agent Certification and Cancellation Page purchaser receipt Important: Read Carefully</HD>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">ILSRP number</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date of report</FP>


        <P>We must give you a copy of this Property Report and give you an opportunity to read it before you sign any contract or agreement. By signing this receipt, you acknowledge that you have received a copy of our Property Report.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Received by</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Street address</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">City</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">State</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Zip</FP>


        <P>If any representations are made to you which are contrary to those in this Report, please notify the:
        </P>
        <FP>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</FP>
        <FP>1700 G Street NW</FP>
        <FP>Washington, DC 20006</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Agent Certification</HD>

        <P>I certify that I have made no representations to the person(s) receiving this Property Report which are contrary to the information contained in this Property Report.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Lot</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Block</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Section</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of salesperson</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Signature</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">Purchase Cancellation</HD>

        <P>If you are entitled to cancel your purchase contract, and wish to do so, you may cancel by personal notice, or in writing. If you cancel in person or by telephone, it is recommended that you immediately confirm the cancellation by certified mail. You may use the form below.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Name of subdivision</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date of contract</FP>


        <P>This will confirm that I/we wish to cancel our purchase contract.

        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Purchaser(s) signature</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">Date</FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXVIII. <E T="03">Affirmation of Senior Executive Officer</E>—§ 1010.219</HD>
        <P>I hereby affirm that I am the Senior Executive Officer of the developer of the lots herein described or will be the Senior Executive Officer of the developer at the time lots are offered for sale or lease to the public, or that I am the agent authorized by the Senior Executive Officer of such developer to complete this statement (if agent, submit written authorization to act as agent); and,</P>
        <P>That the statements contained in this Statement of Record and any supplement hereto, together with any documents submitted herein, are full, true, complete, and correct; and,</P>
        <P>That the developer is bound to carry out the promises and obligations set forth in this Statement of Record and Property Report or I have clearly stated who is or will be responsible; and</P>
        <P>That the fees accompanying this submission are in the amount required by the rules and regulations of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Date)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Signature)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Corporate seal if applicable)</FP>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>(Title)</FP>

        <P>WARNING: 15 U.S.C. 1717 provides: “Any person who willfully violates any of the provisions of this title or of the rules and regulations or any person who willfully, in a Statement of Record filed under, or in a Property Report issued pursuant to this title, makes any untrue statement of a material fact shall upon conviction be fined not more than $10,000.00 or imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXIX. <E T="03">Form for Certification for Disclosure Documents</E>—§ 1010.504(a)(2)</HD>

        <P>The (indicate the State Department of Real Estate or other appropriate entity) has reviewed the attached materials and finds they are true copies of (1) the (indicate Property Report or other similar state accepted document or amendment to such document) for (indicate the name of the subdivision), made effective by the state of ______ on ______ (give date) and still in effect; and (2) the supporting documentation upon which such (indicate the document or amendment) is based.
        </P>
        <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH"/>
        <FP>Signature<PRTPAGE P="317"/>
        </FP>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXX. <E T="03">Language to be Included on Property Report Cover Page</E>—§ 1010.558(a)(1)</HD>
        <P>“If you received this Report prior to signing a contract or agreement, you may cancel your contract or agreement by giving notice to the seller anytime before midnight of the seventh day following the signing of the contract or agreement.</P>
        <P>“If you did not receive this Report before you signed a contract or agreement, you may cancel the contract or agreement anytime within two years from the date of signing.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD3">XXXI. <E T="03">Notice of Revocation Rights</E>—§ 1010.559(a)(1)</HD>
        <P>You have the option to cancel your contract or agreement of sale by notice to the seller until midnight of the seventh day following the signing of the contract or agreement. If you did not receive a Property Report prepared pursuant to the rules and regulations of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, in advance of your signing the contract or agreement, this contract or agreement may be revoked at your option for two years from the date of signing.</P>
      </APPENDIX>
    </SUBPART>
  </PART>
</CFRGRANULE>
