<RULE>
        <PREAMB>
          <PRTPAGE P="60382"/>
          <AGENCY TYPE="S">BUREAU OF CONSUMER FINANCIAL PROTECTION</AGENCY>
          <CFR>12 CFR Parts 1024, and 1026</CFR>
          <DEPDOC>[Docket No. CFPB-2013-0018]</DEPDOC>
          <RIN>RIN 3170-AA37</RIN>
          <SUBJECT>Amendments to the 2013 Mortgage Rules Under the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (Regulation B), Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (Regulation X), and the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z)</SUBJECT>
          <AGY>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
            <P>Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</P>
          </AGY>
          <ACT>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
            <P>Final rule.</P>
          </ACT>
          <SUM>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
            <P>This final rule amends some of the final mortgage rules issued by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection (Bureau) in January 2013. These amendments focus primarily on loss mitigation procedures under Regulation X's servicing provisions, amounts counted as loan originator compensation to retailers of manufactured homes and their employees for purposes of applying points and fees thresholds under the Home Ownership and Equity Protection Act and the Ability-to-Repay rules in Regulation Z, exemptions available to creditors that operate predominantly in &#x201C;rural or underserved&#x201D; areas for various purposes under the mortgage regulations, application of the loan originator compensation rules to bank tellers and similar staff, and the prohibition on creditor-financed credit insurance. The Bureau also is adjusting the effective dates for certain provisions of the loan originator compensation rules. In addition, the Bureau is adopting technical and wording changes for clarification purposes to Regulations B, X, and Z.</P>
          </SUM>
          <DATES>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
            <P>This final rule is effective January 1, 2014.</P>
            <P>In addition this rule changes the effective date from January 10, 2014, to January 1, 2014, for the amendments to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2), 1026.36(a), (b), (d), (e), (f), and (j) and commentary to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) and 1026.36(a), (b), (d), (e), (f), and (j) in Supp. I to part 1026, published February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280.</P>
          </DATES>
          <FURINF>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
            <P>Whitney Patross, Attorney; Richard Arculin, William Corbett, Michael Silver, and Daniel Brown, Counsels; Mark Morelli and Nicholas Hluchyj, Senior Counsels, and Paul Ceja, Senior Counsel and Special Advisor, Office of Regulations, at (202) 435-7700.</P>
          </FURINF>
        </PREAMB>
        <SUPLINF>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Summary of Final Rule</HD>
          <P>In January 2013, the Bureau issued several final rules concerning mortgage markets in the United States (2013 Title XIV Final Rules), pursuant to the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (Dodd-Frank Act), Public Law 111-203, 124 Stat. 1376 (2010).<SU>1</SU>
            <FTREF/>In June 2013, the Bureau proposed several amendments to those final rules (&#x201C;June 2013 Proposal&#x201D;).<SU>2</SU>
            <FTREF/>This final rule adopts with some revisions and additional clarifications the June 2013 Proposal. It makes several amendments to the provisions adopted by the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules to clarify or revise regulatory provisions and official interpretations primarily relating to the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules and the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, as described further below. This final rule also makes modifications to the effective dates for provisions adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, and certain technical corrections and minor refinements to Regulations B, X, and Z. The specifics of these amendments and modifications are discussed in the following paragraphs.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>1</SU>Specifically, on January 10, 2013, the Bureau issued Escrow Requirements Under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z), 78 FR 4726 (Jan. 22, 2013) (2013 Escrows Final Rule), High-Cost Mortgage and Homeownership Counseling Amendments to the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z) and Homeownership Counseling Amendments to the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (Regulation X), 78 FR 6856 (Jan. 31, 2013) (2013 HOEPA Final Rule), and Ability-to-Repay and Qualified Mortgage Standards Under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z), 78 FR 6407 (Jan. 30, 2013) (2013 ATR Final Rule). The Bureau concurrently issued a proposal to amend the 2013 ATR Final Rule, which was finalized on May 29, 2013. See 78 FR 6621 (Jan. 30, 2013) and 78 FR 35430 (June 12, 2013). On January 17, 2013, the Bureau issued the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (Regulation X) and Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z) Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, 78 FR 10901 (Regulation Z) (Feb. 14, 2013) and 78 FR 10695 (Regulation X) (Feb. 14, 2013) (2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules). On January 18, 2013, the Bureau issued the Disclosure and Delivery Requirements for Copies of Appraisals and Other Written Valuations Under the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (Regulation B), 78 FR 7215 (Jan. 31, 2013) (2013 ECOA Final Rule) and, jointly with other agencies, issued Appraisals for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans, 78 FR 10367 (Feb. 13, 2013). On January 20, 2013, the Bureau issued the Loan Originator Compensation Requirements under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z), 78 FR 11280 (Feb. 15, 2013) (2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>2</SU>Amendments to the 2013 Mortgage Rules Under the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (Regulation B), Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (Regulation X), and the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z), 78 FR 39902 (July 2, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>First, the Bureau is adopting several modifications to provisions of Regulation X adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, including those related to error resolution procedures and information requests (&#xA7;&#xA7; 1024.35 and 1024.36), and loss mitigation (&#xA7; 1024.41). With respect to loss mitigation, two of the revisions concern the requirement in &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(2)(i) that a servicer review a borrower's loss mitigation application within five days and provide a notice to the borrower acknowledging receipt and informing the borrower whether the application is complete or incomplete. If the servicer does not deem the application complete, the servicer's notice must also list the missing items and suggest the borrower provide the information by the earliest remaining of four dates specified in the regulation. The changes replace the four specified dates with a requirement that a servicer give a borrower a reasonable date by which the borrower should in which to provide the missing information. New commentary explains the four dates previously specified in the regulation are now treated as milestones that the servicer should consider in selecting a reasonable date, however the final rule allows servicers more flexibility than the existing rule. The changes also set forth requirements and procedures for a servicer to follow in the event that a facially complete application is later found by the servicer to require additional information or corrections to a previously submitted document in order to be evaluated for loss mitigation options available to the borrower. Another modification provides servicers more flexibility in providing short-term payment forbearance plans based on an evaluation of an incomplete loss mitigation application. Other clarifications and revisions address the content of notices required under &#xA7; 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) and (h)(4), which inform borrowers of the outcomes of their evaluation for loss mitigation and any appeals filed by the borrowers. In addition, the amendments address how protections are determined to apply where a foreclosure sale has not been scheduled at the time the borrower submits a loss mitigation application or when a foreclosure sale is rescheduled. Finally, the amendments explain what actions constitute the &#x201C;first notice or filing&#x201D; for purposes of the general ban on proceeding to foreclosure before a<PRTPAGE P="60383"/>borrower is 120 days delinquent, and provide exemptions from the 120-day prohibition for foreclosures for certain reasons other than nonpayment.</P>
          <P>Second, the Bureau is clarifying and revising the definition of points and fees for purposes of the qualified mortgage points and fees cap and the high-cost mortgage points and fees threshold, as adopted in the 2013 ATR Final Rule and the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, respectively. In particular, the Bureau is adding commentary to &#xA7; 1026.32(b)(1)(ii) to clarify for retailers of manufactured homes and their employees what compensation must be counted as loan originator compensation and thus included in the points and fees thresholds. The Bureau also is adding commentary to clarify the treatment of charges paid by parties other than the consumer, including third parties, for purposes of the points and fees thresholds.</P>
          <P>Third, the Bureau is revising two exceptions available under the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules to small creditors operating predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas pending the Bureau's re-examination of the underlying definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; over the next two years, as it recently announced it would do in Ability-to-Repay and Qualified Mortgage Standards Under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z) (May 2013 ATR Final Rule).<SU>3</SU>
            <FTREF/>The Bureau is extending an exception to the general prohibition on balloon features for high-cost mortgages under &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) to allow all small creditors, regardless of whether they operate predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas, to continue originating balloon high-cost mortgages if the loans meet the requirements for qualified mortgages under &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.43(e)(6) or 1026.43(f). In addition, the Bureau is amending an exemption from the requirement to establish escrow accounts for higher-priced mortgage loans under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) for small creditors that extend more than 50 percent of their total covered transactions secured by a first lien in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during the preceding calendar year. To prevent creditors that qualified for the exemption in 2013 from losing eligibility in 2014 or 2015 because of changes in which counties are considered rural while the Bureau is re-evaluating the underlying definition of &#x201C;rural,&#x201D; the Bureau is amending this provision to allow creditors to qualify for the exemption if they extended more than 50 percent of their total covered transactions in rural or underserved counties in any of the previous three calendar years (assuming the other criteria for eligibility are also met).</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>3</SU>78 FR 35430 (June 12, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>Fourth, the Bureau is adopting revisions, as well as general technical and wording changes, to various provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule in &#xA7; 1026.36. These include revising the definition of &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; in the regulatory text and commentary, such as provisions addressing when employees of a creditor or loan originator in certain administrative or clerical roles (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>tellers or greeters) may become &#x201C;loan originators&#x201D; and thus subject to the rule, upon providing contact information or credit applications for loan originators or creditors to consumers; further clarification on the meaning of &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; which is used throughout &#xA7; 1026.36(a); and additional clarifications regarding when employees of manufactured housing retailers may be classified as loan originators. The Bureau also is adopting a number of clarifications to the commentary on prohibited payments to loan originators.</P>
          <P>Fifth, the Bureau is clarifying and revising three aspects of the rules implementing the Dodd-Frank Act prohibition on creditors financing credit insurance premiums in connection with certain consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling. The Bureau is adding new &#xA7; 1026.36(i)(2)(ii) to clarify what constitutes financing of such premiums by a creditor. The Bureau also is adding new &#xA7; 1026.36(i)(2)(iii) to clarify when credit insurance premiums are considered to be calculated and paid on a monthly basis, for purposes of the statutory exclusion from the prohibition for certain credit insurance premium calculation and payment arrangements. And, finally, the Bureau is adding new comment 36(i)-1 to clarify when including the credit insurance premium or fee in the amount owed violates the rule.</P>
          <P>Sixth, the Bureau is changing the effective date for certain provisions under the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, so they take effect on January 1, 2014, rather than January 10, 2014, as originally provided. The affected provisions are the amendments to or additions of (as applicable) &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) (record retention), &#xA7; 1026.36(a) (definitions), &#xA7; 1026.36(b) (scope), &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (compensation), &#xA7; 1026.36(e) (anti-steering), &#xA7; 1026.36(f) (qualifications), and &#xA7; 1026.36(j) (compliance policies and procedures for depository institutions) and the associated commentary. The Bureau believes that this change will facilitate compliance because these provisions largely focus on compensation plan structures, registration and licensing, and hiring and training requirements that are often structured on an annual basis and typically do not vary from transaction to transaction. After reviewing comments, the Bureau has decided to keep the date for implementation of the ban on financing credit insurance under &#xA7; 1026.36(i) as January 10, 2014, consistent with the date previously adopted in the Loan Originator Compensation Requirements under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z); Prohibition on Financing Credit Insurance Premiums; Delay of Effective Date (2013 Effective Date Final Rule).<SU>4</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>4</SU>78 FR 32547 (May 31, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>In addition to the clarifications and amendments to Regulations X and Z discussed above, the Bureau is adopting technical corrections and minor clarifications to wording throughout Regulations B, X, and Z that are generally not substantive in nature.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Background</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Title XIV Rules Under the Dodd-Frank Act</HD>
          <P>In response to an unprecedented cycle of expansion and contraction in the mortgage market that sparked the most severe U.S. recession since the Great Depression, Congress passed the Dodd-Frank Act, which was signed into law on July 21, 2010. Public Law 111-203, 124 Stat. 1376 (2010). In the Dodd-Frank Act, Congress established the Bureau and, under sections 1061 and 1100A, generally consolidated the rulemaking authority for Federal consumer financial laws, including the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (ECOA), Truth in Lending Act (TILA), and Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (RESPA), in the Bureau.<SU>5</SU>

            <FTREF/>At the same time, Congress significantly amended the statutory requirements governing mortgage practices with the intent to restrict the practices that contributed to and exacerbated the crisis. Under the statute, most of these new requirements would have taken effect automatically on January 21, 2013, if the Bureau had not issued implementing regulations by that<PRTPAGE P="60384"/>date.<SU>6</SU>
            <FTREF/>To avoid uncertainty and potential disruption in the national mortgage market at a time of economic vulnerability, the Bureau issued several final rules in a span of less than two weeks in January 2013 to implement these new statutory provisions and provide for an orderly transition.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>5</SU>Sections 1011 and 1021 of the Dodd-Frank Act, in title X, the &#x201C;Consumer Financial Protection Act,&#x201D; Public Law 111-203, sections 1001-1100H, codified at 12 U.S.C. 5491, 5511. The Consumer Financial Protection Act is substantially codified at 12 U.S.C. 5481-5603. Section 1029 of the Dodd-Frank Act excludes from this transfer of authority, subject to certain exceptions, any rulemaking authority over a motor vehicle dealer that is predominantly engaged in the sale and servicing of motor vehicles, the leasing and servicing of motor vehicles, or both. 12 U.S.C. 5519.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>6</SU>Dodd-Frank Act section 1400(c), 15 U.S.C. 1601 note.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>On January 10, 2013, the Bureau issued the 2013 ATR Final Rule, the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, and the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule. On January 17, 2013, the Bureau issued the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules. On January 18, 2013, the Bureau issued Appraisals for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans<SU>7</SU>
            <FTREF/>(issued jointly with other agencies) and the 2013 ECOA Final Rule. On January 20, 2013, the Bureau issued the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. Most of these rules will become effective on January 10, 2014.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>7</SU>78 FR 10367 (Feb. 13, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>Concurrent with the 2013 ATR Final Rule, on January 10, 2013, the Bureau issued Proposed Amendments to the Ability to Repay Standards Under the Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z) (2013 ATR Concurrent Proposal), which the Bureau finalized on May 29, 2013 (May 2013 ATR Final Rule).<SU>8</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>8</SU>78 FR 6622 (Jan. 30, 2013); 78 FR 35430 (June 12, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Implementation Initiative for New Mortgage Rules</HD>
          <P>On February 13, 2013, the Bureau announced an initiative to support implementation of its new mortgage rules (Implementation Plan),<SU>9</SU>
            <FTREF/>under which the Bureau would work with the mortgage industry and other stakeholders to ensure that the new rules can be implemented accurately and expeditiously. The Implementation Plan includes: (1) Coordination with other agencies, including to develop consistent, updated examination procedures; (2) publication of plain-language guides to the new rules; (3) publication of additional corrections and clarifications of the new rules, as needed; (4) publication of readiness guides for the new rules; and (5) education of consumers on the new rules.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>9</SU>Consumer Financial Protection Bureau Lays Out Implementation Plan for New Mortgage Rules. Press Release. Feb. 13, 2013.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>In the June 2013 proposal, the Bureau proposed amendments to its new mortgage rules. This final rule adopts those proposed amendments with some additional clarifications and revisions. The purpose of these updates is to address important questions raised by industry, consumer groups, or other agencies.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Comments on the Proposed Rule</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received 280 comments on the proposed rule on which the final rule is based. Many of these comments discussed issues on which the proposed rule did not seek comment or address. A number of comments addressed, for example, the small servicer exemption, the general effective dates for the 2013 Title XIV Rules finalized in January 2013, whether the Bureau should reconsider replacing the &#xA7; 1026.36(a) definition of &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; with the definition provided under the SAFE Act, or whether the Bureau should amend the provision of the mortgage servicing rules that deals with second or successive loss mitigation applications. This final rule does not make any changes outside the scope of the proposal. As proposed, it focuses on specific, narrow implementation and interpretive issues, rather than broader policy changes.</P>
          <P>The Bureau has examined all comments submitted and discusses those that were responsive to the proposal in the section-by-section analysis below.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">III. Legal Authority</HD>
          <P>The Bureau is issuing this final rule pursuant to its authority under ECOA, TILA, RESPA, and the Dodd-Frank Act. Section 1061 of the Dodd-Frank Act transferred to the Bureau the &#x201C;consumer financial protection functions&#x201D; previously vested in certain other Federal agencies, including the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (Federal Reserve Board). The term &#x201C;consumer financial protection function&#x201D; is defined to include &#x201C;all authority to prescribe rules or issue orders or guidelines pursuant to any Federal consumer financial law, including performing appropriate functions to promulgate and review such rules, orders, and guidelines.&#x201D;<SU>10</SU>
            <FTREF/>Section 1061 of the Dodd-Frank Act also transferred to the Bureau all of the Department of Housing and Urban Development's (HUD) consumer protection functions relating to RESPA.<SU>11</SU>
            <FTREF/>Title X of the Dodd-Frank Act, including section 1061 of the Dodd-Frank Act, along with ECOA, TILA, RESPA, and certain subtitles and provisions of title XIV of the Dodd-Frank Act, are Federal consumer financial laws.<SU>12</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>10</SU>12 U.S.C. 5581(a)(1).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>11</SU>Public Law 111-203, 124 Stat. 1376, section 1061(b)(7); 12 U.S.C. 5581(b)(7).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>12</SU>Dodd-Frank Act section 1002(14), 12 U.S.C. 5481(14) (defining &#x201C;Federal consumer financial law&#x201D; to include the &#x201C;enumerated consumer laws&#x201D; and the provisions of title X of the Dodd-Frank Act); Dodd-Frank Act section 1002(12), 12 U.S.C. 5481(12) (defining &#x201C;enumerated consumer laws&#x201D; to include TILA), Dodd-Frank section 1400(b), 15 U.S.C. 1601 note (defining &#x201C;enumerated consumer laws&#x201D; to include certain subtitles and provisions of Title XIV).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. ECOA</HD>
          <P>Section 703(a) of ECOA authorizes the Bureau to prescribe regulations to carry out the purposes of ECOA. Section 703(a) further states that such regulations may contain&#x2014;but are not limited to&#x2014;such classifications, differentiation, or other provision, and may provide for such adjustments and exceptions for any class of transactions as, in the judgment of the Bureau, are necessary or proper to effectuate the purposes of ECOA, to prevent circumvention or evasion thereof, or to facilitate or substantiate compliance. 15 U.S.C. 1691b(a).</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. RESPA</HD>
          <P>Section 19(a) of RESPA, 12 U.S.C. 2617(a), authorizes the Bureau to prescribe such rules and regulations, to make such interpretations, and to grant such reasonable exemptions for classes of transactions, as may be necessary to achieve the purposes of RESPA, which include its consumer protection purposes. In addition, section 6(j)(3) of RESPA, 12 U.S.C. 2605(j)(3), authorizes the Bureau to establish any requirements necessary to carry out section 6 of RESPA, and section 6(k)(1)(E) of RESPA, 12 U.S.C. 2605(k)(1)(E), authorizes the Bureau to prescribe regulations that are appropriate to carry out RESPA's consumer protection purposes. As identified in the 2013 RESPA Servicing Final Rule, the consumer protection purposes of RESPA include ensuring that servicers respond to borrower requests and complaints in a timely manner and maintain and provide accurate information, helping borrowers avoid unwarranted or unnecessary costs and fees, and facilitating review for foreclosure avoidance options.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. TILA</HD>

          <P>Section 105(a) of TILA, 15 U.S.C. 1604(a), authorizes the Bureau to prescribe regulations to carry out the purposes of TILA. Under section 105(a), such regulations may contain such additional requirements, classifications, differentiations, or other provisions, and may provide for such adjustments and exceptions for all or any class of transactions, as in the judgment of the Bureau are necessary or proper to effectuate the purposes of TILA, to prevent circumvention or evasion<PRTPAGE P="60385"/>thereof, or to facilitate compliance therewith. A purpose of TILA is &#x201C;to assure a meaningful disclosure of credit terms so that the consumer will be able to compare more readily the various credit terms available to him and avoid the uninformed use of credit.&#x201D; TILA section 102(a), 15 U.S.C. 1601(a). In particular, it is a purpose of TILA section 129C, as amended by the Dodd-Frank Act, to assure that consumers are offered and receive residential mortgage loans on terms that reasonably reflect their ability to repay the loans and that are understandable and not unfair, deceptive, and abusive. Section 105(f) of TILA, 15 U.S.C. 1604(f), authorizes the Bureau to exempt from all or part of TILA any class of transactions if the Bureau determines that TILA coverage does not provide a meaningful benefit to consumers in the form of useful information or protection. Under TILA section 103(bb)(4), the Bureau may adjust the definition of points and fees for purposes of that threshold to include such charges that the Bureau determines to be appropriate.</P>
          <P>TILA section 129C(b)(3)(B)(i) provides the Bureau with authority to prescribe regulations that revise, add to, or subtract from the criteria that define a qualified mortgage upon a finding that such regulations are necessary or proper to ensure that responsible, affordable mortgage credit remains available to consumers in a manner consistent with the purposes of the ability-to-repay requirements; or are necessary and appropriate to effectuate the purposes of the ability-to-repay requirements, to prevent circumvention or evasion thereof, or to facilitate compliance with TILA sections 129B and 129C. 15 U.S.C. 1639c(b)(3)(B)(i). In addition, TILA section 129C(b)(3)(A) requires the Bureau to prescribe regulations to carry out the purposes of the qualified mortgage provisions, such as to ensure that responsible and affordable mortgage credit remains available to consumers in a manner consistent with the purposes of TILA section 129C. 15 U.S.C. 1639c(b)(3)(A).</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">D. The Dodd-Frank Act</HD>
          <P>Section 1022(b)(1) of the Dodd-Frank Act authorizes the Bureau to prescribe rules &#x201C;as may be necessary or appropriate to enable the Bureau to administer and carry out the purposes and objectives of the Federal consumer financial laws, and to prevent evasions thereof.&#x201D; 12 U.S.C. 5512(b)(1). Title X of the Dodd-Frank Act is a Federal consumer financial law. Accordingly, the Bureau is exercising its authority under the Dodd-Frank Act section 1022(b) to prescribe rules that carry out the purposes and objectives of ECOA, RESPA, TILA, title X, and the enumerated subtitles and provisions of title XIV of the Dodd-Frank Act, and prevent evasion of those laws.</P>
          <P>Section 1032(a) of the Dodd-Frank Act provides that the Bureau &#x201C;may prescribe rules to ensure that the features of any consumer financial product or service, both initially and over the term of the product or service, are fully, accurately, and effectively disclosed to consumers in a manner that permits consumers to understand the costs, benefits, and risks associated with the product or service, in light of the facts and circumstances.&#x201D; 12 U.S.C. 5532(a). The authority granted to the Bureau in Dodd-Frank Act section 1032(a) is broad, and empowers the Bureau to prescribe rules regarding the disclosure of the &#x201C;features&#x201D; of consumer financial products and services generally. Accordingly, the Bureau may prescribe rules containing disclosure requirements even if other Federal consumer financial laws do not specifically require disclosure of such features.</P>
          <P>Dodd-Frank Act section 1032(c) provides that, in prescribing rules pursuant to Dodd-Frank Act section 1032, the Bureau &#x201C;shall consider available evidence about consumer awareness, understanding of, and responses to disclosures or communications about the risks, costs, and benefits of consumer financial products or services.&#x201D; 12 U.S.C. 5532(c). Accordingly, in amending provisions authorized under Dodd-Frank Act section 1032(a), the Bureau has considered available studies, reports, and other evidence about consumer awareness, understanding of, and responses to disclosures or communications about the risks, costs, and benefits of consumer financial products or services.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is amending rules finalized in January 2013 that implement certain Dodd-Frank Act provisions. In particular, the Bureau is amending regulatory provisions adopted by the 2013 ECOA Final Rule, the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, and the 2013 ATR Final Rule.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">IV. Effective Dates</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Provisions Other Than Those Related to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule or the 2013 Escrows Final Rule</HD>
          <P>In enacting the Dodd-Frank Act, Congress significantly amended the statutory requirements governing a number of mortgage practices. Under the Dodd-Frank Act, most of these new requirements would have taken effect automatically on January 21, 2013, if the Bureau had not issued implementing regulations by that date.<SU>13</SU>
            <FTREF/>Where the Bureau was required to prescribe implementing regulations, the Dodd-Frank Act further provided that those regulations must take effect not later than 12 months after the date of the regulations' issuance in final form.<SU>14</SU>
            <FTREF/>The Bureau issued the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules in January 2013 to implement these new statutory provisions and provide for an orderly transition. To allow the mortgage industry sufficient time to comply with the new rules, the Bureau established January 10, 2014&#x2014;one year after issuance of the earliest of the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules&#x2014;as the baseline effective date for nearly all of the new requirements. In the preamble to certain of the various 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, the Bureau further specified that the new regulations would apply to transactions for which applications were received on or after January 10, 2014.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>13</SU>Dodd-Frank Act section 1400(c)(3), 15 U.S.C. 1601 note.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>14</SU>Dodd-Frank Act section 1400(c)(1)(B), 15 U.S.C. 1601 note.</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>Except for the amendments regarding the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule and the 2013 Escrows Final Rule discussed below, the Bureau proposed an effective date of January 10, 2014. The Bureau proposed this effective date because it is consistent with the effective dates for the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, which this final rule clarifies, revises, or amends. Most of the proposed amendments were intended to clarify application of certain aspects of these rules in advance of the January 10, 2014 effective date, or amend them in manners that facilitate compliance. As discussed in the various 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, the Bureau believes that having a consistent effective date across most of the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules will facilitate compliance. This includes any clarifications, revisions, or other amendments made during the implementation period&#x2014;particularly those amendments designed to facilitate compliance with the overarching 2013 Title XIV Final Rules. Thus, because the clarifications, revisions, and amendments to the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules adopted in this final rule interrelate with or depend on other aspects of the underlying 2013 Title XIV Final Rules and are intended largely to facilitate compliance with those rules,<PRTPAGE P="60386"/>the Bureau does not believe that the amendments adopted by this final rule should become effective on a different date than the underlying regulations. The Bureau thus proposed an effective date of January 10, 2014 for any amendments adopted by this final rule.</P>
          <P>The Bureau received some comments from industry and trade associations that addressed the effective dates, but most of these comments generally requested a delayed effective date across all the rules, which the Bureau did not propose. The Bureau received a handful of comments that asked for staggered effective dates for the amended rules, but none of these comments provided a reasonable means of implementing the proposed amendments at a date later than the underlying regulations the proposal would have amended. Despite these comments, the Bureau remains persuaded that it would be impracticable for these amendments to take effect later than the underlying regulations they amend. Moreover, the Bureau believes that these amendments should help industry participants comply with the other components of the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, which in most cases also will take effect January 10, 2014. The Bureau thus is adopting the effective date of January 10, 2014, for the amendments in this document other than as discussed in parts IV.B and IV.C below.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. For Provisions Related to the 2013 Escrows Final Rule</HD>

          <P>The Bureau proposed an effective date of January 1, 2014 for the amendments to the new provisions in &#xA7; 1026.35 that govern higher-priced mortgage loan escrow requirements, which took effect on June 1, 2013. While the Bureau established January 10, 2014 as the baseline effective date for most of the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, it identified certain provisions that it believed did not present significant implementation burdens for industry, including amendments to &#xA7; 1026.35 adopted by the 2013 Escrows Final Rule. For these provisions, the Bureau set an earlier effective date of June 1, 2013. The proposal would have amended one such provision, &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A), which provides an exemption from the higher-priced mortgage loan escrow requirement to creditors that extend more than 50 percent of their total covered transactions secured by a first lien in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during the preceding calendar year and also meet other small creditor criteria, and do not otherwise maintain escrow accounts for loans serviced by themselves or an affiliate. In light of recent changes to which counties meet the definition of &#x201C;rural,&#x201D; the Bureau proposed to amend this provision to prevent creditors that qualified for the exemption in 2013 from losing eligibility in 2014 or 2015 because of these changes. The proposal would have allowed creditors to qualify for the exemption if they qualified in any of the previous three calendar years (assuming the other criteria for eligibility are also met). In addition, the proposal would have amended &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) to prevent creditors that were previously ineligible for the exemption, but may now qualify in light of the proposed changes, from losing eligibility because they had established escrow accounts for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans (for which applications were received after June 1, 2013), as required when the final rule took effect and prior to the proposed amendments taking effect. The Bureau proposed to make this amendment effective for applications received on or after January 1, 2014, because the &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) exemption applies based on a calendar year and relates to a regulation that is already in effect. The Bureau received no comments addressing the proposed effective date of this provision, other than comments that generally supported the proposal.</P>
          <P>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis below, the Bureau is adopting amendments to &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) as proposed. In addition, the Bureau is adopting amendments to the commentary to this section substantially as proposed with one additional clarification. The Bureau believes it is appropriate to set a January 1, 2014 effective date for these provisions. The Bureau notes that a January 1, 2014 effective date is more beneficial to industry, because the amendment would only expand eligibility for the exemption&#x2014;thus an effective date of January 1, 2014, as opposed to January 10, 2014, would mean that creditors are able to take advantage of this expanded exemption earlier. Accordingly, the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) and its commentary will apply to applications received on or after January 1, 2014.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Provisions Related to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule</HD>
          <P>The effective date for certain provisions in this final rule related to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, along with the related provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, is January 1, 2014, for the reasons discussed below.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">V. Effective Date of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Rule</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. General</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>As described in the proposal, the Bureau established January 10, 2014, as the baseline effective date for nearly all of the provisions in the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, including most provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. In the proposal, the Bureau stated that it believed that having a consistent effective date across nearly all of the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules would facilitate compliance. However, as explained in the proposal, the Bureau identified a few provisions that it believed did not present significant implementation burdens for industry, including &#xA7; 1026.36(h) on mandatory arbitration clauses and waivers of certain consumer rights and &#xA7; 1026.36(i) on financing credit insurance, as adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. As explained in the proposal, for these provisions (and associated commentary), the Bureau set an earlier effective date of June 1, 2013.<SU>15</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>15</SU>After interpretive issues were raised concerning the credit insurance provision as discussed in the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, the Bureau temporarily delayed and extended the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(i) in the 2013 Effective Date Final Rule until January 10, 2014. 78 FR 32547 (May 31, 2013). In the proposal, the Bureau requested comment on whether the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(i) may be set earlier than January 10, 2014.</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>As described in the proposal, since issuing the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule in January 2013, the Bureau has received a number of questions about transition issues, particularly with regard to application of provisions under &#xA7; 1026.36(d) that generally prohibit basing loan originator compensation on transaction terms but permit creditors to award non-deferred profits-based compensation subject to certain limits. For instance, as discussed in the proposal, the Bureau has received inquiries about when creditors and loan originator organizations may begin taking into account transactions for purposes of paying compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan pursuant to &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>the 10-percent total compensation limit, or the 10-percent limit). As the Bureau stated in the proposal, while the profits-based compensation provisions present relatively complicated transition issues, the Bureau is also conscious of the fact that most other provisions in the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final<PRTPAGE P="60387"/>Rule are simpler to implement because they largely recodify and clarify existing requirements that were previously adopted by the Federal Reserve Board in 2010 with regard to loan originator compensation, and by various agencies under the Secure and Fair Enforcement for Mortgage Licensing Act of 2008, 12 U.S.C. 5106-5116 (SAFE Act), with regard to loan originator qualification requirements. The Bureau also stated in the proposal that these provisions are focused on compensation plan structures, registration and licensing, and hiring and training requirements that are often structured on an annual basis and typically do not vary from transaction to transaction.</P>
          <P>For all of these reasons, the Bureau proposed moving the general effective date for most provisions adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule to January 1, 2014. The Bureau stated in the proposal that, although this change would shorten the implementation period by nine days, the Bureau believes that the change would actually facilitate compliance and reduce implementation burden by providing a cleaner transition period that more closely aligns with changes to employers' annual compensation structures and registration, licensing, and training requirements. In addition, the Bureau also stated that, because elements of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule concerning retention of records, definitions, scope, and implementing procedures affect multiple provisions, the Bureau was proposing to make the change with regard to the bulk of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule as described further below, rather than attempting to treat individual provisions in isolation. Finally, the Bureau also proposed changes to the effective date for provisions on financing of credit insurance under &#xA7; 1026.36(i), in connection with proposing further clarifications and guidance on the Dodd-Frank Act requirements related to that provision.</P>
          <P>The Bureau stated in the proposal that it believed these changes would facilitate compliance and help ensure that the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule does not have adverse unintended consequences. The Bureau requested public comment on these proposed effective dates, including on any suggested alternatives.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received approximately 30 comments addressing the proposed changes to the effective date for the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule other than &#xA7; 1026.36(i).<SU>16</SU>

            <FTREF/>The comments generally were supportive of these proposed changes. A national association of credit unions and several state credit union associations supported moving up the effective date from January 10, 2014, to January 1, 2014, stating that a January 1 date would result in a cleaner transition period that more closely aligns with changes to employers' annual compensation structures and registration, licensing, and training requirements. A national trade association of banking institutions stated its appreciation for the Bureau's efforts to facilitate compliance and establish effective dates that are better aligned with banker systems. This association wrote that it did not believe a January 1 effective date would constitute a major burden. The association urged the Bureau, however, to enact effective dates that apply to transactions that are<E T="03">either</E>consummated on or after January 1, 2014<E T="03">or</E>for which the creditor paid compensation on or after that date. According to the association, allowing for an alternative option would best accommodate the various payment systems and methods that exist across various institutions and would not, in its opinion, give rise to significant difficulties in terms of examinations.<SU>17</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>16</SU>The comments regarding the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(i) are discussed separately below.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>17</SU>The association stated further that, under this approach, an institution would have to abide by whatever effective date methodology it selects.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>One community bank commented that it would pose unnecessary and wasteful burdens on financial institutions of all sizes to necessitate a separate accounting and reporting for a nine-day period, because accounting periods for compensation generally commence annually each January 1st. A large mortgage company stated that it supported the change because moving the effective date to January 1, 2014, would help lenders update their systems on a consistent basis and avoid any potential lapses in accounting or confusion that could emerge between January 1 and January 10. One community bank stated that it is &#x201C;operationally efficient&#x201D; to apply rule changes at the beginning of a month and that there would be no real difference in compliance burden because &#x201C;most lenders would naturally&#x201D; comply as of the earlier date anyway. A state association representing banking institutions wrote that moving up the effective date by nine days aligns more closely with payroll records and tax reporting and may actually be easier to implement from an operational basis than a January 10 effective date. This association did report that its members have indicated that they will not be able to meet either a January 1 or a January 10, 2014, effective date due to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule's complexity and pending amendments.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>As discussed in more detail below, the Bureau is finalizing the effective dates for &#xA7; 1026.36 (and interrelated provisions in &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2)) adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule (and associated commentary), and the amendments to and additions to those sections contained in today's final rule, as proposed. The Bureau discusses in turn below the effective dates for different provisions of &#xA7; 1026.36 (and interrelated provisions in &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2)). These clarifications and amendments to the effective date require only minimal revisions to the rule text and commentary and primarily are reflected in the Dates caption and discussion of effective dates in this Supplementary Information. As amended by the Dodd-Frank Act, TILA section 105(a), 15 U.S.C. 1604(a), directs the Bureau to prescribe regulations to carry out the purposes of TILA, and provides that such regulations may contain additional requirements, classifications, differentiations, or other provisions, and may provide for such adjustments and exceptions for all or any class of transactions, that the Bureau judges are necessary or proper to effectuate the purposes of TILA, to prevent circumvention or evasion thereof, or to facilitate compliance. Under Dodd-Frank Act section 1022(b)(1), 15 U.S.C. 5512(b)(1), the Bureau has general authority to prescribe rules as may be necessary or appropriate to enable the Bureau to administer and carry out the purposes and objectives of the Federal consumer financial laws, and to prevent evasions thereof. The Bureau is changing the effective date of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule with respect to those provisions described above pursuant to its TILA section 105(a) and Dodd-Frank Act section 1022(b)(1) authority.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Effective Date for Amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d)</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>

          <P>The Bureau proposed three specific changes to the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (and associated commentary) contained in<PRTPAGE P="60388"/>the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. First, the Bureau proposed that the provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule revising &#xA7; 1026.36(d) would be effective January 1, 2014, not January 10, 2014. The Bureau discussed its concern that an effective date of January 10, 2014, for the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) may result in creditors and loan originator organizations believing that they have to account separately for the period from January 1 through January 9, 2014, when applying the new compensation restrictions under &#xA7; 1026.36(d). While recognizing that this proposal would mean that creditors and loan originator organizations would have a slightly shorter implementation period, the Bureau stated that on balance it believed the proposed change would have eased compliance burdens for creditors and loan originator organizations by eliminating any concern about a need for separate accountings as described above. As noted above, the Bureau also proposed to change the effective date for the addition of &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) (records retention) (and associated commentary) from January 10, 2014, to January 1, 2014, to dovetail with the proposal to change the effective date of &#xA7; 1026.36(d) to January 1, 2014, to ensure that records on compensation paid between January 1 and January 10, 2014, are properly maintained.</P>
          <P>Second, the Bureau proposed that the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (other than the addition of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii), as discussed below) would have applied to transactions that are consummated and for which the creditor or loan originator organization paid compensation on or after January 1, 2014. The Bureau stated its belief that applying the effective date for the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) based on application receipt, rather than based on transaction consummation and compensation payment, could present compliance challenges. This proposed change, as the Bureau discussed in the proposal, would have permitted transactions to be taken into account for purposes of compensating individual loan originators under the exceptions set forth in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) if the transactions were consummated and compensation was paid to the individual loan originator on or after January 1, 2014, even if the applications for those transactions were received prior to January 1, 2014. The Bureau stated that it believes this clarification, in conjunction with the proposed change to the effective date for the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) described above, would have reduced compliance burdens on creditors and loan originator organizations by allowing them to take into account all transactions consummated in 2014 (and for which compensation is paid to individual loan originators in 2014) for purposes of paying compensation under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) that is earned in 2014. This proposed revision also would have allowed the consumer-paid compensation restrictions and exceptions thereto in the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(2) to be effective upon the consummation of any transaction where such compensation is paid in 2014 even if the application for that transaction was received in 2013.</P>
          <P>Third, the Bureau proposed that the provisions of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii), which pertain to contributions to or benefits under designated tax-advantaged plans for individual loan originators, would apply to transactions for which the creditor or loan originator organization paid compensation on or after January 1, 2014, regardless of when the transactions were consummated or the applications were received. The Bureau explained in the proposal that these changes regarding the effective date for the revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) would have more clearly reflected the Bureau's intent to permit payment of compensation related to designated tax-advantaged plans during both 2013 (as explained in CFPB Bulletin 2012-2 clarifying current &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1))<SU>18</SU>
            <FTREF/>and thereafter (under the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule).</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>18</SU>The Bureau explained in the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule that it issued CFPB Bulletin 2012-2 (the Bulletin) to address questions regarding the application of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1) to &#x201C;Qualified Plans&#x201D; (as defined in the Bulletin). The Bureau noted in that Supplementary Information that until the final rule takes effect, the clarifications in CFPB Bulletin 2012-2 remain in effect. Moreover, as the Bureau stated in the proposal, the Bureau interprets &#x201C;Qualified Plan&#x201D; as used in the Bulletin to include the designated tax-advantaged plans described in the final rule.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>In addition to the three specific changes to the effective date described above, the Bureau solicited comment generally on whether the proposed changes to the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) are appropriate or whether other approaches should be considered. In particular, the Bureau solicited comment on whether the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) should take effect on January 1, 2014, and apply to all payments of compensation made on or after that date, regardless of the date of consummation of the transactions on whose terms the compensation was based.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>Industry commenters generally supported the proposed changes to the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) that were added by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. There were no objections to the Bureau's proposal to delete application receipt as the triggering event for the effective date provisions of &#xA7; 1026.36 (other than for &#xA7; 1026.36(g)). One state trade association of banking institutions wrote that applying the effective date for revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) based on receipt of applications would create &#x201C;serious compliance and recordkeeping challenges.&#x201D; Moreover, industry commenters generally supported the shift of the effective date for the amendments of &#xA7; 1026.36(d) from January 10 to January 1, 2014 (see discussion above with regard to the general comments the Bureau received on the changes to the effective dates for the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule). Industry commenters also did not raise any objections to the proposed revisions to the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii), which would have applied to transactions for which compensation is paid on or after January 1, 2014, without regard to when the transactions were consummated. Nor did industry commenters specifically object to the proposal to change the effective date for the addition of &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) (records retention) from January 10, 2014, to January 1, 2014.</P>

          <P>Several commenters expressly supported the Bureau's proposal to apply the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (other than the addition of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii)) to transactions consummated on or after January 1, 2014,<E T="03">and</E>where compensation was paid on or after January 1, 2014. A large depository institution wrote that this approach to the effective date would be a &#x201C;welcome clarification.&#x201D; One industry commenter that specializes in the financing of manufactured housing, in expressing support for proposed changes to the effective date, objected to the alternative on which the Bureau solicited comment (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>that the effective date would apply to compensation paid on or after January 1, 2014, regardless of the date of consummation of the transaction).<SU>19</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>19</SU>This commenter noted its agreement with the Bureau's statement in the proposal that such an approach could raise complexity about how the new rule would apply to payments under non-deferred profits-based compensation plans made on or after January 1, 2014, where the compensation payments were based on the terms of transactions consummated in 2013. This commenter wrote that such an approach would adversely affect, without<PRTPAGE/>fair warning, those creditors and their employees for whom 2013 compensation plans were made in mid-2012.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <PRTPAGE P="60389"/>

          <P>A small number of industry commenters asked that the Bureau provide more flexibility as to the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d). As noted above, one national trade association asked that the effective dates for the various provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule be triggered<E T="03">either</E>by the consummation of transactions on or after January 1, 2014,<E T="03">or</E>by the payment of compensation on or after January 1, 2014, with the complying parties having the option of selecting the applicable triggering event. A state association representing banking institutions similarly asked for an &#x201C;either/or&#x201D; approach with regard to the proposed trigger for the effective date. A state association representing banking institutions stated that the proposed formula for the effective date (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>considering both the consummation date and the payment date) was unnecessarily complex, and instead recommended that the effective date be tied solely to the payment date. A national trade association of mortgage banking institutions and a mortgage company recommended that the Bureau adopt January 1, 2014, as an optional effective date, with mandatory implementation as of January 10, 2014. The association reasoned that while the earlier effective date may benefit many lenders, there may be some lenders that have already arranged compliance for the later date and would be forced to incur additional expense if compliance were required earlier. The mortgage company stated this change might assist in a small way in regards to payroll systems.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>

          <P>The Bureau is finalizing the effective date and applicability for the amendments to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.36(d) and 1026.25(c)(2) (and associated commentary) adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule and the proposed amendments and additions thereto in the June 2013 proposal, as proposed. That is: (1) The amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (other than the addition of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii)) and the provisions of &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) will apply to transactions that are consummated and for which the creditor or loan originator organization paid compensation on or after January 1, 2014; and (2) the provisions of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) will apply to transactions for which the creditor or loan originator organization paid compensation on or after January 1, 2014, regardless of when the transactions were consummated or their applications were received. For the reasons stated in the proposal and supported by many of the commenters, the Bureau believes that a January 1, 2014, effective date will ease compliance burden by aligning the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) with the date on which annual changes to compensation policies are implemented. Moreover, the Bureau believes that tying the application of the effective date for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (other than the addition of &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) and 1026.25(c)(2)) to conjunctive triggering events on or after January 1, 2014 (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>the consummation of transactions<E T="03">and</E>the payment of compensation based on the terms of those transactions) best facilitates a smooth transition from one set of compensation rules to another. The Bureau thus disagrees with the commenters that asked for an &#x201C;either/or&#x201D; approach (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>tied to either the consummation date or the payment date) or for the effective date to be tied only to payment of compensation. A rule where the complying party has the option of choosing among two possible triggering events potentially would create confusion for complying parties and examiners about whether compensation earned in 2013 but paid in 2014 is subject to the current compensation rules under &#xA7; 1026.36(d) or the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) added by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, and as to whether the amended recordkeeping requirements in &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2) would apply. Moreover, as one commenter suggested, permitting creditors and loan originator organizations to pay, in 2014, compensation earned in 2013&#x2014;at which time the current compensation rules were still in effect&#x2014;might disadvantage creditors or loan originator organizations that relied on the current rules in setting up their 2013 compensation programs in 2012.</P>
          <P>The Bureau also believes that providing for an optional compliance date of January 1, 2014&#x2014;as suggested by a small number of industry commenters&#x2014;would add complexity which would likely outweigh the benefits of the flexibility that some complying parties might gain from this approach. The Bureau is concerned that this approach to the effective date would lead to unnecessary dispersion of compliance dates over a ten-day period in early 2014, which in turn would be difficult to track by examiners and enforcing parties, and potentially raise other legal and operational questions. It could potentially lead to gaps in recordkeeping as well. Even further confusion could result due to the continued effect of the current compensation rules for an additional nine-day period. The Bureau also notes that the weight of comments it received on the proposed effective date changes supported a mandatory compliance date of January 1, 2014.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Effective Dates for Amendments to or Additions of &#xA7; 1026.36(a), (b), (e), (f), (g), and (j)</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>Rather than implementing the proposed change in effective dates for &#xA7; 1026.36(d) in isolation, the Bureau also proposed to make the amendments to or additions of (as applicable) &#xA7; 1026.36(a) (definitions), &#xA7; 1026.36(b) (scope), &#xA7; 1026.36(e) (anti-steering), &#xA7; 1026.36(f) (qualifications) and &#xA7; 1026.36(j) (compliance policies and procedures for depository institutions) (and associated commentary) contained in the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule take effect on January 1, 2014. The Bureau proposed not to tie the effective date to the receipt of a particular loan application, but rather to a date certain. Because these provisions rely on a common set of definitions and in some cases cross-reference each other,<SU>20</SU>
            <FTREF/>the Bureau proposed to make them effective on January 1, 2014, and without reference to receipt of applications to avoid a potential incongruity among the effective dates of the substantive provisions and the effective dates of the regulatory definitions and scope provisions supporting those substantive provisions. In the proposal, the Bureau stated that it believes this proposed approach would facilitate compliance.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>20</SU>For example, &#xA7; 1026.36(j) requires that depository institutions establish written policies and procedures reasonably designed to ensure and monitor compliance with &#xA7; 1026.36(d), (e), (f), and (g).</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>The Bureau did not, however, propose to adjust the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(g) (and associated commentary), which requires that loan originators' names and identifier numbers be provided on certain loan documentation, except to clarify and confirm that the provision takes effect with regard to any application received on or after January 10, 2014, by a creditor or a loan originator organization. Because this provision requires modifications to documentation for individual loans and the systems that generate such documentation, the Bureau stated in the<PRTPAGE P="60390"/>proposal that it believes it is appropriate to have this provision take effect with the other 2013 Title XIV Final Rules that affect individual loan processing.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>As noted above, the commenters that addressed the proposed changes to the effective dates for the provisions of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule generally expressed support for the proposed changes. In nearly all cases, these comments did not discuss the application of the effective date to specific provisions within &#xA7; 1026.36, other than the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d). One national trade association that requested an optional compliance date of January 1, 2014, for the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) noted that, if the Bureau were to adopt a mandatory compliance date of January 1, 2014, it nonetheless agreed with the proposal to keep the effective date for the provisions of &#xA7; 1026.36(g) as January 10, 2014. The association stated that systems changes to revise loan documents scheduled to take effect on January 10 should not be made costlier or less convenient as a result of the Bureau's changes to the effective date provisions.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>

          <P>The Bureau is finalizing the effective date for the amendments to or additions of &#xA7; 1026.36(a), (b), (e), (f), (g), and (j) (and associated commentary) contained in the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule and the proposed amendments and additions thereto in the June 2013 proposal, as proposed. Therefore: (1) The effective date for the amendments to or additions of &#xA7; 1026.36(a), (b), (e), (f), and (j) as finalized in this rule will be January 1, 2014 (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>a date certain that is not tied to a triggering event, such as receipt of an application on or after that date); and (2) the effective date for the addition of &#xA7; 1026.36(g) will be January 10, 2014, and that section therefore will apply to all transactions for which the creditor or loan originator organization received an application on or after that date.<SU>21</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>21</SU>While a depository institution must have its policies and procedures under &#xA7; 1026.36(j) in place by January 1, 2014, including policies and procedures covering &#xA7; 1026.36(g), the depository institution is, of course, not required to ensure and monitor compliance with &#xA7; 1026.36(g) until January 10, 2014, the effective date of &#xA7; 1026.36(g).</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>While the Bureau is not changing the effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(g), it has become aware that some uncertainty exists with respect to the application of this provision where more than one loan originator organization is involved in originating the same transaction (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>a mortgage broker and a creditor performing origination services with respect to the same transaction). The Bureau understands that some loan originator organizations are planning to comply by including the name and Nationwide Mortgage Licensing System and Registry (NMLSR) ID (where the NMLSR has provided one) for<E T="03">multiple</E>loan originator organizations involved in originating the transaction on the loan documents, while others are planning to comply by including the name and NMLSR ID (where the NMLSR has provided one) for just<E T="03">one</E>of the loan originator organizations involved in originating the transaction on the loan documents. The Bureau believes that either approach complies with the rule in its current form. However, the Bureau is considering proposing to clarify at some point in the future that the name and NMLSR ID (where the NMLSR has provided one) for<E T="03">multiple</E>loan originator organizations involved in originating the transaction must be included on the loan documents. If the Bureau ultimately adopts such a clarification, it will provide adequate time for compliance.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Effective Date for &#xA7; 1026.36(i)</HD>
          <P>As discussed in the 2013 Effective Date Final Rule and below, the Bureau initially adopted a June 1, 2013 effective date for &#xA7; 1026.36(i), but later delayed the provision's effective date to January 10, 2014, while the Bureau considered addressing interpretive questions concerning the provision's applicability to transactions other than those in which a lump-sum premium is added to the loan amount at consummation. The Bureau sought comment on whether the January 10, 2014 effective date would be appropriate in light of the proposed changes, or whether an earlier effective date could be set that permits sufficient time for creditors to adjust their insurance premium practices as necessary. The Bureau received comments from trade associations, the credit insurance industry, credit unions and other financial institutions, as well as consumer groups, which addressed the proposed effective date. Industry commenters and trade associations strongly preferred the January 10th date to an earlier date, and stated that system adjustments will be required to implement the final rule. However, these commenters generally supported the January 10, 2014 effective date as reasonable, so long as the final rule does not materially differ from the proposal. Consumer groups suggested that the Bureau set the effective date at January 1, 2014, noting that the consumer benefit derived from the provision has already been delayed from its original effective date of June 1, 2013.</P>
          <P>As discussed in the section-by-section analysis below, the Bureau is adopting amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(i) substantially as proposed, with some additional clarifications. The Bureau believes that creditors will need time to adjust certain credit insurance premium billing practices to account for the final rule, but believes that the January 10, 2014 effective date adopted in the 2013 Effective Date Final Rule will allow sufficient time for compliance. This approach is consistent with comments from industry and trade associations, as well as the generally applicable effective date for the 2013 Title XIV Final Rules, including for several provisions the Bureau is amending through this notice.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">VI. Section-by-Section Analysis</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Regulation Z</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">General&#x2014;Technical Corrections</HD>
          <P>In addition to the clarifications and amendments to Regulation Z discussed below, the Bureau proposed technical corrections and minor clarifications to wording throughout Regulation Z that are not substantive in nature. The Bureau is adopting such technical and wording clarifications as proposed to regulatory text in &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.23, 1026.31, 1026.32, 1026.35, and 1026.36 and to commentary to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.25, 1026.32, 1026.34, 1026.36, and 1026.41. In addition, the Bureau is adding additional technical corrections to regulation text in &#xA7; 1026.43 and commentary to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.25, 1026.32, and 1026.43. The Bureau also is making one correction to an amendatory instruction that relates to FR Doc. 2013-16962, published on Wednesday July 24, 2013.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Section 1026.35Requirements for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">35(b) Escrow Accounts</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">35(b)(2) Exemptions</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">35(b)(2)(iii)</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">35(b)(2)(iii)(A)</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>In addition to the HOEPA and ATR balloon provisions discussed above, the definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; also relate to the &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) exemption from the requirement that creditors establish escrow accounts for certain higher-priced mortgage loans available to small creditors that operate predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas. The exemption in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) was designed to promote access to credit by exempting small creditors in rural or underserved areas that might have sufficient difficulty maintaining escrow accounts that they would curtail making higher-priced mortgage loans rather than trigger the escrow account requirement. As adopted in the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, and as amended by the May 2013 Escrows Final Rule,<SU>34</SU>
            <FTREF/>the exemption is available to creditors that extended more than 50 percent of their total covered transactions secured by a first lien on properties that are located in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during the preceding calendar year. In general, a county's status as &#x201C;rural&#x201D; is defined in relation to Urban Influence Codes (UICs) established by the United States Department of Agriculture's Economic Research Service.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>34</SU>78 FR 30739 (May 23, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>Because of updated information from the 2010 Census, however, numerous counties' status under the Bureau's definition will change between 2013 and 2014, with a small number of new counties meeting the definition of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and approximately 82 counties no longer meeting that definition. The Bureau estimates that approximately 200-300 otherwise eligible creditors during 2013 could lose their eligibility for 2014 solely because of changes in the status of the counties in which they operate (assuming the geographical distribution of their mortgage originations does not change significantly over the relevant period).<SU>35</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>35</SU>The extent of such volatility in the transition from 2012 rural/non-rural status (for purposes of eligibility for the exemption during 2013) to 2013 rural/non-rural status (for purposes of eligibility for the exemption during 2014) is likely far greater than during other year-to-year transitions. This is due to the fact that this first year-to-year transition under the Bureau's &#x201C;rural&#x201D; definition happens to coincide with the redesignation by the USDA's Economic Research Service of U.S. counties' urban influence codes, on which the &#x201C;rural&#x201D; definition is generally based. This redesignation occurs only decennially, based on the most recent census data. Nevertheless, for purposes of eligibility for the exemption during 2013 and 2014, the volatility is significant&#x2014;just as creditors are first attempting to apply the exemption's criteria.</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>In light of the Bureau's intent to review whether the definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; should be adjusted further during the two-year transition period for balloon-payment mortgages discussed above, the Bureau proposed to revise the exemption provided by &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) to the general requirement that creditors establish an escrow account for first lien higher-priced mortgage loans where a small creditor operates predominantly in rural or underserved areas and meets various other criteria. The proposal would have revised &#xA7; 1026.35(b) and its commentary to minimize volatility in the definitions while they are being re-evaluated. The proposal also would have amended &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) and its commentary to conform to the expansion of the exemption to creditors that may meet the &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) criteria for calendar year 2014 based on loans made in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties in calendar year 2011, but not 2012 or 2013.</P>
          <P>The Bureau sought comment on these proposed amendments and also proposed an effective date for the amendments that would apply to transactions where applications were received on or after January 1, 2014, in light of the proposed change to the calendar year exemption under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii).</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received substantial comments from trade associations, credit unions, and other industry advocates supporting the proposed amendments. Many of the comments relating to the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(A) discussed above also discussed the amendments to &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) and offered similar or identical comments commending the Bureau for facilitating compliance with the requirements adopted by the 2013 Escrow Final Rule, particularly in light of changes to &#x201C;rural&#x201D; status for certain counties based on the last available Census data that would have caused certain creditors to lose eligibility for the exemption. The same housing counseling organization that disagreed with the balloon exception adopted by the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule also disagreed with the original exemption from the escrows requirement and thus also the proposed expansion. As before, this commenter did not raise any specific issues related to the proposal, but rather stated that all higher-priced mortgage loans should be escrowed, without exception. As discussed in part V above, while nearly all comments supported the proposal in general, no comments expressly addressed the January 1, 2014 effective date.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>The Bureau is adopting revised &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) as proposed. The amended provision provides that, to qualify for the exemption, a creditor must have extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions secured by a first lien on properties located in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during any of the preceding three calendar years. The provision thus prevents a creditor from losing eligibility for the exemption under the &#x201C;rural or underserved&#x201D; element of the test unless it has failed to exceed the 50-percent threshold three years in a row.</P>
          <P>As discussed above in the section-by-section analysis of &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C), the Bureau also is modifying the exception from the prohibition on balloon payments for high-cost mortgages in that section. Section 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) provides an exception to the general prohibition on balloon payments for high-cost mortgages for balloon-payment qualified mortgages made by certain creditors operating predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas. Believing that the same rationale for allowing balloon-payment qualified mortgages made by creditors in rural or underserved areas applies to high-cost mortgages, the Bureau adopted the &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) exception in the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule. As explained above, the Bureau believes the same underlying rationale for the two-year transition period for balloon-payment qualified mortgages described above applies equally to the &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) exception from the high-cost mortgage balloon prohibition. Accordingly, the Bureau believes it is appropriate to extend this temporary framework to &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) and therefore is amending &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C) to include loans meeting the criteria under &#xA7; 1026.43(e)(6). Thus, for both balloon-payment qualified mortgages and for the high-cost mortgage balloon prohibition, the Bureau has adopted a two-year transition period during which the special treatment of balloon-payment loans does not depend on the creditor operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas.</P>

          <P>The Bureau considered taking the same approach with regard to the<PRTPAGE P="60416"/>escrow requirement but concluded ultimately that a smaller adjustment was appropriate. Because higher-priced mortgage loans are already subject to an escrow requirement, all creditors are currently required to maintain escrow accounts for such loans. Implementation of the amendments to the exemption will thus reduce burden for some creditors, but does not impose different requirements than the status quo except as to the length of time that an escrow account must be maintained. This is fundamentally different than the ability-to-repay and high-cost mortgage requirements, which would prohibit new balloon-payment loans from being accorded qualified mortgage status or from being made going forward absent implementation of the special exemptions. In addition, the Bureau may change the definitions of rural or underserved areas as the result of its re-examination process but does not anticipate lifting the requirement that creditors operate predominantly in rural or underserved areas to qualify for the exemption because Congress specifically contemplated that limitation on the escrows exemption. Accordingly, the Bureau believes it is appropriate to leave the definition in place, but to prevent volatility in the definition from negatively affecting creditors while the Bureau re-evaluates the underlying definitions. The Bureau believes that, as with the two balloon-payment provisions for which the Bureau believes two-year transition periods are appropriate, this amendment will benefit consumers by expanding access to credit in certain areas that met the definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; at some time in the preceding three calendar years and also will facilitate compliance for creditors that make these loans. The Bureau also believes that the amendment will promote additional consistency between the regulatory provisions adopted by the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, the 2013 ATR Final Rule, and the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, thereby facilitating compliance for affected creditors.</P>
          <P>The Bureau notes that the mechanics of &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) differ slightly from the express transition period ending on January 10, 2016, under &#xA7; 1026.43(e)(6). Thus, this amendment does not parallel the same transition period precisely, as does revised &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C), which simply incorporates &#xA7; 1026.43(e)(6)'s conditions by cross-reference. Instead, revised &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(A) approximates a two-year transition period by extending from one to three years the time for which a creditor, once eligible for the exemption, cannot lose that eligibility because of changes in the rural (or underserved) status of the counties in which the creditor operates. Because the 2013 Escrows Final Rule took effect on June 1, 2013, the escrows provisions already have begun operating over seven months earlier than the provisions adopted by the 2013 HOEPA and ATR Final Rules (which take effect on January 10, 2014). Thus, whereas the two balloon-payment provisions specifically last through January 10, 2016, the escrows-requirement exemption will guarantee eligibility (for a creditor that is eligible during 2013 with respect to operating predominantly in rural or underserved areas, and meets the other applicable criteria) through 2015. Thus, the revised &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) exemption will approximately, though not exactly, track the extension of the balloon exemption for qualified mortgages under &#xA7; 1026.43(e)(6), and the extension of the HOEPA balloon exemption under revised &#xA7; 1026.32(d)(1)(ii)(C).</P>

          <P>In addition to the changes discussed above, the Bureau also is amending &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) and its commentary to conform to the expansion of the exemption to creditors that may meet the section 35(b)(2)(iii)(A) criteria for calendar year 2014 based on loans made in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties in calendar year 2011, but not 2012 or 2013. Section &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) currently prohibits any creditor from availing itself of the exemption if it maintains escrow accounts for any extensions of consumer credit secured by real property or a dwelling that it or its affiliate currently service, unless the escrow accounts were established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013, or were established after consummation as an accommodation for distressed consumers. With respect to loans where escrows were established on or after April 1, 2010, and before June 1, 2013, the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Escrows Final Rule explained that the Bureau believes creditors should not be penalized for compliance with the then current regulation, which would have required any such loans to be escrowed after April 1, 2010, and prior to June 1, 2013&#x2014;the date the exemption took effect. The Bureau understands that creditors that did not make more than 50 percent of their first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties in calendar year 2012 would have been ineligible for the exemption for calendar year 2013, and thus would have been required under &#xA7; 1026.35(a) to establish escrow accounts for any higher-priced mortgage loans those creditors made after June 1, 2013. However, it is possible in light of the amendments the Bureau is adopting that some of these same creditors may have met this criteria during calendar year 2011&#x2014;and thus, because the Bureau is finalizing the proposal and allowing creditors to qualify for the exemption (assuming they satisfy the other conditions set forth in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(B), (C), and (D))&#x2014;such creditors will qualify for the exemption in 2014. However, absent additional clarification, there would be one barrier: For applications received on or after June 1, 2013, but before the date the proposed amendment takes effect (as proposed, January 1, 2014), such a creditor that made a first-lien higher-priced mortgage loan would have been required to escrow for that loan, and thus would be deemed ineligible under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D). The Bureau does not believe that such creditors should lose the exemption because they were ineligible prior to the proposed amendment taking effect and thus made loans with escrows from June 1, 2013, through December 31, 2013. As the Bureau discussed in the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Escrows Final Rule, the Bureau believes creditors should not be penalized for compliance with the current regulation. The Bureau thus believes it is appropriate to amend &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) and comment 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>)-1.iv to exclude escrow accounts established after April 1, 2010 and before January 1, 2014.</P>

          <P>In addition, the Bureau is revising comment 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>)-1.iv to clarify that the date ranges provided in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) apply to transactions for which creditors received applications on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014. As discussed above, the Bureau believes such creditors should still qualify for the exemption provided under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions for which they received applications on or after January 1, 2014, other than those described in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">2</E>), and they otherwise qualify under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii). The Bureau believes this clarification reflects both the manner in which the 2013 Escrows Rule originally applied to transactions and the applicability of this final rule.<PRTPAGE P="60417"/>
          </P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Section 1026.36Loan Originator Compensation</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(a) Definitions</HD>
          <P>Section 1026.36(a) defines the term &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36 as a person<SU>36</SU>
            <FTREF/>who, for or in expectation of direct or indirect compensation or other monetary gain, engages in a defined set of activities or services (unless otherwise excluded). Section 1026.36(a) describes these activities broadly to include any such person who &#x201C;takes an application, offers, arranges, assists a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain, negotiates, or otherwise obtains or makes an extension of consumer credit for another person; or through advertising or other means of communication represents to the public that such person can or will perform any of these activities.&#x201D; Commentary to &#xA7; 1026.36(a) further describes and provides illustrations of these activities, including how the practice of &#x201C;referring&#x201D; consumers to creditors or loan originators, may affect one's status under the section.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>36</SU>&#x201C;Person&#x201D; is defined in &#xA7; 1026.2(a)(22) to mean, &#x201C;a natural person or an organization, including a corporation, partnership, proprietorship, association, cooperative, estate, trust, or government unit.&#x201D;</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>Following publication of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, the Bureau received numerous inquiries from industry regarding the activities that, if done for compensation or gain, would cause a person to be classified as a &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; under &#xA7; 1026.36. As discussed below, many of these inquiries sought clarification regarding specific terms used throughout the section, such as &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; or guidance on how the provision may apply to certain loan originator or creditor employees, agents or contractors such as tellers and greeters, as well as other interpretive questions. In response, the Bureau proposed several amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(a) and associated commentary adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule to resolve inconsistencies in wording, to conform the comments to the intended operation of the regulation text, and to address issues raised during the regulatory implementation process. The Bureau proposed these changes pursuant to its TILA section 105(a) and Dodd-Frank Act section 1022(b)(1) authority. As discussed below, the Bureau is adopting most of these amendments as proposed with some revisions and additional clarifying amendments.</P>

          <P>The Bureau also proposed to revise comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B to clarify those provisions' application to loan originator or creditor agents and contractors as well as employees. The Bureau is not adopting this aspect of the proposal. As discussed below, comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B illustrate two situations where an employee of a creditor or loan originator is conducting &#x201C;in house&#x201D; activity for his or her employer that is not considered to be &#x201C;referring&#x201D;: (1) Handing applications from the employer to a consumer; and (2) providing loan originator or creditor contact information for the loan originator or creditor entity for which the person works, or a person that works for the same entity. The Bureau proposed to clarify that comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B may be available to certain persons who work for creditors or loan originators, but may not technically be &#x201C;employed&#x201D; by the loan originator or creditor organization&#x2014;<E T="03">i.e.,</E>contract employees, temporary employees, interns, or other persons who may be working on a voluntary basis or being paid by another entity. However, upon further consideration, the Bureau believes the terms &#x201C;agent&#x201D; and &#x201C;contractor&#x201D; could be interpreted more broadly than the Bureau intended to include independent contractors or agents used by loan originators or creditors to refer customers to that loan originator or creditor. The Bureau did not intend these provisions to be applied this broadly, and also is concerned that such a reading could be inconsistent with other applicable laws, such as RESPA's prohibition on referral fees for federally related mortgages. Accordingly, the Bureau is limiting the scope of this comment to employees of loan originators or creditors.</P>
          <P>The Bureau notes, however, that this does not mean these provisions may never be available to certain persons who may possibly be considered agents or contractors, such as temps or contract employees. While these provisions are limited to employees of creditors or loan originators, &#xA7; 1026.2(b)(3) states that any terms not defined by Regulation Z is given the meanings given to them by State law or contract. The Bureau believes the term &#x201C;employee&#x201D;&#x2014;which is not defined under Regulation Z&#x2014;is commonly defined under State law as well as employment contracts, and may extend to such persons in appropriate circumstances.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">A. References to Credit Terms</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>The Bureau proposed to amend &#xA7; 1026.36(a) and its commentary to clarify the meaning of &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; which is used in defining some of the exclusions to the general definition of &#x201C;loan originator,&#x201D; thereby further delineating the general definition. For example, as adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) allows persons who act as assistants to loan originators to perform clerical or administrative tasks on a loan originator's behalf without becoming loan originators themselves. To be eligible for the exclusion, however, the person must not, among other things, offer or negotiate &#x201C;credit terms available from a creditor.&#x201D;</P>
          <P>Similarly, comment 36(a)-4.i. explains when providing a consumer with a credit application, an activity that would otherwise be a referral, does not cause a person to be classified as a loan originator. This comment provides an exception to certain persons who, among other things, do not discuss &#x201C;specific credit terms or products available from a creditor with the consumer.&#x201D;</P>

          <P>In addition, comment 36(a)-4.ii.B explains when a loan originator's or creditor's employee, such as a teller or greeter, may engage in providing loan originator contact information to consumers, an activity that would otherwise be a referral, without being classified as a loan originator. This comment provides that the definition of loan originator does not include a creditor's or loan originator's employee who provides loan originator or creditor contact information to a consumer, provided the employee does not, among other things, &#x201C;discuss particular credit terms available from a creditor.&#x201D;<E T="03">See also</E>&#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) and comments 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">2</E>through-1.i.A.<E T="03">4</E>(other similar references to credit terms). This exclusion also assists in defining persons who are loan originators in the sense that it implies persons who do discuss specific or particular credit terms, as this activity is further clarified in this rule, would be included in the definition.</P>

          <P>Following publication of the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, the Bureau received numerous inquiries from loan originators and creditors seeking guidance on the meaning of &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; in these various contexts. In light of these inquiries, the Bureau was concerned that the term &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; could have been construed too broadly and in a manner that could render any person that provides such general information a loan originator, which was not the Bureau's intent. Rather, the Bureau generally intended the references to &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; throughout &#xA7; 1026.36(a) to refer to particular credit terms that<PRTPAGE P="60418"/>are or may be made available<E T="03">to the consumer</E>selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics. Distinct from such particular credit terms are general credit terms that a loan originator or creditor makes available and advertises to the public at large, such as where such person merely states: &#x201C;We offer rates as low as 3% to qualified consumers.&#x201D;</P>
          <P>To address these questions, the Bureau proposed to clarify usage of the term &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; throughout the section in several ways. First, the Bureau noted that the definition of &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; which explains the term includes rate, fees, and other costs, had been provided only by a parenthetical clause in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) (a single exclusion that relates to retailers of manufactured homes) rather than in a separate, definitional provision. Thus, the definition appears to be limited to that single provision, even though the term is used in multiple places throughout &#xA7; 1026.36(a). For clarification purposes, the Bureau proposed to move this definition from &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), to new &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(6), which explicitly makes the definition applicable to the entire section. The Bureau solicited comment on whether additional guidance concerning the meaning of particular credit terms that are or may be made available to the consumer in light of the consumer's financial characteristics is necessary, and if so, what clarifications would be helpful.</P>
          <P>Second, the Bureau proposed to revise &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and (B), and comments 36(a)-1 and -4 to address inconsistencies regarding the meaning of &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; and to clarify that an activity involving credit terms for purposes of determining when a person is a loan originator must relate to &#x201C;particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics,&#x201D; not credit terms generally. The proposal would have clarified that a person who discusses with a consumer that, based on the consumer's financial characteristics, a creditor should be able to offer the consumer an interest rate of 3%, would be considered a loan originator. However, a person who merely states general information such as &#x201C;we offer rates as low as 3% to qualified consumers&#x201D; would not have been considered a loan originator because the person is not offering particular credit terms that are or may be available to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received comments from trade associations, industry, and consumer groups that addressed this clarification. Most commenters generally supported the proposed clarification that &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; refers to &#x201C;credit terms that are or may be made available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics,&#x201D; as well as the proposed explanation that &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; includes rates, fees, and other costs. Some commenters requested additional clarification regarding the meaning and application of &#x201C;the consumer's financial characteristics.&#x201D; A few industry commenters suggested that &#x201C;financial characteristics&#x201D; be limited to traditional factors that influence a credit decision, such as income and credit score. These commenters also asked the Bureau to clarify that an assessment of a consumer's financial characteristics does not include a person simply having general knowledge of the consumer's account or finances, but requires an actual assessment of the consumer's financial characteristics that form the basis for selection of credit terms. Consumer groups generally supported the clarification, but suggested that an assessment of a consumer's financial characteristics should include steering based on other factors such as race, ethnicity, or zip code.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>The Bureau is adopting the clarifications to references to &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and comments 36(a)-1 and -4 as proposed, and new &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(6) (which states the definition of &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; for purposes of the section) as proposed with an additional clarification. In response to public comments requesting additional clarification, the Bureau is modifying proposed &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(6) to clarify that credit terms are selected based on a consumer's financial characteristics when those terms are selected based on factors that may influence a credit decision, such as the consumer's debts, income, assets, or credit history. The Bureau intends this language to capture situations where credit terms are offered or discussed as available or potentially available to a consumer based on that consumer's ability to obtain such credit. This would include examining the consumer's credit history (which could include a credit score), income, debts, or assets and then selecting credit terms that are either available or potentially available to the consumer based on those factors. The Bureau does not intend this language to cover situations where, for example, an employee of a loan originator or creditor may be aware of a consumer's assets, income, or other factors but does not select credit terms based on those factors.</P>

          <P>The Bureau is not providing additional commentary to address potential referral concerns based on race, gender, ethnicity, or other non-financial factors. The Bureau intends this provision only to provide clarification on when a person may be considered a &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; by discussing credit terms&#x2014;<E T="03">i.e.,</E>when the terms have been selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics. To the extent that inappropriate non-financial characteristics such as race, gender, or ethnicity may factor into the selection of credit terms, the Bureau believes such situations would be addressed by other applicable laws such as ECOA and the Fair Housing Act. In any event, the Bureau did not intend this clarification to define the appropriate means of evaluating consumers for credit; rather it only intended to clarify when a person may be considered a loan originator by virtue of discussing credit terms with a consumer. The Bureau believes these changes better align the scope of the loan originator definition with the intended scope of &#xA7; 1026.36.</P>
          <P>Finally, as explained below in the section that discusses applicability of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1) to employees of manufactured home retailers, the Bureau is not adopting the proposed clarification to &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) except for removing the parenthetical reference defining credit terms.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">B. Application-Related Administrative and Clerical Tasks</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>

          <P>Comment 36(a)-4 and its subparts explain certain activities that, for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36(a), do not constitute &#x201C;referring&#x201D; as defined in comment 36(a)-1, when done (in the absence of other loan originator activities defined in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)) by certain managers, administrative or clerical staff, or similar employees of a loan originator or creditor. One such comment, 36(a)-4.i, provides guidance regarding when such persons engage in application-related administrative and clerical tasks. Specifically, this comment provides that persons do not act as loan originators when they (1) at the request of the consumer, provide an application form to the consumer; (2) accept a completed application form from the consumer; or (3) without assisting the consumer in completing<PRTPAGE P="60419"/>the application, processing or analyzing the information, or discussing specific credit terms or products available from a creditor with the consumer, deliver the application to a loan originator or creditor.</P>
          <P>After publication of the final rule, the Bureau received inquiries regarding the scope of this comment, specifically if the Bureau intended this comment to allow such persons only to provide applications from the entity for which they work to consumers without that constituting a &#x201C;referral,&#x201D; or if the exception is broader and would allow any such person to influence consumers' decisions and refer them to a particular creditor or set of creditors without being considered loan originators. The Bureau proposed revisions to comment 36(a)-4.i to clarify when providing a consumer with a credit application amounts to acting as a loan originator, as opposed to falling under the exclusion provided in comment 36(a)-4.i for application-related administrative and clerical tasks. Specifically, the Bureau proposed to revise this comment to clarify that the exclusion only extends to a loan originator or creditor employee (or agent or contractor) that provides a credit application form from the entity for which the person works to the consumer for the consumer to complete.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received a number of comments from industry and trade associations that supported these clarifications. Most of these comments did not identify any additional need for clarification or suggestions. The Bureau also received a few comments from the manufactured housing industry, which are addressed separately in the discussion of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) below.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>For the reasons discussed above, the Bureau is adopting comment 36(a)-4.i mostly as proposed, with some conforming changes for purposes of consistency with comment 36(a)-4.ii.B. While generally any person, including a loan originator employee would be acting as a loan originator for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1) if he or she refers consumers to a particular creditor by providing an application from that creditor, the Bureau does not believe that a loan originator or creditor employee should be considered a loan originator for simply providing an application from the loan originator or creditor entity for which he or she works. The Bureau believes that, in such a case, provided that the person does not assist the consumer in completing the application or otherwise influence his or her decision, the person is performing an administrative task on behalf of the entity for which he or she works. Thus, in the Bureau's view, there would be little appreciable benefit for consumers for the rule to regard such persons as loan originators.</P>
          <P>Also, as discussed below with respect to employees who provide creditor or loan originator contact information under comment 36(a)-4.ii.B, the Bureau believes ambiguity regarding the meaning of &#x201C;in response to a consumer's request&#x201D;&#x2014;a factor included in both comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B&#x2014;could cause unnecessary compliance challenges. Moreover, the Bureau notes that classifying such individuals as loan originators for providing an application without first waiting for an express request from the consumer would subject them to the requirements applicable to loan originators. Again, in the Bureau's view, there would be little appreciable benefit for consumers for the rule to regard such persons as loan originators where the person is simply providing a credit application from the entity for whom the person works. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting comment 36(a)-4.i as proposed, including removing the condition that the provision of the application must be &#x201C;at the request of the consumer&#x201D; and making a conforming change to the comment to only apply to employees of the loan originator or creditor, not all persons. However, the Bureau is making some wording changes for purposes of consistency with comment 36(a)-4.ii.B. The Bureau also is removing a reference to &#x201C;credit products&#x201D; which also is inconsistent with comment 36(a)-4.ii.B. The Bureau believes in both instances the rule should consider employees to be loan originators when such persons discuss credit terms that are or may be made available by a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, not when they simply discuss particular categories of credit products generally, such as mortgages or home equity loans. Also as discussed above, the Bureau is not adopting proposed language that expressly would have extended this comment to agents or contractors of loan originators or creditors.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">C. Responding to Consumer Inquiries and Providing General Information</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Employees of a Creditor or Loan Originator Who Provide Loan Originator or Creditor Contact Information</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>Comment 36(a)-4.ii.B provides that the definition of loan originator does not include persons who, as employees of a creditor or loan originator, provide loan originator or creditor contact information to a consumer in response to the consumer's request, provided that the employee does not discuss particular credit terms available from a creditor and does not direct the consumer, based on the employee's assessment of the consumer's financial characteristics, to a particular loan originator or creditor seeking to originate particular credit transactions to consumers with those financial characteristics. Prior to issuing the proposal, the Bureau received many inquiries on this topic from stakeholders expressing concern that, absent a clarifying amendment, the rule could be interpreted to require tellers, greeters, or other such employees to be classified as loan originators for merely providing contact information to a consumer who did not clearly or explicitly ask for it. Stakeholders further asserted that such persons should not be considered loan originators when their conduct is limited to following a script prompting them to ask whether the consumer is interested in a mortgage loan and the tellers are not able to engage in any independent assessment of the consumer. Moreover, stakeholders have asserted it would be very costly to implement the training and certification requirements under Regulation Z as amended by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule for employers with large numbers of administrative staff who interact with consumers on a day-to-day basis in the manner described.</P>
          <P>The proposal would have addressed these concerns by removing the requirement that creditor or loan originator contact information must be provided &#x201C;in response to the consumer's request&#x201D; for the exclusion to apply. In addition, and similar to the clarifications regarding credit terms discussed above, the Bureau also proposed to clarify that comment 36(a)-4.ii.B applies to loan originator or creditor agents and contractors as well as employees.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>

          <P>The Bureau received substantial comments from trade associations and<PRTPAGE P="60420"/>industry, including credit unions and other small creditors, supporting the proposal. Consumer advocates also generally supported the proposal and did not raise specific objections to the revised comment. As discussed above, some consumer advocates and trade associations asked for additional clarification on what constitutes an &#x201C;assessment of a consumer's financial characteristics,&#x201D; but most comments did not make specific suggestions other than to note that they support the proposal and welcome the change. The Bureau also received a few comments from the manufactured housing industry requesting additional clarification regarding how the proposed comment would apply to retailers, who, according to these commenters, may not be employees, agents, or contractors of a loan originator or creditor. Specifically, these commenters requested that the Bureau expressly include employees, agents, or contractors of manufactured housing retailers as covered by the provision, even if such person does not work for a loan originator or creditor, but provides loan originator contact information to consumers in the same manner described in the proposal.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>The Bureau is adopting comment 36(a)-4.ii.B as proposed with two modifications. First, as discussed above with respect to comment 36(a)-4.i, the Bureau is not adopting proposed language that would have extended the scope of the comment to agents or contractors of loan originators or creditors. Second, the Bureau is clarifying that the exclusion is only available to employees of a loan originator or creditor that provide the contact information of the loan originator or creditor entity for which he or she works, or of a person who works for that same entity. As proposed, the Bureau is removing the qualifying phrase &#x201C;in response to the consumer's request.&#x201D; The Bureau believes ambiguity regarding the meaning of &#x201C;in response to a consumer's request&#x201D; could have caused unnecessary compliance challenges. In such instances, the Bureau does not believe tellers or other such staff should be considered loan originators for merely providing loan originator or creditor contact information to the consumer (which would consist of such an employee directing a consumer to a loan originator who works for the same entity, or a creditor that is the same entity, as made explicit to conform the language in comments 4.i and 4.ii.B). The Bureau also notes that classifying such individuals as loan originators would subject them to the requirements applicable to loan originators with, in the Bureau's view, little appreciable benefit for consumers. However, the Bureau is retaining language, with some conforming changes, that would cover within the definition of &#x201C;loan originator&#x201D; any such employee of a creditor or loan originator organization who, in the course of providing loan originator or creditor contact information to the consumer, directs that consumer to a particular loan originator or particular creditor based on his or her assessment of the consumer's financial characteristics or discusses particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to the consumer selected based on consumer's financial characteristics. The Bureau believes these actions can influence the credit terms that the consumer ultimately obtains, and continues to believe these actions should result in application of the requirements imposed by the rule on loan originators. The Bureau believes this amendment should enable creditors and loan originators to implement the rule with respect to persons acting under the controlled circumstances specified by the comment while maintaining stronger protections in situations where significant steering could occur.</P>
          <P>As noted above, the Bureau is making one adjustment to the comment to clarify that the exclusion only is available to an employee of a loan originator or creditor who provides the contact information of the loan originator or creditor entity for which he or she works, or of a person who works for that same entity. The Bureau recognizes that the proposed amendments did not expressly limit the exclusion in this way. However, the Bureau intended that the exclusion be subject to this limitation and believes it was strongly implied, given that the language of the exclusion begins with the qualification that the definition of loan originator does not include persons who,&#x201D; as employees of a creditor or loan originator,&#x201D; engage in certain activities. The fact that the exclusion only applies to persons in their capacity as employees of creditors or loan originators signals that they are only providing loan originator or creditor contract information for the entity for which they work. The Bureau did not contemplate that such persons would provide contact information, as employees of a creditor or loan originator, to loan originators or creditors that were not their employers and no comments indicating a different understanding of this provision were received. However, to better clarify application of the provision, the Bureau is modifying comment 36(a)-4.ii.B to state that the exclusion only extends to employees providing the contact information of &#x201C;the entity for which he or she works or of a person who works for that same entity.&#x201D; The Bureau believes this will eliminate any ambiguity in the proposed comment that may have led such employees to believe the exclusion would extend to providing contact information for loan originators or creditors outside the entity for which they work. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting this revised comment as proposed with this modification.</P>
          <P>Finally, as discussed in greater detail below in the section that addresses employees of manufactured housing retailers, the Bureau also received some comments that suggested manufactured housing retailer employees should be exempt from the loan originator definition altogether for &#x201C;referring,&#x201D; or otherwise should fall under this particular exclusion, regardless of whether they are employees, agents, or contractors of a loan originator or creditor. As discussed below in the discussion of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), the Bureau does not believe that any additional amendments to this comment are necessary that relate to manufactured housing retailer employees.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Describing Other Product-Related Service.</HD>

          <P>Comment 36(a)-4.ii.C provides that the definition of loan originator does not include persons who describe other product-related services. The Bureau proposed to amend this comment to provide examples of persons who describe other product-related services. The proposed new examples would have included persons who describe optional monthly payment methods via telephone or via automatic account withdrawals, the availability and features of online account access, the availability of 24-hour customer support, or free mobile applications to access account information. In addition, the proposed amendment to comment 36(a)-4.iii.C would have clarified that persons who perform the administrative task of coordinating the closing process are excluded, whereas persons who arrange credit transactions are not excluded. The Bureau received comments that generally supported the proposed clarifications, but did not receive comments specifically addressing this clarification in isolation. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting<PRTPAGE P="60421"/>revised comments 36(a)-4.ii.C and 36(a)-4.iii.C as proposed.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">3. Amounts for Charges for Services That Are Not Loan Origination Activities</HD>
          <P>Comment 36(a)-5.iv.B provides that compensation includes any salaries, commissions, and any financial or similar incentive, regardless of whether it is labeled as payment for services that are not loan origination activities. The Bureau proposed to revise this comment to provide that compensation includes any salaries, commissions, and any financial or similar incentive &#x201C;to an individual loan originator,&#x201D; regardless of whether it is labeled as payment for services that are not loan origination activities. The proposed wording change conforms this provision to the other provisions in comment 36(a)-5.iv that permit compensation paid to a loan originator organization under certain circumstances for services it performs that are not loan originator activities. The Bureau received comments that generally supported the proposed clarifications, but did not receive comments specifically addressing this clarification in isolation. Accordingly, the Bureau is adopting revised comment 36(a)-5 as proposed.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">D. Clarification of Exclusion for Employees of Retailers of Manufactured Homes</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>As discussed above, the Bureau proposed to revise both &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) to address several inconsistencies regarding the meaning of &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; and to clarify that any such activity must relate to &#x201C;particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics,&#x201D; not credit terms generally. The proposed rule preamble also provided examples of how the proposed revisions to comment 36(a)-4.i would affect such employees of manufactured home retailers. As a result of these proposed revisions, employees (or agents or contractors) of manufactured home retailers who provide a credit application form from one particular creditor or loan originator organization that is not the entity for which they work would not have qualified for the exclusions in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) or &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) and comment 36(a)-4.i. would not apply. In contrast, an employee of a manufactured home retailer who simply provides a credit application form from one particular creditor or loan originator organization that is his or her employer potentially would have been eligible for the exclusions in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(B) and comment 36(a)-4.i potentially would have applied. An agent or contractor of a manufactured home retailer who simply provides a credit application form from one particular creditor or loan originator organization it works for as agent or contractor potentially would have been eligible for the exclusion in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and comment 36(a)-4.i. potentially would have applied. The proposed revisions also would have clarified that comment 36(a)-4.i. would apply to someone who merely delivers a completed credit application form from the consumer to a creditor or loan originator if other conditions are met, but would have removed language that could have been misinterpreted to suggest that comment 36(a)-4.i. would apply to someone who accepts an application in the sense of taking or helping the consumer complete an application could be eligible for the exclusion.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received comments from the manufactured housing industry that sought additional clarification on how the proposed amendments would apply to employees of manufactured housing retailers. Specifically, these comments relate to the illustrations of the proposed amendments the Bureau provided in the preamble indicating that comment 36(a)-4.i would only apply to manufactured housing retailer employees who also are employees (or agents or contractors) of the creditor or loan originator. Commenters expressed concern that manufactured housing retailer employees are typically not employees, agents, or contractors of a loan originator or creditor, and thus would only be able to take advantage of this particular exclusion in the case where the retailer itself provides financing or acts as the loan originator. These commenters suggested that retailer employees should be allowed to &#x201C;refer&#x201D; customers to particular loan originators or creditors other than the retailer itself without being considered loan originators, so long as the other conditions set forth in comment 36(a)-4.i are met. In addition, these commenters also suggested that their employees should not be covered by the loan originator rules at all to the extent that they do not receive compensation from any creditor for such activity. No other commenters focused on application of the rules to manufactured home retailer employees.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>As discussed below, the Bureau is adopting several clarifying amendments and additional commentary to address comments from the manufactured housing industry that questioned the applicability to manufactured home retailer employees of commentary that describes &#x201C;referral&#x201D; as loan originator activity and of various exclusions set forth in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A), &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), and discussed in comment 36(a)-4 and its subparts.</P>
          <P>
            <E T="03">Background.</E>As an initial interpretive matter, the Bureau believes it is helpful to outline the statutory provision implemented by &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), and how it relates to other provisions implemented by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. TILA section 103(cc)(2)(A) provides a three-part test for determining if a person is a loan originator, namely that, for or in expectation of direct or indirect compensation or gain, a person (1) Takes a mortgage application, (2) assists a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain a mortgage loan, or (3) offers or negotiates terms of a mortgage loan. The language of TILA section 103(cc) that defines a &#x201C;mortgage originator&#x201D; does not specifically include the term &#x201C;refer&#x201D; or its variants. However, the Bureau has interpreted both &#x201C;assists a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain a residential mortgage loan&#x201D; under section 103(cc)(2)(A)(ii) and &#x201C;offers&#x201D; under section 103(cc)(2)(A)(iii) to include a referral of a consumer to a loan originator or creditor.<SU>37</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>37</SU>
              <E T="03">See</E>78 FR at 11300, including footnote 62 (Supplemental Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, discussing &#x201C;offers&#x201D;).</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>This definition, which forms the basis for the definition of loan originator adopted in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i), applies generally to all persons, unless one of a limited number of exclusions applies. One such exclusion exists for manufactured home retailer employees in TILA section 103(cc)(2)(C)(ii), and provides that the second part of the three-part test described above&#x2014;assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain a mortgage loan&#x2014;does not render a retailer employee a loan originator provided the employee does not engage in either of the other two steps (taking an application or offering or negotiating terms) and also does not advise a consumer on loan terms (including rates, fees, and other costs). Thus, a retailer employee who merely assists without offering, negotiating, taking an application, or advising, is not a loan originator (while one who offers or negotiates, takes an<PRTPAGE P="60422"/>application, or advises on loan terms would be a loan originator).</P>
          <P>This statutory provision was implemented by &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), which is based on, and largely tracks, the statutory language. Consistent with this statutory structure, &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) provides an exclusion for &#x201C;An employee of a manufactured home retailer who does not take a consumer credit application, offer or negotiate credit terms available from a creditor, or advise a consumer on credit terms (including rates, fees, and other costs) available from a creditor.&#x201D; The effect of this exclusion is that retailer employees are loan originators if they do anything in the general, core definition in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i) other than &#x201C;assist&#x201D; in a manner that doesn't constitute taking, advising, offering or negotiating, or advising on credit terms. Because both &#x201C;assisting&#x201D; and &#x201C;offering&#x201D; include the activity of referring, a retailer employee who makes a referral is &#x201C;offering&#x201D; and therefore is a loan originator.<SU>38</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>

              <SU>38</SU>This aspect of the retailer employee exclusion was implemented by &#xA7; 1026.36(a) as adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, and explicitly addressed in the preamble to that rule, where the Bureau responded to similar comments from the manufactured housing industry. One of those comments asserted that, under the proposed exclusion for employees of a manufactured home retailer, employees could be compensated, in effect, for referring a consumer to a creditor without becoming a loan originator. The Bureau made clear that this was not a correct reading of the exclusion, and explained its basis for disagreeing.<E T="03">See</E>78 FR at 11305.</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>The Bureau believes these provisions make clear how employees of manufactured housing retailers fit within the &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i) definition of loan originator, including with respect to referrals as described in comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1.</E>The Bureau also provided some additional explanation in the Supplementary Information to the proposed rule, which sought to clarify further the application of comment 36(a)-4.i to such employees. However, the Bureau continues to receive inquiries from industry, including comments received in connection with the June 2013 Proposal, that indicate there is still substantial confusion regarding the application of these provisions and comments to employees of manufactured housing retailers. For this reason, the Bureau is adopting additional commentary to provide further guidance and codify explanations previously set forth in the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule and the June 2013 Proposal.</P>
          <P>
            <E T="03">Proposed amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B).</E>The Bureau is not adopting in this final rule proposed amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B) other than moving the definition of &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; to &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(6). As discussed above related to &#x201C;credit terms,&#x201D; the Bureau proposed to modify the reference to &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; in &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), as well as comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B, to be limited to &#x201C;credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics.&#x201D; As discussed above, the Bureau believes this limitation is appropriate in the context of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B. Each of these provisions addresses situations where employees of a loan originator or creditor may, absent exception, be considered loan originators for conducting activity within the entities for which they work. For example, &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) relates to persons who perform purely administrative or clerical tasks on behalf of a person who is classified as a loan originator or creditor, while comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B relate to determining whether an employee of a loan originator or creditor engages in &#x201C;referring&#x201D; by providing an application from the entity for which such person works, or providing loan originator or creditor contact information for a loan originator or creditor that is or works for the same entity. Each of these situations applies to persons who may be assisting loan originators within the same entity or otherwise technically &#x201C;referring&#x201D; consumers to loan originators or creditors that are or work for the same entity. However, upon further consideration the Bureau believes the limitation is not appropriate in the context of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), which states that a manufactured home retailer employee would not be considered a loan originator if that person does not, among other things, &#x201C;offer or negotiate credit terms&#x201D; or &#x201C;advise a consumer on credit terms.&#x201D; The limitation is only intended to apply in the context of an employee of a loan originator or creditor assisting a loan originator or making a referral to the loan originator or creditor entity for which such person works. To the extent a retailer of manufactured housing is also a loan originator or creditor, the exclusions under &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(A) and comments 36(a)-4.i and 36(a)-4.ii.B may be available for its employees. However, the limitation has no applicability outside of the loan originator or creditor employer/employee context and, accordingly, is not being included as the Bureau proposed in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B), which addresses a different employer/employee context.</P>
          <P>Accordingly, the Bureau is not adopting this proposed change to &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)(B).</P>
          <P>
            <E T="03">Referrals.</E>The Bureau is amending comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1</E>to explain further the underlying statutory and regulatory bases for including &#x201C;referrals&#x201D; as loan originator activity. As adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1</E>explains what actions constitute &#x201D; referring&#x201D; for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i), while comment 36(a)-4 and its subparts provide guidance on certain activities that do not constitute referring. The Bureau is amending this comment to explain that referring is an activity included under each of the activities of offering, arranging, or assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain an extension of credit. Accordingly, the Bureau believes this amendment makes clear that, while a referral may be considered &#x201C;assisting,&#x201D; it also falls within other statutory and regulatory categories of loan originator activity not excluded from the loan originator definition for manufactured housing retailer employees. The Bureau believes the discussion above and the conforming revision to comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1</E>better clarify what activities, when done by an employee of a retailer of manufactured homes, will cause such an employee to be classified as a loan originator for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36. The Bureau further notes this revision is consistent with the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, which provides an extensive discussion of the activities covered by TILA section 103(cc)(2)(A)(ii).<SU>39</SU>
            <FTREF/>As noted above in this preamble, the retailer employee exclusion allows such an employee to engage in &#x201C;assisting&#x201D; activities in a manner that doesn't constitute taking, advising, offering or negotiating, or advising on credit terms.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>39</SU>See 78 FR at 11301 through 11303.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>
            <E T="03">New commentary.</E>In addition, the Bureau is adding new commentary to provide further guidance on what activities may be considered &#x201C;assisting,&#x201D; but not other loan originator activities such as offering, arranging, or taking an application. In the Bureau's view, these activities, when engaged in by employees of manufactured housing retailers (in the absence of other activities), do not render such employees loan originators for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36. Accordingly, to provide greater clarity concerning the retailer employee exclusion consistent with these conclusions, a new comment<PRTPAGE P="60423"/>36(a)(1)(i)(B) is added by this final rule. The comment states that engaging in certain listed activities, as described below, does not make such an employee a loan originator.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is adding new comment 36(a)(1)(i)(B)-1.i to explain that a retailer employee may generally describe the credit application process to a consumer and that this activity, standing alone, would not cause the employee to be considered a loan originator.<SU>40</SU>
            <FTREF/>However, the retailer employee would be considered a loan originator if he or she advises on credit terms available from a creditor.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>40</SU>
              <E T="03">See</E>78 FR at 11302.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>The Bureau is adding new comment 36(a)(1)(i)(B)-1.ii to explain that a retailer employee may prepare residential mortgage loan packages without being considered a loan originator.<SU>41</SU>
            <FTREF/>Thus, a retailer employee may compile and process application materials and supporting documentation and, further consistent with the Final Rule, provide general application instruction to consumers so consumers can complete an application, but without interacting or communicating with the consumer regarding specific transaction terms.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>41</SU>
              <E T="03">See</E>TILA section 103(cc)(4) (definition of &#x201C;assists&#x201D;).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>The Bureau notes that this comment is consistent with the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, which states:</P>
          
          <EXTRACT>
            <P>The Bureau agrees that persons generally engaged in loan processing orwho compile and process application materials and supportingdocumentation and do not take an application, collect information onbehalf of the consumer, or communicate or interact with consumers regardingspecific transaction terms or products are not loan originators (see the separatediscussion above on taking an application and collecting informationon behalf of the consumer).<SU>42</SU>
              <FTREF/>
            </P>
            <FTNT>
              <P>
                <SU>42</SU>78 FR at 11303</P>
            </FTNT>
            
          </EXTRACT>
          <P>In contrast, however, the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule also noted that &#x201C;filling out a consumer's application, inputting the information into an online application or other automated system, and taking information from the consumer over the phone to complete the application should be considered `tak[ing] an application' for the purposes of the rule.&#x201D;<SU>43</SU>
            <FTREF/>Because the retailer employee exclusion does not apply if the employee engages in taking an application, filling out a consumer's application, inputting the information into an online application or other automated system, and taking information from the consumer over the phone to complete the application would make the employee a loan originator.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>43</SU>78 FR at 11299.<E T="03">See also</E>comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">3.,</E>78 FR at 11415.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>The Bureau is adding new comment 36(a)(1)(i)(B)-1.iii to explain that a retailer employee may collect information on behalf of the consumer with regard to a residential mortgage loan.<SU>44</SU>

            <FTREF/>This activity is not included in the activities covered by taking or offering or assisting that would make a retailer employee a loan originator. Comment 36(a)-1.i.<E T="03">3.</E>and the Supplementary Information to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule describe the activity of collecting information on behalf of the consumer as including gathering information or supporting documentation from third parties on behalf of the consumer to provide to the consumer, for the consumer then to provide in the application or for the consumer to submit to the loan originator or creditor.<SU>45</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>44</SU>
              <E T="03">See</E>TILA section 103(cc)(4) (definition of &#x201C;assists a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain a residential mortgage loan&#x201D;).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>45</SU>78 FR at 11303, 11415.</P>
          </FTNT>

          <P>The Bureau is adding new comment 36(a)(1)(i)(B)-1.iv to explain that a retailer employee may provide or make available general information about creditors that may offer financing for manufactured homes in the consumer's general area, when doing so does not otherwise amount to &#x201C;referring&#x201D; as defined in comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1.</E>Comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1</E>provides in part that referring &#x201C;includes any oral or written action directed to a consumer that can affirmatively influence the consumer to select a particular loan originator or creditor to obtain an extension of credit when the consumer will pay for such credit.&#x201D; Although this statement hardly covers the range of activities that may constitute referring, it does provide a basis for addressing the relatively unique circumstances of manufactured home retailer employees, who are covered by a limited statutory exclusion from the definition of loan originator.</P>

          <P>The Bureau believes that most consumers purchasing a manufactured home will need financing, and that a limited set of options may be available. As public commenters have noted, only a small number of creditors make loans secured by manufactured homes, and it is beneficial to consumers for that information to be made available to them by a retailer. To facilitate consumer access to credit in this situation, new comment 36(a)(1)(i)(B)-.1.iv allows a retailer employee to make general information about creditors or loan originators available, which includes making available, in a neutral manner, general brochures or information about the different creditors or loan originators that may offer financing to a consumer, but does not include recommending a particular creditor or loan originator or otherwise influencing the consumer's decision. The Bureau believes this comment falls within the purview of the quoted portion of comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1</E>above, taking into consideration the unique circumstances and the limited statutory exclusion.</P>

          <P>Finally, the Bureau notes that the comment extends to providing general information about loan originators (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>mortgage brokers) as well as creditors. Based on public comments, the Bureau believes that under current market conditions only a small number of specialized creditors currently operate in this market, and the Bureau is not aware of any mortgage brokers or similar loan originators that currently operate in this space. Nevertheless, the Bureau recognizes that circumstances may change and brokers or other loan originators may decide to offer loans secured by manufactured homes, and if that were to occur the Bureau believes the same logic that applies to creditors described above would apply with respect to these persons or organizations. Accordingly, the comment includes loan originators as well as creditors.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(b) Scope</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">The Proposal</HD>
          <P>The Bureau proposed to revise the scope of provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(b) to reflect the applicability of the servicing provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c) regarding payment processing, pyramiding late fees, and payoff statements as modified by the 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule.<SU>46</SU>

            <FTREF/>Current &#xA7; 1026.36(b) and comment 36(b)-1 (relocated from &#xA7; 1026.36(f) and comment 36-1, respectively, by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule)<PRTPAGE P="60424"/>provide that &#xA7; 1026.36(c) applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. The new payment processing provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c)(1) and the restrictions on pyramiding late fees in &#xA7; 1026.36(c)(2) both apply to consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. The new payoff statement provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c)(3), however, apply more broadly to consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>46</SU>Among other things, the 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule implemented TILA sections 129F and 129G added by section 1464 of the Dodd-Frank Act. The requirements in TILA section 129F concerning prompt crediting of payments apply to consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. The requirements in TILA section 129G concerning payoff statements apply to creditors or servicers of a home loan. The 2013 TILA Servicing Final Rule, however, did not substantively revise the existing late fee pyramiding requirement in &#xA7; 1026.36(c) but instead redesignated the requirement as new paragraph 36(c)(2) to accommodate the regulatory provisions implementing TILA sections 129F and 129G.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>The proposal would have revised &#xA7; 1026.36(b) and comment 36(b)-1 to state that &#xA7; 1026.36(c)(1) and (c)(2) apply to consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. The proposed revisions also would have provided that &#xA7; 1026.36(c)(3) applies to a consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling (even if it is not the consumer's principal dwelling). The Bureau sought comment on these proposed revisions generally. The Bureau also invited comment on whether additional revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(b) and comment 36(b)-1 should be considered to clarify further the applicability of the provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c) as modified by the 2013 Servicing Final Rules.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Comments</HD>
          <P>The Bureau received one comment that generally supported this clarification.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">Final Rule</HD>
          <P>The Bureau is adopting these revisions to &#xA7; 1026.36(b) and comment 36(b)-1 as proposed, to conform them to modifications made to &#xA7; 1026.36(c) by the 2013 Servicing Final Rules that changed the applicability of certain provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c). The Bureau believes the revisions are necessary to reflect the applicability of the provisions in &#xA7; 1026.36(c) as modified by the 2013 Servicing Final Rules.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(d) Prohibited Payments to Loan Originators</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(d)(1) Payments Based on a Term of the Transaction</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(d)(1)(i)</HD>
          <P>The Bureau proposed to revise comments 36(d)(1)-1.ii and 36(d)(1)-1.iii.D, which interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i)-(ii), to improve the consistency of the wording across the regulatory text and commentary, and provide further interpretation of the intended meaning of the regulatory text. The Bureau did not receive any comments pertaining to these particular proposed changes. As described below in the section-by-section analysis for &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), the Bureau received a small number of comments expressing general support for the proposed clarifications to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) and its commentary. The Bureau is finalizing the revisions to comments 36(d)(1)-1.ii and -1.iii.D as proposed. As it stated in the proposal, the Bureau believes these changes facilitate compliance.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(d)(1)(iii)</HD>
          <P>The Bureau proposed to revise the portions of comment 36(d)(1)-3 that interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) to improve the consistency of the wording across the regulatory text and commentary, and provide further interpretation of the intended meaning of the regulatory text. The Bureau did not receive any comments pertaining to these particular proposed changes. As described below in the section-by-section analysis for &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), the Bureau received a small number of comments expressing general support for the proposed clarifications to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) and its commentary. The Bureau is finalizing the revisions to the portions of comment 36(d)(1)-3 that interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) as proposed. As it stated in the proposal, the Bureau believes these changes facilitate compliance.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD3">36(d)(1)(iv)</HD>

          <P>The Bureau proposed revisions to the portions of comment 36(d)(1)-3 that interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv). Section 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) permits, under certain circumstances, the payment of compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan to an individual loan originator even if the compensation is directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. Section 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) permits this compensation if it does not exceed 10 percent of the individual loan originator's total compensation corresponding to the time period for which the compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is paid. Comments 36(d)(1)-3.ii through -3.v further interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>). Section 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>) permits this compensation if the individual loan originator is a loan originator for ten or fewer consummated transactions during the 12-month period preceding the compensation determination. Comment 36(d)(1)-3.vi further interprets &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>). The Bureau proposed to amend comment 36(d)(1)-3 to improve the consistency of the wording across the regulatory text and commentary, provide further interpretation as to the intended meaning of the regulatory text in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), and ensure that the examples included in the commentary accurately reflect the interpretations of the regulatory text contained elsewhere in the commentary. As the Bureau explained in the proposal, nearly all of the proposed revisions address the commentary sections that interpret the meaning of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>setting forth the 10-percent total compensation limit) and not &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>). In the proposal, the Bureau explained that it was proposing more extensive clarifications to two comments interpreting &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1), comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.A, which clarifies the meaning of &#x201C;total compensation&#x201D; as used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>), and comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.C, to clarify the meaning of &#x201C;time period&#x201D; in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>). The Bureau stated in the proposal that these proposed revisions were collectively intended to clarify that, while the time period used to determine both elements of the 10-percent limit ratio is the same: (1) the non-deferred profits-based compensation for the time period is whatever such compensation was earned during that time period, regardless of when it was actually paid; and (2) compensation that is actually paid during the time period, regardless of when it was earned, generally will be included in the amount of total compensation for that time period, but whether the compensation is included ultimately depends on the type of compensation.</P>
          <P>Of the institutions and individuals who submitted comments on the proposed changes to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, very few specifically discussed the proposed clarifications and amendments to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) and its commentary. One large depository institution first highlighted some of the proposed changes to the &#xA7; 1026.36(d) commentary and then stated that it generally agreed with the Bureau's proposed amendments and clarifications. Some consumer groups expressed general disagreement with elements of &#xA7; 1026.36(d) adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule, which they believe the proposed revisions would amplify, but did not address any specific issues with the proposal itself.</P>

          <P>The Bureau is finalizing the changes to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) and the portions of comment 36(d)(1)-3 that interpret &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) as proposed. As it stated in the proposal, the Bureau<PRTPAGE P="60425"/>believes these changes would facilitate compliance.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">VII. Section 1022(b)(2) of the Dodd-Frank Act</HD>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Overview</HD>
          <P>In developing the final rule, the Bureau has considered the potential benefits, costs, and impacts.<SU>52</SU>
            <FTREF/>In addition, the Bureau has consulted, or offered to consult with, the prudential regulators, the Securities and Exchange Commission, HUD, the Federal Housing Finance Agency, the Federal Trade Commission, and the Department of the Treasury, including regarding consistency with any prudential, market, or systemic objectives administered by such agencies.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>52</SU>Specifically, section 1022(b)(2)(A) of the Dodd-Frank Act calls for the Bureau to consider the potential benefits and costs of a regulation to consumers and covered persons, including the potential reduction of access by consumers to consumer financial products or services; the impact on depository institutions and credit unions with $10 billion or less in total assets as described in section 1026 of the Dodd-Frank Act; and the impact on consumers in rural areas.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>As noted above, this rule makes amendments to some of the final mortgage rules issued by the Bureau in January of 2013.<SU>53</SU>
            <FTREF/>These amendments focus primarily on clarifying or revising (1) Provisions of Regulation X's related to information requests and error notices; (2) loss mitigation procedures under Regulation X's servicing provisions; (3) amounts counted as loan originator compensation to retailers of manufactured homes and their employees for purposes of applying points and fees thresholds under HOEPA and the qualified mortgage rules in Regulation Z; (4) determination of which creditors operate predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas for various purposes under the mortgage regulations; (5) application of the loan originator compensation rules to bank tellers and similar staff; and (6) the prohibition on creditor-financed credit insurance. The Bureau also is adjusting the effective dates for certain provisions adopted by the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule and making technical and wording changes for clarification purposes to Regulations B, X, and Z.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>53</SU>For convenience, the reference to these January 2013 rules is also meant to encompass the rules issued in May 2013 that amended the January rules, including the May 2013 Escrows Final Rule.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>The Bureau notes that for some analyses, there are limited data available with which to quantify the potential costs, benefits and impacts of this final rule. In particular, the Bureau did not receive comments specifically addressing the Section 1022 analysis in the proposed rule. Still, general economic principles as well as the information and analysis on which the January rules were based provide insight into the benefits, costs and impacts and where relevant, the analysis provides a qualitative discussion of the benefits, cost and impacts of the final rule.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Potential Benefits and Costs to Consumers and Covered Persons</HD>
          <P>The Bureau believes that, compared to the baseline established by the final rules issued in January 2013,<SU>54</SU>
            <FTREF/>an important benefit of most of the provisions of this final rule to both consumers and covered persons is an increase in clarity and precision of the regulations and an accompanying reduction in compliance costs. Other benefits and costs are considered below.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>54</SU>The Bureau has discretion in any rulemaking to choose an appropriate scope of analysis with respect to potential benefits and costs and an appropriate baseline.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>As described above, the Bureau is amending the commentary to &#xA7; 1024.35(c) and &#xA7; 1024.36(b). As adopted by the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Rules, these provisions and accompanying commentary require a servicer that has established an exclusive address at which it will receive communications pursuant to &#xA7; 1024.35 and &#xA7; 1024.36 to disclose that address whenever it provides a borrower any contact information for assistance from the servicer. The Bureau is amending the commentary so that the exclusive address need be provided on the written notice that designates the specific address; the periodic statement or coupon book required pursuant to 12 CFR 1026.41; any Web site the servicer maintains in connection with the servicing of the loan; and any notice required pursuant to &#xA7;&#xA7; 1024.39 or .41 that includes contact information for assistance.</P>
          <P>These amendments reduce the costs to servicers of complying with &#xA7; 1024.35(c) and &#xA7; 1024.36(b) of the final rule by reducing the number of documents and other sources of information that must be modified to include the designated address. The Bureau believes that these amendments will cause at most a minimal reduction in the benefits to consumers. A borrower looking for the address to which to send a notice of error or a request for information would likely consult the servicer's Web site, the borrower's statement or coupon book, any loss mitigation documents, or perhaps the written notice designating the specific address. Further, servicers have an obligation, established by the January rule, to maintain policies and procedures reasonably designed to achieve the objective of informing borrowers of the procedures for submitting written notices of error and written information requests. Thus, a servicer should provide the proper address to a borrower who contacts the servicer for the address to which to send a notice of error or a request for information. In light of these two parallel requirements, the Bureau believes borrowers will still have ready access to the exclusive address and are not likely to send a notice of error or a request for information to an improper address. Alternatives that would require the designated address on even fewer documents or communications would further reduce the compliance costs to servicers but would increase the risk that borrowers who wish to send a notice of error or a request for information would consult a document that did not include the exclusive address and would misroute their notice or request accordingly.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is amending &#xA7; 1024.35(g)(1)(iii)(B) (untimely notices of error) and &#xA7; 1024.36(f)(1)(v)(B) (untimely requests for information), which, as adopted in January, provided respectively that the notice or request is untimely if it is delivered to the servicer more than one year after a mortgage loan balance was paid in full. Under the amended provisions, the one-year period designated by these requirements will begin when a mortgage loan is discharged, such as through foreclosure or deed in lieu of foreclosure, even if the loan balance was not paid in full.</P>

          <P>These amendments reduce costs to servicers by increasing the number of situations in which a notice or request is untimely and servicers are therefore not required to comply with certain requirements of &#xA7; 1024.35 or &#xA7; 1024.36. To the extent servicers no longer respond to notices or requests that are untimely because of these amendments, the lack of a response may impose some cost to consumers. The Bureau does not have data on the frequency with which borrowers with a mortgage that is terminated without being paid in full also assert an error or request information (within the scope of these requirements) more than one year after such termination, nor does the Bureau have information on the subsequent outcomes for such borrowers. However, the Bureau believes that one year after a mortgage loan is discharged generally provides sufficient time for borrowers to assert errors or request information. Consequently, an inability to obtain a response to such a notice or request during the longer period the rule prescribed before these amendments<PRTPAGE P="60433"/>would constitute at most a minimal impact on the benefits to consumers.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is amending the commentary to &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(2)(i) and adding new &#xA7; 1024.41(c)(2)(iv) to address the situation in which a servicer determines that additional information from the borrower is needed to complete an evaluation of a loss mitigation application after the servicer has informed the borrower, via the notice pursuant to &#xA7; 1026.41(b)(2)(i)(B), that the loss mitigation application is complete or the borrower provided the particular information identified as missing in an original notice. In summary, the servicer must request the additional information and provide a reasonable time for the borrower to respond. If the borrower provides the additional information, the 30-day evaluation period within which to evaluate the borrower for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower begins as of the date the borrower provides the remaining information. The borrower, on the other hand, receives the protections against foreclosure during the period provided to gather the supplemental information. If the borrower provides the additional information, the borrower will also receive the right to appeal and other rights as though the application were actually complete when either the borrower submitted the original loss mitigation application (if the notice informed the borrower that the application was complete) or the borrower provided the particular information identified in the original notice (if the notice informed the borrower that the application was incomplete). In situations in which a servicer determines that supplemental information from the borrower is needed after sending the &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(2)(i)(B) notice, these dates will generally be earlier than the date on which the borrower provides the supplemental information to make the application complete. Accordingly, the amended final rule provides greater consumer protections than the original final rule or the proposal.</P>
          <P>The costs to the servicer of these amendments are the costs of complying that are incremental to the baseline costs arising from the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules. The Bureau believes that in all cases these costs are small given other provisions of the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules. As discussed above, under that final rule, servicers are required to review a loss mitigation application to determine whether it is complete or incomplete, to have policies and procedures reasonably designed to achieve the objectives of identifying documents and information that a borrower is required to submit to complete an otherwise incomplete loss mitigation application, and to exercise reasonable diligence in obtaining documents and information necessary to complete an incomplete application. Thus, the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules already obligated the servicer to exercise reasonable diligence to bring to completion an application that was facially complete but in fact lacked information necessary for review. The servicer would therefore, even absent the new provisions, have the personnel and infrastructure needed to contact the borrower for additional information and evaluate the application since these are required to comply with the other obligations stated above. Thus, the Bureau does not believe that the costs of complying with the amendment are significant.</P>
          <P>The benefits to consumers of these amendments are the benefits of servicers following the procedures adopted by this final rule that are incremental to the baseline benefits defined by the final servicing rule. The amendment requires servicers to promptly request any additional information or documents needed to complete a facially complete loss mitigation application, and also provides borrowers with a reasonable amount of time to provide any such documents or information. The amendment delays the 30-day period during which a servicer must evaluate a complete application until after the borrower has provided such documents or information. This additional time benefits consumers by encouraging thorough review of these applications. Further, the rule will make clear that a servicer has fulfilled its obligations if it follows the new procedure. This encourages servicers to acknowledge and rectify their errors and therefore increases the likelihood that servicers will make loss mitigation decisions on the basis of complete information.</P>
          <P>As an alternative, if borrowers receive protections from the date on which the application is actually complete (instead of facially complete), it is more likely the date would be past the 120th day of delinquency or closer to the date of a foreclosure sale. Servicers might have slightly lower costs under this alternative, perhaps from a shorter period of providing continuity of contact and monitoring the property, but borrowers would receive fewer protections against foreclosure. Further, servicers that wanted to provide fewer protections could more easily manipulate the date on which an application is actually complete than the date on which it is facially complete given that facial completeness is determined by a mandated timeline and disclosure and by how quickly the consumer provides any missing information identified in the disclosure.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is amending the &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) time period disclosure requirement, which requires a servicer to provide a date by which a borrower should submit any missing documents and information necessary to make a loss mitigation application complete. As explained above, &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(2)(ii) as originally adopted requires the servicer to notify the borrower that the borrower should submit such missing documents and information by the earliest of certain dates. This requirement would have applied even if the nearest date would leave the borrower with very little time to assemble the missing information. The amendment requires the servicer to provide a reasonable date by which the borrower should submit the documents and information necessary to make the loss mitigation application complete. Commentary provides additional guidance and advises a servicer to select the nearest of four key dates that is at least seven days in the future. This change presents some tradeoff in benefits and costs for consumers, but on balance the Bureau believes that it will be beneficial to consumers. Consumers who would have been provided impracticable dates for responding in the initial notice generally benefit from this amendment by being provided with useful information. In particular, the Bureau believes that some consumers who might have failed to complete the loss mitigation application altogether when faced with an impracticable date for submitting materials would be more likely to complete the application by a reasonable date as determined under the amended rule, and thus to secure consideration for foreclosure alternatives and some of the important procedural rights available to them under the loss mitigation regulations. Servicers will incur one-time costs for changes to software to check whether the nearest key date is closer than the rule permits and provide the later date in this case. Servicers may also incur costs associated with receiving additional complete loss mitigation applications.</P>

          <P>The Bureau is adding a new provision in &#xA7; 1024.41(b)(3) addressing how borrower protections are determined when no foreclosure sale is scheduled as of the date a complete loss mitigation application is received or when a foreclosure sale is rescheduled after receipt of a complete application. Under the final servicing rule, a servicer could,<PRTPAGE P="60434"/>arguably, initiate the foreclosure process on day 121 of delinquency, receive a complete loss mitigation application from a borrower, schedule a foreclosure sale within 90 days, and then provide fewer protections than those afforded to loss mitigation applications received at least 90 days before a scheduled foreclosure sale. The new provisions provide that if no foreclosure sale has been scheduled as of the date that a complete loss mitigation application is received, the application shall be treated as if it were received at least 90 days before a scheduled foreclosure sale. In addition, the new provisions make clear that whether certain foreclosure protections and other rights in the rule apply depends on the date for which a foreclosure sale was scheduled at the time of a borrower's complete application. If the scheduled date later changes, the foreclosure protections and other rights that arose at the time of the complete application do not change.</P>
          <P>The Bureau recognizes that the new provisions may reduce some of the flexibility servicers had under the 2013 Mortgage Servicing Rule. This is a cost to servicers. Further, some servicers in possession of an incomplete loss mitigation application on day 121 of delinquency who would not have scheduled a foreclosure sale may now do so in order to avoid the risk of a longer time to foreclosure. As a result, certain borrowers may have less time to respond to a loss mitigation offer and no right to appeal a denial. On the other hand, borrowers with servicers that do not accelerate the scheduling of foreclosure sales have clearer rights and most likely more time to respond to a loss mitigation offer and a right to appeal a denial. The Bureau cannot quantify these different effects, but believes that they are most likely small given the wide range of other factors that determine the time to foreclosure.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is modifying &#xA7; 1024.41(c)(2) to allow servicers to offer certain short-term forbearances to borrowers, notwithstanding the prohibition on servicers offering a loss mitigation option to a borrower based on the review of an incomplete loss mitigation application. This provision imposes no costs on servicers because it does not impose any new obligations on servicers relative to the final rule. The provision benefits servicers by providing a relatively low-cost way for servicers to provide borrowers with a particular loss mitigation option. Similarly, the provision imposes no costs on borrowers since the borrower can reject forbearance based on review of an incomplete loss mitigation option, provide a complete loss mitigation application, and be reviewed for all loss mitigation options available to the borrower (and other protections) as under the final rule. The provision benefits borrowers by providing borrowers with a particular loss mitigation option on the basis of an incomplete application and therefore without exhausting the option to have the servicer review a complete loss mitigation application.</P>
          <P>As discussed above, the Bureau is conscious of the fact that some servicers have significantly exacerbated borrowers' financial difficulties in the past by using short-term forbearance programs inappropriately instead of reviewing the borrowers for long-term options. Thus, in developing this provision, the Bureau has sought to ensure that borrowers would receive significant benefits from forbearance based on review of an incomplete loss mitigation option with minimal additional risk or loss of consumer protections. However, while a long forbearance period creates risks to consumers by generating a significant debt and increasing the chance the borrower might have been better off with an option that the servicer would have offered after evaluating a complete loss mitigation application, the comments received also emphasized heavily that very short forbearance periods do not provide much benefit to borrowers in situations in which forbearance is being used appropriately because they do not allow sufficient time for borrowers to remedy the short-term problems that created the need for forbearance and resume making payments on their loans. The Bureau does not have data with which to identify the average or maximum length of time of forbearance that would balance these factors. Further, the risks to consumers from not specifying a maximum length of time for forbearance are mitigated somewhat by the fact that a borrower who receives a forbearance agreement without having submitted a complete loss mitigation application can trigger a review for loss mitigation options by submitting a complete application more than 37 days before a scheduled foreclosure sale. Taking these factors into account, the Bureau believes that borrowers benefit more from the new forbearance provisions than they would from alternatives that imposed a maximum length of time on forbearance.</P>
          <P>The Bureau is also clarifying the &#x201C;first notice or filing&#x201D; standard in &#xA7; 1024.41(f). The 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules prohibited servicers from making the &#x201C;first notice or filing&#x201D; under state law during the first 120 days of the borrower's delinquency, but interpreted &#x201C;first notice or filing&#x201D; broadly to include notices of default or other notices required by applicable law in order to pursue acceleration of a mortgage loan obligation or the sale of a property securing a mortgage loan obligation. The Bureau is modifying this interpretation and adopting a narrower construction that more closely tracks the Federal Housing Administration's &#x201C;first legal&#x201D; standard. The Bureau also is clarifying how the rule works across states with different foreclosure laws&#x2014;such as in &#x201C;judicial&#x201D; states where foreclosure requires an action filed in court and in &#x201C;non-judicial&#x201D; states where foreclosure requires notice or publication of sale.</P>
          <P>The Bureau believes these amendments will benefit servicers by clarifying the scope of actions prohibited during a borrower's first 120 days in accordance with a familiar standard. In addition, the amendments will not unduly delay foreclosures in states that provide statutory or other notice and cure processes in advance of a foreclosure action or sale by forcing servicers to wait 120 days to send such a notice. The Bureau believes these amendments will benefit borrowers because they will allow notices that do not initiate foreclosure, but instead are intended to provide borrowers with information about counseling and other loss mitigation resources as a means of avoiding foreclosure during the first 120 days of delinquency, when those notices are most likely to benefit borrowers. The Bureau recognizes the possibility that these amendments may, in certain States, allow foreclosure to be initiated more quickly than under the Final Rule, but the Bureau believes that the amendments are beneficial to borrowers overall.</P>

          <P>In addition, the Bureau is modifying or clarifying other Regulation X loss mitigation provisions. The Bureau is amending &#xA7; 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) to state explicitly that the notice required by &#xA7; 1024.41(c)(1)(ii) must state the deadline for accepting or rejecting a servicer's offer of a loss mitigation option. The Bureau is amending &#xA7; 1024.41(h)(4) to provide expressly that the notice informing a borrower of the determination of his or her appeal must also state the amount of time the borrower has to accept or reject an offer of a loss mitigation option after the notice is provided to the borrower. The Bureau is amending &#xA7; 1024.41(f)(1), the prohibition on referral to foreclosure until after the 120th day of delinquency, by exempting a foreclosure based on a borrower's violation of a due-on-sale clause or in which the servicer is joining the foreclosure action of a subordinate<PRTPAGE P="60435"/>lienholder. Finally, the Bureau is clarifying the requirement in &#xA7; 1024.41(d)(1) (re-codified as &#xA7; 1024.41(d)) that a servicer must disclose the reasons for the denial of any trial or permanent loan modification option available to the borrower to make clear that this provision requires the servicer to disclose only determinations actually made by the servicer and does not require a servicer to continue evaluating additional factors after a decision has been established. The Bureau believes these modifications will only minimally increase costs to servicers and the clarifications will likely benefit both servicers and consumers, in part through reduced implementation costs.</P>
          <P>Two of the sets of modifications to the Regulation Z provisions involve loan originator compensation. The Bureau is clarifying for retailers of manufactured homes and their employees what compensation can be attributed to a transaction at the time the interest rate is set and must be included in the points and fees thresholds for qualified mortgages and high-cost mortgages under HOEPA. As discussed above, the final rule will exclude from points and fees of loan originator compensation paid by a retailer of manufactured homes to its employees and will clarify that the sales price of a manufactured home does not include loan originator compensation that must be included in points and fees. Both of these changes will reduce the burden for creditors in manufactured home transactions by eliminating the need for them in certain circumstances to attempt to determine what, if any, retailer employee compensation and what, if any, part of the sales price will count as loan originator compensation that must be included in points and fees. This amendment is also likely to lower slightly the amount of money counted toward the points and fees thresholds on the covered loans. As a result, keeping all other provisions of a given loan fixed, this will result in a greater number of loans to be eligible to be qualified mortgages. For such loans, the costs of origination may be slightly lower as a result of the slightly decreased liability for the lender and any assignees and for possibly decreased compliance costs. Consumers may benefit from slightly increased access to credit and lower costs on the affected loans, however these consumers will also not have the added consumer protections that accompany loans made under the general ability-to-repay provisions. The lower amount of points and fees may also lead fewer loans to be above the points and fees triggers for high-cost mortgages under HOEPA: This should make these loans both more available and offered at a lower cost to consumers, though consumers will not have the added consumer protections that apply to high-cost mortgages. A more detailed discussion of these effects is contained in the discussion of benefits, costs, and impacts in part VII of the 2013 ATR Final Rule and the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule.</P>

          <P>The Bureau also is revising the commentary addressing when employees of a creditor or loan originator in certain administrative or clerical roles (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>tellers or greeters) may become &#x201C;loan originators&#x201D; under the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Rule, and therefore subject to that Rule's requirements applicable to loan originators, such as qualification requirements and restrictions on certain compensation practices. As noted above, classifying such individuals as loan originators would subject them to the requirements applicable to loan originators with, in the Bureau's view, little appreciable benefit for consumers. Removing them from this classification should lower compliance costs including those related to SAFE Act training, certification requirements, and compensation restrictions.</P>
          <P>The final rule's provisions regarding credit insurance clarify what constitutes financing of such premiums by a creditor, and is therefore generally prohibited under the Dodd-Frank Act with regard to credit insurance on mortgage loans. The final rule will also clarify when credit insurance premiums are considered to be calculated and paid on a monthly basis for purposes of a statutory exclusion from the prohibition for certain credit insurance premium calculation and payment arrangements. As noted earlier, the Bureau believes that language in the preamble to the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule led to some confusion among creditors and credit insurance providers regarding whether credit insurance products were prohibited under the rule based on how their premiums are calculated. The Bureau is now clarifying that the prohibition only extends to creditors financing credit insurance premiums, and providing additional guidance on what constitutes creditor financing and what is excluded from the prohibition. Specifically, the Bureau is finalizing a modified version of the clarification it proposed that provides increased clarity regarding the application of the rule to certain products&#x2014;particularly to insurance with &#x201C;level&#x201D; or &#x201C;levelized&#x201D; premiums&#x2014;and this should benefit both creditors and providers of credit insurance products. As discussed above, the modification will, among other things, permit creditors to continue providing credit insurance products, including those with &#x201C;level&#x201D; or &#x201C;levelized&#x201D; premiums, so long as the premium is not treated as an obligation owed by the consumer beyond the month in which it is due. The Bureau also solicited comment on an alternative clarification, and believes on the basis of comments that the alternative is less clear and no more protective of consumers than the provision the Bureau is finalizing.</P>
          <P>The final rule will also make two adjustments to provisions that provide certain exceptions for creditors operating predominantly in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; areas during the next two years, while the Bureau reexamines the definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; as it recently announced in the May 2013 ATR Final Rule. Specifically, the final rule will extend an exception to the general prohibition on balloon features for high-cost mortgages under the 2013 HOEPA Final Rule that is available to certain loans made by small creditors who operate predominantly in rural or underserved areas temporarily to all small creditors, regardless of their geographic operations. The final rule will also amend an exemption from the requirement to maintain escrows for higher-priced mortgage loans under the 2013 Escrow Final Rule that is available to small creditors that extended more than 50 percent of their total covered transactions secured by a first lien in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during the preceding calendar year to allow small creditors to qualify for the exemption if they made more than 50 percent of their covered transactions in &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; counties during any of the previous three calendar years.</P>

          <P>As noted above, the Bureau believes expanding the balloon-payment exception for high-cost mortgages to allow certain small creditors operating in areas that do not qualify as &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; to continue to originate certain high-cost mortgages with balloon payments during the next two years will benefit creditors who might be unable to convert to offering adjustable rate mortgages by the time the final rules take effect in January 2014. The final rule will also promote consistency between HOEPA requirements and the May 2013 ATR Final Rule, thereby facilitating compliance for creditors. The Bureau believes that the final rule will also benefit consumers by increasing access to credit relative to the<PRTPAGE P="60436"/>2013 HOEPA Final Rule. Although balloon loans can in some cases increase risks for consumers, the Bureau believes that those risks are appropriately mitigated in these circumstances because the balloon loans must meet the requirements for qualified mortgages in order to qualify for the exception. This includes certain restrictions on the amount of up-front points and fees and various loan features, as well as a requirement that the loans be held on portfolio by the small creditor. These requirements reduce the risk of potentially abusive lending practices and provide strong incentives for the creditor to underwrite the loan appropriately.</P>
          <P>The amendment to the qualifications for the exemption from the escrow requirements should minimize the disruptions from any changes in the categorization of certain counties while the Bureau is reevaluating the underlying definitions. This in turn should lower compliance costs for certain creditors during the interim period. Consumers may benefit from greater access to credit and lower costs, but in return will not receive the benefits of an escrow account. A more detailed discussion of these effects is contained in the discussion of benefits, costs, and impacts in part VII of the 2013 Escrows Final Rule.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Impact on Depository Institutions and Credit Unions With $10 Billion or Less in Total Assets, as Described in Section 1026; the Impact of the Provisions on Consumers in Rural Areas; Impact on Access to Consumer Financial Products and Services</HD>
          <P>The final rule is generally not expected to have a differential impact on depository institutions and credit unions with $10 billion or less in total assets as described in section 1026. The exceptions are those provisions related to the definitions of &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; which directly impact entities with under $2 billion in total assets. The final rule may have some differential impacts on consumers in rural areas. To the extent that manufactured housing loans, higher-priced mortgage loans, high-cost loans or balloon loans are more prevalent in these areas, the relevant provisions may have slightly greater impacts. As discussed above, costs for creditors in these areas should be reduced; consumers should benefit from increased access to credit and lower costs, though they will not have access to the heightened protections afforded by various provisions. Given the nature and limited scope of the changes in the final rule, the Bureau does not believe that the final rule will reduce consumers' access to consumer financial products and services.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">VIII. Regulatory Flexibility Act Analysis</HD>
          <P>The Regulatory Flexibility Act (RFA) generally requires an agency to conduct an initial regulatory flexibility analysis (IRFA) and a final regulatory flexibility analysis (FRFA) of any rule subject to notice-and-comment rulemaking requirements.<SU>55</SU>
            <FTREF/>These analyses must &#x201C;describe the impact of the proposed rule on small entities.&#x201D;<SU>56</SU>
            <FTREF/>An IRFA or FRFA is not required if the agency certifies that the rule will not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities,<SU>57</SU>
            <FTREF/>or if the agency considers a series of closely related rules as one rule for purposes of complying with the IRFA or FRFA requirements.<SU>58</SU>
            <FTREF/>The Bureau also is subject to certain additional procedures under the RFA involving the convening of a panel to consult with small business representatives prior to proposing a rule for which an IRFA is required.<SU>59</SU>
            <FTREF/>
          </P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>55</SU>5 U.S.C. 601<E T="03">et seq.</E>
            </P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>56</SU>5 U.S.C. 603(a). For purposes of assessing the impacts of the proposed rule on small entities, &#x201C;small entities&#x201D; is defined in the RFA to include small businesses, small not-for-profit organizations, and small government jurisdictions. 5 U.S.C. 601(6). A &#x201C;small business&#x201D; is determined by application of Small Business Administration regulations and reference to the North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) classifications and size standards. 5 U.S.C. 601(3). A &#x201C;small organization&#x201D; is any &#x201C;not-for-profit enterprise which is independently owned and operated and is not dominant in its field.&#x201D; 5 U.S.C. 601(4). A &#x201C;small governmental jurisdiction&#x201D; is the government of a city, county, town, township, village, school district, or special district with a population of less than 50,000. 5 U.S.C. 601(5).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>57</SU>5 U.S.C. 605(b).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>58</SU>5 U.S.C. 605(c).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>59</SU>5 U.S.C. 609.</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>This rulemaking is part of a series of rules that have revised and expanded the regulatory requirements for entities that originate or service mortgage loans. As noted above, in January, 2013, the Bureau issued the 2013 ATR Final Rule, 2013 Escrows Final Rule, 2013 HOEPA Final Rule, 2013 Mortgage Servicing Final Rules, and the 2013 Loan Originator Compensation Final Rule. Since January 2013, the Bureau also has issued the May 2013 ATR Final Rule, May 2013 Escrows Final Rule, and the 2013 Effective Date Final Rule, along with Amendments to the 2013 Mortgage Rules under the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (Regulation X) and Truth in Lending Act (Regulation Z).<SU>60</SU>
            <FTREF/>The Supplementary Information to each of these rules set forth the Bureau's analyses and determinations under the RFA with respect to those rules. Because these rules qualify as &#x201C;a series of closely related rules,&#x201D; for purposes of the RFA, the Bureau relies on those analyses and determines that it has met or exceeded the IRFA and FRFA requirements.</P>
          <FTNT>
            <P>
              <SU>60</SU>78 FR 44686 (July 24, 2013).</P>
          </FTNT>
          <P>In the alternative, the Bureau also concludes that the final rule will not have a significant impact on a substantial number of small entities. As noted, this final rule generally clarifies the existing rule and to the extent any changes are substantive, these changes will not have a material impact on small entities. The provisions related to servicing do not apply to many small entities under the small servicer exemption (and to the extent that they do, small entities will benefit from the same increased flexibility under the proposed provisions as other servicers), while the provisions related to loan originator compensation and the &#x201C;rural&#x201D; and &#x201C;underserved&#x201D; definitions lower the regulatory burden and possible compliance costs for affected entities. Therefore, the undersigned certifies that the rule will not have a significant impact on a substantial number of small entities.</P>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">IX. Paperwork Reduction Act</HD>
          <P>This final rule amends 12 CFR Part 1002 (Regulation B) which implements the Equal Credit Opportunity Act, 12 CFR Part 1026 (Regulation Z), which implements the Truth in Lending Act (TILA), and 12 CFR Part 1024 (Regulation X), which implements the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act (RESPA). Regulations B, Z and X currently contain collections of information approved by OMB. The Bureau's OMB control number for Regulation B is 3170-0013, for Regulation Z is 3170-0015 and for Regulation X is 3170-0016. However, the Bureau has determined that this proposed rule would not materially alter these collections of information or impose any new recordkeeping, reporting, or disclosure requirements on the public that would constitute collections of information requiring approval under the Paperwork Reduction Act, 44 U.S.C. 3501 et seq.</P>
          <LSTSUB>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects</HD>
            <CFR>12 CFR Part 1002</CFR>

            <P>Aged, Banks, Banking, Civil rights, Consumer protection, Credit, Credit unions, Discrimination, Fair lending, Marital status discrimination, National banks, National origin discrimination, Penalties, Race discrimination, Religious discrimination, Reporting and<PRTPAGE P="60437"/>recordkeeping requirements, Savings associations, Sex discrimination.</P>
            <CFR>12 CFR Part 1024</CFR>
            <P>Condominiums, Consumer protection, Housing, Mortgage servicing, Mortgages, Reporting and recordkeeping.</P>
            <CFR>12 CFR Part 1026</CFR>
            <P>Advertising, Consumer protection, Credit, Credit unions, Mortgages, National banks, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Savings associations, Truth in lending.</P>
          </LSTSUB>
          <HD SOURCE="HD1">Authority and Issuance</HD>
          <P>For the reasons set forth in the preamble, the Bureau amends 12 CFR parts 1002, 1024, and 1026 as set forth below:</P>
          <REGTEXT PART="1026" TITLE="12">
            <PART>
              <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 1026&#x2014;TRUTH IN LENDING (REGULATION Z)</HD>
            </PART>
            <AMDPAR>12. The authority citation for part 1026 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
            <AUTH>
              <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>

              <P>12 U.S.C. 2601, 2603-2605, 2607, 2609, 2617, 5511, 5512, 5532, 5581; 15 U.S.C. 1601<E T="03">et seq.</E>
              </P>
            </AUTH>
          </REGTEXT>
          <REGTEXT PART="1026" TITLE="12">
            <AMDPAR>16. Section 1026.35 is amended by revising paragraphs (b)(2)(iii)(A), and (b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">1</E>) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
            <SECTION>
              <SECTNO>&#xA7; 1026.35</SECTNO>
              <SUBJECT>Requirements for higher-priced mortgage loans.</SUBJECT>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(b) * * *</P>
              <P>(2) * * *</P>
              <P>(i) * * *</P>
              <P>(D) A reverse mortgage transaction subject to &#xA7; 1026.33.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(iii) * * *</P>
              <P>(A) During any of the three preceding calendar years, the creditor extended more than 50 percent of its total covered transactions, as defined by &#xA7; 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, on properties that are located in counties that are either &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved,&#x201D; as set forth in paragraph (b)(2)(iv) of this section;</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(D) * * *</P>
              <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) Escrow accounts established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014; or</P>
              <STARS/>
            </SECTION>
          </REGTEXT>
          <REGTEXT PART="1026" TITLE="12">
            <AMDPAR>17. Section 1026.36, as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, is amended by revising paragraphs (a)(1)(i)(A) and (B), adding paragraphs (a)(6), revising paragraph (b), and revising paragraph (j)(2) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
            <SECTION>
              <SECTNO>&#xA7; 1026.36</SECTNO>
              <SUBJECT>Prohibited acts or practices and certain requirements for credit secured by a dwelling.</SUBJECT>
              <P>(a) * * *</P>
              <P>(1) * * *</P>
              <P>(i) * * *</P>
              <P>(A) A person who does not take a consumer credit application or offer or negotiate credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, but who performs purely administrative or clerical tasks on behalf of a person who does engage in such activities.</P>
              <P>(B) An employee of a manufactured home retailer who does not take a consumer credit application, offer or negotiate credit terms, or advise a consumer on credit terms.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(6)<E T="03">Credit terms.</E>For purposes of this section, the term &#x201C;credit terms&#x201D; includes rates, fees, and other costs. Credit terms are selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics when those terms are selected based on any factors that may influence a credit decision, such as debts, income, assets, or credit history.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(b)<E T="03">Scope.</E>Paragraphs (c)(1) and (2) of this section apply to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Paragraph (c)(3) of this section applies to a consumer credit transaction secured by a dwelling. Paragraphs (d) through (i) of this section apply to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling. This section does not apply to a home equity line of credit subject to &#xA7; 1026.40, except that paragraphs (h) and (i) of this section apply to such credit when secured by the consumer's principal dwelling and paragraph (c)(3) applies to such credit when secured by a dwelling. Paragraphs (d) through (i) of this section do not apply to a loan that is secured by a consumer's interest in a timeshare plan described in 11 U.S.C. 101(53D).</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>(j) * * *</P>
              <P>(2) For purposes of this paragraph (j), &#x201C;depository institution&#x201D; has the meaning in section 1503(3) of the SAFE Act, 12 U.S.C. 5102(3). For purposes of this paragraph (j), &#x201C;subsidiary&#x201D; has the meaning in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act, 12 U.S.C. 1813.</P>
              <STARS/>
            </SECTION>
          </REGTEXT>
          <REGTEXT PART="1026" TITLE="12">
            <AMDPAR>20. In Supplement I to Part 1026:</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>a. Under<E T="03">Section 1026.25&#x2014;Record Retention</E>
            </AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>i. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 25(c)(2) Records related to requirements for loan originator compensation,</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraph 1 is revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>d. Under<E T="03">Section 1026.35&#x2014;Requirements for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</E>
            </AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>i. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii),</E>paragraphs 1 introductory text and 1.i are revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>ii. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1),</E>paragraph 1 is revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>e. Under<E T="03">Section 1026.36&#x2014;Prohibited Acts or Practices in Connection With Credit Secured by a Dwelling</E>
            </AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>i. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 36(a),</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraphs 1, 4.i, 4.ii.B, 4.ii.C, 4.iii.C, 4.iv.B,  5 introductory text, 5.iv introductory text and 5.iv.B are revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>ii. Paragraph<E T="03">36(a)(1)(i)(B)</E>and paragraph 1 are added.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>iii. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 36(b),</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraph 1 is revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>iv. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 36(d)(1),</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraphs 1, 3, and 6 are revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>v. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 36(f)(3)(i),</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraphs 1 and 2 are revised.</AMDPAR>
            <AMDPAR>vi. Under<E T="03">Paragraph 36(f)(3)(ii),</E>as amended February 15, 2013, at 78 FR 11280, paragraphs 1 and 2 are revised.</AMDPAR>
            <P>The revisions read as follows:</P>
            <HD SOURCE="HD1">Supplement I to Part 1026&#x2014;Official Interpretations</HD>
            <EXTRACT>
              <STARS/>
              <SUBPART>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart D&#x2014;Miscellaneous</HD>
                <HD SOURCE="HD2">Section 1026.25&#x2014;Record Retention</HD>
                <STARS/>
              </SUBPART>
              <P>25(c) Records related to certain requirements for mortgage loans.</P>
              <P>25(c)(2) Records related to requirements for loan originator compensation.</P>
              <P>1. * * *</P>
              <P>i.<E T="03">Records sufficient to evidence payment and receipt of compensation.</E>Records are sufficient to evidence payment and receipt of compensation if they demonstrate the following facts: The nature and amount of the compensation; that the compensation was paid, and by whom; that the compensation was received, and by whom; and when the payment and receipt of compensation occurred. The compensation agreements themselves are to be retained in all circumstances consistent with &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2)(i). The additional records that are sufficient necessarily will vary on a case-by-case basis depending on the facts and circumstances, particularly with regard to the nature of the compensation. For example, if the compensation is in the form of a salary, records to be retained might include copies of required filings under the Internal Revenue Code that demonstrate the amount of the salary. If the compensation is in the form of a contribution to or a benefit under a designated tax-advantaged plan, records to be maintained might include copies of required filings under the Internal Revenue Code or other applicable Federal law relating to the plan, copies of the plan and amendments thereto in which individual loan originators participate and the names of any loan originators covered by the plan, or determination letters from the Internal Revenue Service regarding the plan. If the compensation is in the nature of a commission or bonus, records to be retained might include a settlement agent &#x201C;flow of funds&#x201D; worksheet or other written record or a creditor closing instructions letter directing disbursement of fees at consummation. Where a loan originator is a mortgage broker, a disclosure of compensation or broker agreement required by applicable State law that recites the broker's total compensation for a transaction is a record of the amount actually paid to the loan originator in connection with the transaction, unless actual compensation deviates from the amount in the disclosure or agreement. Where compensation has been decreased to defray the cost, in whole or part, of an unforeseen increase in an actual settlement cost over an estimated settlement cost disclosed to the consumer pursuant to section 5(c) of RESPA (or omitted from that disclosure), records to be maintained are those documenting the decrease in compensation and reasons for it.</P>
              <P>ii.<E T="03">Compensation agreement.</E>For purposes of &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(2), a compensation agreement includes any agreement, whether oral, written, or based on a course of conduct that establishes a compensation arrangement between the parties (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>a brokerage agreement between a creditor and a mortgage broker or provisions of employment contracts between a creditor and an individual loan originator employee addressing payment of compensation). Where a compensation agreement is oral or based on a course of conduct and cannot itself be maintained, the records to be maintained are those, if any, evidencing the existence or terms of the oral or course of conduct compensation agreement. Creditors and loan originators are free to specify what transactions are governed by a particular compensation agreement as they see fit. For example, they may provide, by the terms of the agreement, that the agreement governs compensation payable on transactions consummated on or after some future effective date (in which case, a prior agreement governs transactions consummated in the meantime). For purposes of applying the record retention requirement to transaction-specific commissions, the relevant compensation agreement for a given transaction is the agreement pursuant to which compensation for that transaction is determined.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">25(c)(3) Records related to minimum standards for transactions secured by a dwelling.</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Evidence of compliance with repayment ability provisions.</E>A creditor must retain evidence of compliance with &#xA7; 1026.43 for three years after the date of consummation of a consumer credit transaction covered by that section. (See comment 25(c)(3)-2 for guidance on the retention of evidence of compliance with the requirement to offer a consumer a loan without a prepayment penalty under &#xA7; 1026.43(g)(3).) If a creditor must verify and document information used in underwriting a transaction subject to &#xA7; 1026.43, the creditor shall retain evidence sufficient to demonstrate compliance with the documentation requirements of the rule. Although a creditor need not retain actual paper copies of the documentation used in underwriting a transaction subject to &#xA7; 1026.43, to comply with &#xA7; 1026.25(c)(3), the creditor must be able to reproduce such records accurately. For example, if the creditor uses a consumer's Internal Revenue Service (IRS) Form W-2 to verify the consumer's income, the creditor must be able to reproduce the IRS Form W-2 itself, and not merely the income information that was contained in the form.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <HD SOURCE="HD2">Section 1026.35&#x2014;Requirements for Higher-Priced Mortgage Loans</HD>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">35(b) Escrow accounts.</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">35(b)(2) Exemptions.</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii).</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Requirements for exemption.</E>Under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii), except as provided in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(v), a creditor need not establish an escrow account for taxes and insurance for a higher-priced mortgage loan, provided the following four conditions are satisfied when the higher-priced mortgage loan is consummated:</P>
              <P>i. During any of the three preceding calendar years, more than 50 percent of the creditor's total first-lien covered transactions, as defined in &#xA7; 1026.43(b)(1), are secured by properties located in counties that are either &#x201C;rural&#x201D; or &#x201C;underserved,&#x201D; as set forth in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iv). Pursuant to that section, a creditor may rely as a safe harbor on a list of counties published by the Bureau to determine whether counties in the United States are rural or underserved for a particular calendar year. Thus, for example, if a creditor originated 90 covered transactions, as defined by &#xA7; 1026.43(b)(1), secured by a first lien, during 2011, 2012, or 2013, the creditor meets this condition for an exemption in 2014 if at least 46 of those transactions in one of those three calendar years are secured by first liens on properties that are located in such counties.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">Paragraph 35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(1).</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Exception for certain accounts.</E>Escrow accounts established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014, are not counted for purposes of &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D). For applications received on and after January 1, 2014, creditors, together with their affiliates, that establish new escrow accounts, other than those described in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">2</E>), do not qualify for the exemption provided under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii). Creditors, together with their affiliates, that continue to maintain escrow accounts established for first-lien higher-priced mortgage loans for which applications were received on or after April 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2014, still qualify for the exemption provided under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii) so long as they do not establish new escrow accounts for transactions for which they received applications on or after January 1, 2014, other than those described in &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii)(D)(<E T="03">2</E>), and they otherwise qualify under &#xA7; 1026.35(b)(2)(iii).</P>
              <STARS/>
              <HD SOURCE="HD2">Section 1026.36&#x2014;Prohibited Acts or Practices in Connection With Credit Secured by a Dwelling</HD>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(a) Definitions.</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Meaning of loan originator.</E>i.<E T="03">General.</E>A. Section 1026.36(a) defines the set of activities or services any one of which, if done for or in the expectation of compensation or gain, makes the person doing such activities or<PRTPAGE P="60445"/>performing such services a loan originator, unless otherwise excluded. The scope of activities covered by the term loan originator includes:</P>
              <P>
                <E T="03">1.</E>Referring a consumer to any person who participates in the origination process as a loan originator. Referring is an activity included under each of the activities of offering, arranging, or assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying to obtain an extension of credit. Referring includes any oral or written action directed to a consumer that can affirmatively influence the consumer to select a particular loan originator or creditor to obtain an extension of credit when the consumer will pay for such credit. See comment 36(a)-4 with respect to certain activities that do not constitute referring.</P>
              <P>
                <E T="03">2.</E>Arranging a credit transaction, including initially contacting and orienting the consumer to a particular loan originator's or creditor's origination process or particular credit terms that are or may be available to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, assisting the consumer to apply for credit, taking an application, offering particular credit terms to the consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, negotiating credit terms, or otherwise obtaining or making an extension of credit.</P>
              <P>
                <E T="03">3.</E>Assisting a consumer in obtaining or applying for consumer credit by advising on particular credit terms that are or may be available to that consumer based on the consumer's financial characteristics, filling out an application form, preparing application packages (such as a credit application or pre-approval application or supporting documentation), or collecting application and supporting information on behalf of the consumer to submit to a loan originator or creditor. A person who, acting on behalf of a loan originator or creditor, collects information or verifies information provided by the consumer, such as by asking the consumer for documentation to support the information the consumer provided or for the consumer's authorization to obtain supporting documents from third parties, is not collecting information on behalf of the consumer. See also comment 36(a)z4.i through iv with respect to application-related administrative and clerical tasks and comment 36(a)-1.v with respect to third-party advisors.</P>
              <P>
                <E T="03">4.</E>Presenting particular credit terms for the consumer's consideration that are selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, or communicating with a consumer for the purpose of reaching a mutual understanding about prospective credit terms.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>4. * * *</P>
              <P>i.<E T="03">Application-related administrative and clerical tasks.</E>The definition of loan originator does not include a loan originator's or creditor's employee who provides a credit application form from the entity for which the person works to the consumer for the consumer to complete or, without assisting the consumer in completing the credit application, processing or analyzing the information, or discussing particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics, delivers the credit application from a consumer to a loan originator or creditor. A person does not assist the consumer in completing the application if the person explains to the consumer filling out the application the contents of the application or where particular consumer information is to be provided, or generally describes the credit application process to a consumer without discussing particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics.</P>
              <P>ii.<E T="03">Responding to consumer inquiries and providing general information.</E>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who:</P>
              <P>A. * * *</P>
              <P>B. As employees of a creditor or loan originator, provide loan originator or creditor contact information of the loan originator or creditor entity for which he or she works, or of a person who works for that the same entity to a consumer, provided that the person does not discuss particular credit terms that are or may be available from a creditor or loan originator to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics and does not direct the consumer, based on his or her assessment of the consumer's financial characteristics, to a particular loan originator or particular creditor seeking to originate credit transactions to consumers with those financial characteristics;</P>
              <P>C. Describe other product-related services (for example, persons who describe optional monthly payment methods via telephone or via automatic account withdrawals, the availability and features of online account access, the availability of 24-hour customer support, or free mobile applications to access account information); or</P>
              <P>D. * * *</P>
              <P>iii.<E T="03">Loan processing.</E>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who, acting on behalf of a loan originator or a creditor:</P>
              <P>A. * * *</P>
              <P>B. * * *</P>
              <P>C. Coordinate consummation of the credit transaction or other aspects of the credit transaction process, including by communicating with a consumer about process deadlines and documents needed at consummation, provided that any communication that includes a discussion about credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics only confirms credit terms already agreed to by the consumer;</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>iv.<E T="03">Underwriting, credit approval, and credit pricing.</E>The definition of loan originator does not include persons who:</P>
              <P>A. * * *</P>
              <P>B. Approve particular credit terms or set particular credit terms available from a creditor to that consumer selected based on the consumer's financial characteristics in offer or counter-offer situations, provided that only a loan originator communicates to or with the consumer regarding these credit terms, an offer, or provides or engages in negotiation, a counter-offer, or approval conditions; or</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>5.<E T="03">Compensation.</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>iv.<E T="03">Amounts for charges for services that are not loan origination activities.</E>
              </P>
              <P>A. * * *</P>
              <P>B. Compensation includes any salaries, commissions, and any financial or similar incentive to an individual loan originator, regardless of whether it is labeled as payment for services that are not loan origination activities.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(a)(1)(i)(B) Employee of a retailer of manufactured homes.</E>
              </P>

              <P>1. The definition of loan originator does not include an employee of a manufactured home retailer that &#x201C;assists&#x201D; a consumer in obtaining or applying for consumer credit as defined in comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">3,</E>provided the employee does not advise the consumer on specific credit terms, or otherwise engage in loan originator activity as defined in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1). The following examples describe activities that, in the absence of other activities, do not define a manufactured home retailer employee as a loan originator:</P>
              <P>i. Generally describing the credit application process to a consumer without advising on credit terms available from a creditor.</P>
              <P>ii. Preparing residential mortgage loan packages, which means compiling and processing loan application materials and supporting documentation, and providing general application instructions to consumers so consumers can complete an application, without interacting or communicating with the consumer regarding transaction terms, but not filling out a consumer's application, inputting the information into an online application or other automated system, or taking information from the consumer over the phone to complete the application.</P>
              <P>iii. Collecting information on behalf of the consumer with regard to a residential mortgage loan. Collecting information &#x201C;on behalf of the consumer&#x201D; would include gathering information or supporting documentation from third parties on behalf of the consumer to provide to the consumer, for the consumer then to provide in the application or for the consumer to submit to the loan originator or creditor.</P>

              <P>iv. Providing or making available general information about creditors or loan originators that may offer financing for manufactured homes in the consumer's general area, when doing so does not otherwise amount to &#x201C;referring&#x201D; as defined in comment 36(a)-1.i.A.<E T="03">1.</E>This includes making available, in a neutral manner, general brochures or information about the different creditors or loan originators that may offer financing to a consumer, but does not include recommending a particular creditor or loan originator or otherwise influencing the consumer's decision.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(b) Scope.</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Scope of coverage.</E>Section 1026.36(c)(1) and (c)(2) applies to closed-end consumer<PRTPAGE P="60446"/>credit transactions secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Section 1026.36(c)(3) applies to a consumer credit transaction, including home equity lines of credit under &#xA7; 1026.40, secured by a consumer's dwelling. Paragraphs (h) and (i) of &#xA7; 1026.36 apply to home equity lines of credit under &#xA7; 1026.40 secured by a consumer's principal dwelling. Paragraphs (d), (e), (f), (g), (h), and (i) of &#xA7; 1026.36 apply to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling. Closed-end consumer credit transactions include transactions secured by first or subordinate liens, and reverse mortgages that are not home equity lines of credit under &#xA7; 1026.40. See &#xA7; 1026.36(b) for additional restrictions on the scope of &#xA7; 1026.36, and &#xA7;&#xA7; 1026.1(c) and 1026.3(a) and corresponding commentary for further discussion of extensions of credit subject to Regulation Z.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(d) Prohibited payments to loan originators.</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(d)(1) Payments based on a term of a transaction.</E>
              </P>
              <P>1. * * *</P>
              <P>ii.<E T="03">Single or multiple transactions.</E>The prohibition on payment and receipt of compensation under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i) encompasses compensation that directly or indirectly is based on the terms of a single transaction of a single individual loan originator, the terms of multiple transactions by that single individual loan originator, or the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. Compensation to an individual loan originator that is based upon profits determined with reference to a mortgage-related business is considered compensation that is based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. For clarification about the exceptions permitting compensation based upon profits determined with reference to mortgage-related business pursuant to either a designated tax-advantaged plan or a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan, see comment 36(d)(1)-3. For clarification about &#x201C;mortgage-related business,&#x201D; see comments 36(d)(1)-3.v.B and -3.v.E.</P>
              <P>A. Assume that a creditor pays a bonus to an individual loan originator out of a bonus pool established with reference to the creditor's profits and the profits are determined with reference to the creditor's revenue from origination of closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by a dwelling. In such instance, the bonus is considered compensation that is based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. Therefore, the bonus is prohibited under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i), unless it is otherwise permitted under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv).</P>

              <P>B. Assume that an individual loan originator's employment contract with a creditor guarantees a quarterly bonus in a specified amount conditioned upon the individual loan originator meeting certain performance benchmarks (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>volume of originations monthly). A bonus paid following the satisfaction of those contractual conditions is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of a transaction by an individual loan originator, the terms of multiple transactions by that individual loan originator, or the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i) as clarified by this comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii, because the creditor is obligated to pay the bonus, in the specified amount, regardless of the terms of transactions of the individual loan originator or multiple individual loan originators and the effect of those terms of multiple transactions on the creditor's profits. Because this type of bonus is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators, as described in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i) (as clarified by this comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii), it is not subject to the 10-percent total compensation limit described in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>).</P>
              <P>iii. * * *</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>D. The fees and charges described above in paragraphs B and C can only be a term of a transaction if the fees or charges are required to be disclosed in the Good Faith Estimate, the HUD-1, or the HUD-1A (and subsequently in any integrated disclosures promulgated by the Bureau under TILA section 105(b) (15 U.S.C. 1604(b)) and RESPA section 4 (12 U.S.C. 2603) as amended by sections 1098 and 1100A of the Dodd-Frank Act).</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>3.<E T="03">Interpretation of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) and (iv).</E>Subject to certain restrictions, &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) and &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) permit contributions to or benefits under designated tax-advantaged plans and compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan even if the contributions, benefits, or compensation, respectively, are based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators.</P>
              <P>i.<E T="03">Designated tax-advantaged plans.</E>Section 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) permits an individual loan originator to receive, and a person to pay, compensation in the form of contributions to a defined contribution plan or benefits under a defined benefit plan provided the plan is a designated tax-advantaged plan (as defined in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii)), even if contributions to or benefits under such plans are directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. In the case of a designated tax-advantaged plan that is a defined contribution plan, &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) does not permit the contribution to be directly or indirectly based on the terms of that individual loan originator's transactions. A defined contribution plan has the meaning set forth in Internal Revenue Code section 414(i), 26 U.S.C. 414(i). A defined benefit plan has the meaning set forth in Internal Revenue Code section 414(j), 26 U.S.C. 414(j).</P>
              <P>ii.<E T="03">Non-deferred profits-based compensation plans.</E>As used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), a &#x201C;non-deferred profits-based compensation plan&#x201D; is any compensation arrangement where an individual loan originator may be paid variable, additional compensation based in whole or in part on the mortgage-related business profits of the person paying the compensation, any affiliate, or a business unit within the organizational structure of the person or the affiliate, as applicable (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>depending on the level within the person's or affiliate's organization at which the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is established). A non-deferred profits-based compensation plan does not include a designated tax-advantaged plan or other forms of deferred compensation that are not designated tax-advantaged plans, such as those created pursuant to Internal Revenue Code section 409A, 26 U.S.C. 409A. Thus, if contributions to or benefits under a designated tax-advantaged plan or compensation under another form of deferred compensation plan are determined with reference to the mortgage-related business profits of the person making the contribution, then the contribution, benefits, or other compensation, as applicable, are not permitted by &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) (although, in the case of contributions to or benefits under a designated tax-advantaged plan, the benefits or contributions may be permitted by &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii)). Under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan, the individual loan originator may, for example, be paid directly in cash, stock, or other non-deferred compensation, and the compensation under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan may be determined by a fixed formula or may be at the discretion of the person (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>the person may elect not to pay compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan in a given year), provided the compensation is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of the individual loan originator's transactions. As used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) and this commentary, non-deferred profits-based compensation plans include, without limitation, bonus pools, profits pools, bonus plans, and profit-sharing plans. Compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan could include, without limitation, annual or periodic bonuses, or awards of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prizes or incentives where the bonuses, contributions, or awards are determined with reference to the profits of the person, business unit, or affiliate, as applicable. As used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) and this commentary, a business unit is a division, department, or segment within the overall organizational structure of the person or the person's affiliate that performs discrete business functions and that the person or the affiliate treats separately for accounting or other organizational purposes. For example, a creditor that pays its individual loan originators bonuses at the end of a calendar year based on the creditor's average net return on assets for the calendar year is operating a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv). A bonus that is paid to an individual loan originator from a source other than a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan (or a deferred compensation plan where the bonus is determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits), such as a retention bonus budgeted for in advance or a performance bonus paid out of a bonus pool set aside at the beginning of the<PRTPAGE P="60447"/>company's annual accounting period as part of the company's operating budget, does not violate the prohibition on payment of compensation based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i), as clarified by comment 36(d)(1)-1.ii; therefore, &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) does not apply to such bonuses.</P>
              <P>iii.<E T="03">Compensation that is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators.</E>The compensation arrangements addressed in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii) and (iv) are permitted even if they are directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators. See comment 36(d)(1)-1 for additional interpretation. If a loan originator organization's revenues are exclusively derived from transactions subject to &#xA7; 1026.36(d) (whether paid by creditors, consumers, or both) and that loan originator organization pays its individual loan originators a bonus under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan, the bonus is not directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple transactions by multiple individual loan originators if &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i) is otherwise complied with.</P>
              <P>iv.<E T="03">Compensation based on terms of an individual loan originator's transactions.</E>Under both &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iii), with regard to contributions made to a defined contribution plan that is a designated tax-advantaged plan, and &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A), with regard to compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan, the payment of compensation to an individual loan originator may not be directly or indirectly based on the terms of that individual loan originator's transaction or transactions. Consequently, for example, where an individual loan originator makes loans that vary in their interest rate spread, the compensation payment may not take into account the average interest rate spread on the individual loan originator's transactions during the relevant calendar year.</P>
              <P>v.<E T="03">Compensation under non-deferred profits-based compensation plans.</E>Assuming that the conditions in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A) are met, &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) permits certain compensation to an individual loan originator under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan. Specifically, if the compensation is determined with reference to the profits of the person from mortgage-related business, compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is permitted provided the compensation does not, in the aggregate, exceed 10 percent of the individual loan originator's total compensation corresponding to the time period for which compensation under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is paid. The compensation restrictions under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) are sometimes referred to in this commentary as the &#x201C;10-percent total compensation limit&#x201D; or the &#x201C;10-percent limit.&#x201D;</P>
              <P>A.<E T="03">Total compensation.</E>For purposes of &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>), the individual loan originator's total compensation consists of the sum total of: (1) All wages and tips reportable for Medicare tax purposes in box 5 on IRS form W-2 (or, if the individual loan originator is an independent contractor, reportable compensation on IRS form 1099-MISC) that are actually paid during the relevant time period (regardless of when the wages and tips are earned), except for any compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan that is earned during a different time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.C); (2) at the election of the person paying the compensation, all contributions that are actually made during the relevant time period by the creditor or loan originator organization to the individual loan originator's accounts in designated tax-advantaged plans that are defined contribution plans (regardless of when the contributions are earned); and (3) at the election of the person paying the compensation, all compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan that is earned during the relevant time period, regardless of whether the compensation is actually paid during that time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.C). If an individual loan originator has some compensation that is reportable on the W-2 and some that is reportable on the 1099-MISC, the total compensation is the sum total of what is reportable on each of the two forms.</P>
              <P>B.<E T="03">Profits of the Person.</E>Under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), a plan is a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan if compensation is paid, based in whole or in part, on the profits of the person paying the compensation. As used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv), &#x201C;profits of the person&#x201D; include, as applicable depending on where the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is set, the profits of the person, the business unit to which the individual loan originators are assigned for accounting or other organizational purposes, or any affiliate of the person. Profits from mortgage-related business are profits determined with reference to revenue generated from transactions subject to &#xA7; 1026.36(d). Pursuant to &#xA7; 1026.36(b) and comment 36(b)-1, &#xA7; 1026.36(d) applies to closed-end consumer credit transactions secured by dwellings. This revenue includes, without limitation, and as applicable based on the particular sources of revenue of the person, business unit, or affiliate, origination fees and interest associated with dwelling-secured transactions for which individual loan originators working for the person were loan originators, income from servicing of such transactions, and proceeds of secondary market sales of such transactions. If the amount of the individual loan originator's compensation under non-deferred profits-based compensation plans paid for a time period does not, in the aggregate, exceed 10 percent of the individual loan originator's total compensation corresponding to the same time period, compensation under non-deferred profits-based compensation plans may be paid under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) regardless of whether or not it was determined with reference to the profits of the person from mortgage-related business.</P>
              <P>C.<E T="03">Time period for which the compensation under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is paid and to which the total compensation corresponds.</E>Under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>), determination of whether payment of compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan complies with the 10-percent limit requires a calculation of the ratio of the compensation under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>the compensation subject to the 10-percent limit) and the total compensation corresponding to the relevant time period. For compensation subject to the 10-percent limit, the relevant time period is the time period for which a person makes reference to profits in determining the compensation (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>when the compensation was earned). It does not matter whether the compensation is actually paid during that particular time period. For total compensation, the relevant time period is the same time period, but only certain types of compensation may be included in the total compensation amount for that time period (see comment 36(d)(1)-3.v.A). For example, assume that during calendar year 2014 a creditor pays an individual loan originator compensation in the following amounts: $80,000 in commissions based on the individual loan originator's performance and volume of loans generated during the calendar year; and $10,000 in an employer contribution to a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan on behalf of the individual loan originator. The creditor desires to pay the individual loan originator a year-end bonus of $10,000 under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan. The commissions are paid and employer contributions to the designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan are made during calendar year 2014, but the year-end bonus will be paid in January 2015. For purposes of the 10-percent limit, the year-end bonus is counted toward the 10-percent limit for calendar year 2014, even though it is not actually paid until 2015. Therefore, for calendar year 2014 the individual loan originator's compensation that is subject to the 10-percent limit would be $10,000 (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>the year-end bonus) and the total compensation would be $100,000 (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>the sum of the commissions, the designated tax-advantaged plan contribution (assuming the creditor elects to include it in total compensation for calendar year 2014), and the bonus (assuming the creditor elects to include it in total compensation for calendar year 2014)); the bonus would be permissible under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) because it does not exceed 10 percent of total compensation. The determination of total compensation corresponding to 2014 also would not take into account any compensation subject to the 10-percent limit that is actually paid in 2014 but is earned during a different calendar year (<E T="03">e.g.,</E>an annual bonus determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits for calendar year 2013 that is paid in January 2014). If the employer contribution to the designated tax-advantaged plan is earned in 2014 but actually made in 2015, however, it may not be included in total compensation for 2014. A company, business unit, or affiliate, as applicable, may pay compensation subject to the 10-percent limit during different time periods falling within its annual accounting period for keeping records and reporting income and expenses,<PRTPAGE P="60448"/>which may be a calendar year or a fiscal year depending on the annual accounting period. In such instances, however, the 10-percent limit applies both as to each time period and cumulatively as to the annual accounting period. For example, assume that a creditor uses a calendar-year accounting period. If the creditor pays an individual loan originator a bonus at the end of each quarter under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan, the payment of each quarterly bonus is subject to the 10-percent limit measured with respect to each quarter. The creditor can also pay an annual bonus under the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan that does not exceed the difference of 10 percent of the individual loan originator's total compensation corresponding to the calendar year and the aggregate amount of the quarterly bonuses.</P>
              <P>D.<E T="03">Awards of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prizes or incentives.</E>If any compensation paid to an individual loan originator under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv) consists of an award of merchandise, services, trips, or similar prize or incentive, the cash value of the award is factored into the calculation of the 10-percent total compensation limit. For example, during a given calendar year, individual loan originator A and individual loan originator B are each employed by a creditor and paid $40,000 in salary, and $45,000 in commissions. The creditor also contributes $5,000 to a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan for each individual loan originator during that calendar year, which the creditor elects to include in the total compensation amount. Neither individual loan originator is paid any other form of compensation by the creditor. In December of the calendar year, the creditor rewards both individual loan originators for their performance during the calendar year out of a bonus pool established with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit. Individual loan originator A is paid a $10,000 cash bonus, meaning that individual loan originator A's total compensation is $100,000 (assuming the creditor elects to include the bonus in the total compensation amount). Individual loan originator B is paid a $7,500 cash bonus and awarded a vacation package with a cash value of $3,000, meaning that individual loan originator B's total compensation is $100,500 (assuming the creditor elects to include the reward in the total compensation amount). Under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>), individual loan originator A's $10,000 bonus is permissible because the bonus would not constitute more than 10 percent of individual loan originator A's total compensation for the calendar year. The creditor may not pay individual loan originator B the $7,500 bonus and award the vacation package, however, because the total value of the bonus and the vacation package would be $10,500, which is greater than 10 percent (10.45 percent) of individual loan originator B's total compensation for the calendar year. One way to comply with &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) would be if the amount of the bonus were reduced to $7,000 or less or the vacation package were structured such that its cash value would be $2,500 or less.</P>
              <P>E.<E T="03">Compensation determined only with reference to non-mortgage-related business profits.</E>Compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is not subject to the 10-percent total compensation limit under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) if the non-deferred profits-based compensation plan is determined with reference only to profits from business other than mortgage-related business, as determined in accordance with reasonable accounting principles. Reasonable accounting principles reflect an accurate allocation of revenues, expenses, profits, and losses among the person, any affiliate of the person, and any business units within the person or affiliates, and are consistent with the accounting principles applied by the person, the affiliate, or the business unit with respect to, as applicable, its internal budgeting and auditing functions and external reporting requirements. Examples of external reporting and filing requirements that may be applicable to creditors and loan originator organizations are Federal income tax filings, Federal securities law filings, or quarterly reporting of income, expenses, loan origination activity, and other information required by government-sponsored enterprises. As used in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>), profits means positive profits or losses avoided or mitigated.</P>
              <P>F.<E T="03">Additional examples.</E> <E T="03">1.</E>Assume that, during a given calendar year, a loan originator organization pays an individual loan originator employee $40,000 in salary and $125,000 in commissions, and makes a contribution of $15,000 to the individual loan originator's 401(k) plan. At the end of the year, the loan originator organization wishes to pay the individual loan originator a bonus based on a formula involving a number of performance metrics, to be paid out of a profit pool established at the level of the company but that is determined in part with reference to the profits of the company's mortgage origination unit. Assume that the loan originator organization derives revenues from sources other than transactions covered by &#xA7; 1026.36(d). In this example, the performance bonus would be directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple individual loan originators' transactions as described in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(i), because it is being determined with reference to profits from mortgage-related business. Assume, furthermore, that the loan originator organization elects to include the bonus in the total compensation amount for the calendar year. Thus, the bonus is permissible under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) if it does not exceed 10 percent of the loan originator's total compensation, which in this example consists of the individual loan originator's salary and commissions, the contribution to the 401(k) plan (if the loan originator organization elects to include the contribution in the total compensation amount), and the performance bonus. Therefore, if the loan originator organization elects to include the 401(k) contribution in total compensation for these purposes, the loan originator organization may pay the individual loan originator a performance bonus of up to $20,000 (<E T="03">i.e.,</E>10 percent of $200,000 in total compensation). If the loan originator organization does not include the 401(k) contribution in calculating total compensation, or the 401(k) contribution is actually made in January of the following calendar year (in which case it cannot be included in total compensation for the initial calendar year), the bonus may be up to $18,333.33. If the loan originator organization includes neither the 401(k) contribution nor the performance bonus in the total compensation amount, the bonus may not exceed $16,500.</P>
              <P>
                <E T="03">2.</E>Assume that the compensation during a given calendar year of an individual loan originator employed by a creditor consists of only salary and commissions, and the individual loan originator does not participate in a designated tax-advantaged defined contribution plan. Assume further that the creditor uses a calendar-year accounting period. At the end of the calendar year, the creditor pays the individual loan originator two bonuses: A &#x201C;performance&#x201D; bonus based on the individual loan originator's aggregate loan volume for a calendar year that is paid out of a bonus pool determined with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit, and a year-end &#x201C;holiday&#x201D; bonus in the same amount to all company employees that is paid out of a company-wide bonus pool. Because the performance bonus is paid out of a bonus pool that is determined with reference to the profits of the mortgage origination business unit, it is compensation that is determined with reference to mortgage-related business profits, and the bonus is therefore subject to the 10-percent total compensation limit. If the company-wide bonus pool from which the &#x201C;holiday&#x201D; bonus is paid is derived in part from profits of the creditor's mortgage origination business unit, then the combination of the &#x201C;holiday&#x201D; bonus and the performance bonus is subject to the 10-percent total compensation limit. The &#x201C;holiday&#x201D; bonus is not subject to the 10-percent total compensation limit if the bonus pool is determined with reference only to the profits of business units other than the mortgage origination business unit, as determined in accordance with reasonable accounting principles. If the &#x201C;performance&#x201D; bonus and the &#x201C;holiday&#x201D; bonus in the aggregate do not exceed 10 percent of the individual loan originator's total compensation, the bonuses may be paid under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) without the necessity of determining from which bonus pool they were paid or whether they were determined with reference to the profits of the creditor's mortgage origination business unit.</P>
              <P>G.<E T="03">Reasonable reliance by individual loan originator on accounting or statement by person paying compensation.</E>An individual loan originator is deemed to comply with its obligations regarding receipt of compensation under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) if the individual loan originator relies in good faith on an accounting or a statement provided by the person who determined the individual loan originator's compensation under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan pursuant to &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) and where the statement or accounting is provided within a reasonable time period following the person's determination.<PRTPAGE P="60449"/>
              </P>
              <P>vi.<E T="03">Individual loan originators who originate ten or fewer transactions.</E>Assuming that the conditions in &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(A) are met, &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>) permits compensation to an individual loan originator under a non-deferred profits-based compensation plan even if the payment or contribution is directly or indirectly based on the terms of multiple individual loan originators' transactions if the individual is a loan originator (as defined in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(i)) for ten or fewer consummated transactions during the 12-month period preceding the compensation determination. For example, assume a loan originator organization employs two individual loan originators who originate transactions subject to &#xA7; 1026.36 during a given calendar year. Both employees are individual loan originators as defined in &#xA7; 1026.36(a)(1)(ii), but only one of them (individual loan originator B) acts as a loan originator in the normal course of business, while the other (individual loan originator A) is called upon to do so only occasionally and regularly performs other duties (such as serving as a manager). In January of the following calendar year, the loan originator organization formally determines the financial performance of its mortgage business for the prior calendar year. Based on that determination, the loan originator organization on February 1 decides to pay a bonus to the individual loan originators out of a company bonus pool. Assume that, between February 1 of the prior calendar year and January 31 of the current calendar year, individual loan originator A was the loan originator for eight consummated transactions, and individual loan originator B was the loan originator for 15 consummated transactions. The loan originator organization may award the bonus to individual loan originator A under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>). The loan originator organization may not award the bonus to individual loan originator B relying on the exception under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">2</E>) because it would not apply, although it could award a bonus pursuant to the 10-percent total compensation limit under &#xA7; 1026.36(d)(1)(iv)(B)(<E T="03">1</E>) if the requirements of that provision are complied with.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>6.<E T="03">Periodic changes in loan originator compensation and terms of transactions.</E>Section 1026.36 does not limit a creditor or other person from periodically revising the compensation it agrees to pay a loan originator. However, the revised compensation arrangement must not result in payments to the loan originator that are based on the terms of a credit transaction. A creditor or other person might periodically review factors such as loan performance, transaction volume, as well as current market conditions for loan originator compensation, and prospectively revise the compensation it agrees to pay to a loan originator. For example, assume that during the first six months of the year, a creditor pays $3,000 to a particular loan originator for each loan delivered, regardless of the terms of the transaction. After considering the volume of business produced by that loan originator, the creditor could decide that as of July 1, it will pay $3,250 for each loan delivered by that particular loan originator, regardless of the terms of the transaction. No violation occurs even if the loans made by the creditor after July 1 generally carry a higher interest rate than loans made before that date, to reflect the higher compensation.</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">36(f) Loan originator qualification requirements.</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">Paragraph 36(f)(3).</E>
              </P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">Paragraph 36(f)(3)(i).</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Criminal and credit histories.</E>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(i) requires the loan originator organization to obtain, for any of its individual loan originator employees who is not required to be licensed and is not licensed as a loan originator pursuant to the SAFE Act, a criminal background check, a credit report, and information related to any administrative, civil, or criminal determinations by any government jurisdiction. The requirement applies to individual loan originator employees who were hired on or after January 1, 2014 (or whom the loan originator organization hired before this date but for whom there were no applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire or before January 1, 2014, used to screen the individual). A credit report may be obtained directly from a consumer reporting agency or through a commercial service. A loan originator organization with access to the NMLSR can meet the requirement for the criminal background check by reviewing any criminal background check it receives upon compliance with the requirement in 12 CFR 1007.103(d)(1) and can meet the requirement to obtain information related to any administrative, civil, or criminal determinations by any government jurisdiction by obtaining the information through the NMLSR. Loan originator organizations that do not have access to these items through the NMLSR may obtain them by other means. For example, a criminal background check may be obtained from a law enforcement agency or commercial service. Information on any past administrative, civil, or criminal findings (such as from disciplinary or enforcement actions) may be obtained from the individual loan originator.</P>
              <P>2.<E T="03">Retroactive obtaining of information not required.</E>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(i) does not require the loan originator organization to obtain the covered information for an individual whom the loan originator organization hired as a loan originator before January 1, 2014, and screened under applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire. However, if the individual subsequently ceases to be employed as a loan originator by that loan originator organization, and later resumes employment as a loan originator by that loan originator organization (or any other loan originator organization), the loan originator organization is subject to the requirements of &#xA7; 1026.36(f)(3)(i).</P>
              <STARS/>
              <P>
                <E T="03">Paragraph 36(f)(3)(ii).</E>
              </P>
              <P>1.<E T="03">Scope of review.</E>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(ii) requires the loan originator organization to review the information that it obtains under &#xA7; 1026.36(f)(3)(i) and other reasonably available information to determine whether the individual loan originator meets the standards in &#xA7; 1026.36(f)(3)(ii). Other reasonably available information includes any information the loan originator organization has obtained or would obtain as part of a reasonably prudent hiring process, including information obtained from application forms, candidate interviews, other reliable information and evidence provided by a candidate, and reference checks. The requirement applies to individual loan originator employees who were hired on or after January 1, 2014 (or whom the loan originator organization hired before this date but for whom there were no applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire or before January 1, 2014, used to screen the individual).</P>
              <P>2.<E T="03">Retroactive determinations not required.</E>Section 1026.36(f)(3)(ii) does not require the loan originator organization to review the covered information and make the required determinations for an individual whom the loan originator organization hired as a loan originator on or before January 1, 2014 and screened under applicable statutory or regulatory background standards in effect at the time of hire. However, if the individual subsequently ceases to be employed as a loan originator by that loan originator organization, and later resumes employment as a loan originator by that loan originator organization (or any other loan originator organization), the loan originator organization employing the individual is subject to the requirements of &#xA7; 1026.36(f)(3)(ii).</P>
              <STARS/>
            </EXTRACT>
          </REGTEXT>
          <SIG>
            <DATED>Dated: September 12, 2013.</DATED>
            <NAME>Richard Cordray,</NAME>
            <TITLE>Director, Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.</TITLE>
          </SIG>
        </SUPLINF>
        <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2013-22752 Filed 9-19-13; 4:15 pm]</FRDOC>
        <BILCOD>BILLING CODE 4810-AM-P</BILCOD>
      </RULE>
